<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The catalogue of the chancellors of England, the lord keepers of the Great Seale: and the lord treasurers of England With a collection of divers that have been masters of the Rolles. By I.P. Summerset herald.</title>
            <author>Philipot, John, 1589?-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849870</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15042</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09564)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1252:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The catalogue of the chancellors of England, the lord keepers of the Great Seale: and the lord treasurers of England With a collection of divers that have been masters of the Rolles. By I.P. Summerset herald.</title>
                  <author>Philipot, John, 1589?-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 78, 90-92, [1], 79-82, [2]; 56, 67-85, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Tho. Cotes, and are to be sold by Andrew Crooke in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Philipot.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Lord Chancellor's Dept. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Chronology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Officials and employees --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CATALOGVE OF THE CHANCELLORS OF ENGLAND, THE LORD Keepers of the Great Seale: AND THE LORD TREASV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of England.</p>
            <p>With a Collection of divers that have beene Maſters of the Rolles.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. P. Summerſet Herald.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Tho. Cotes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Andrew Crooke</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>CRESCAM UT PROSIM</q>
                  <q>CONSTANTER ET PRUDENTER</q>
                  <p>The Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Alex Campbell of Ceſnok one of the Senators of the Colledge of Justice and one of the Lords of Her Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> most Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> Pray Counſell &amp; Exchequer &amp;c: 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7</p>
                  <figDesc>bookplate of Sir Alex Campbell</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable and excellent Lord, <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> Primer Earle and Earle <hi>Marſhall</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Baron <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Mowbray, Segrave, Brewes of Gower, Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allan, Clun, Oſwalderſtree, Maltravers</hi> and <hi>Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock,</hi> Iuſtice in Eyre of all the Kings <hi>Forreſts Parkes</hi> and Chaces beyond the River of Trent, Lievetenant generall to his Majeſtie in the Provinces of <hi>Norfolke, Suſſex, Surrey, Northumberland, Weſtmerland</hi> and <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> of the Privy Councell to his Maieſtie in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have received many encouragements (by Friends that have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed theſe Collections) to render them to the publicke, which cannot bee done without
<pb facs="tcp:15042:3"/>
your Lordſhips approbation and permisſion to the Preſſe. The Catalogues of the great officers in <hi>France</hi> (long ſince printed) have offorded much contentment and do worthily preſerve the memory of ſuch as merited in thoſe places and their qualities. And as I have no other but the ſame end in the publiſhing of theſe. So I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſelfe with an humble hope that it will give no diſcontentment. The incouragements your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath conferred up on the office of Armes in generall &amp; my ſelfe in particular with a bountifull hand may give your Lordſhip juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to expect ſome fruite of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours: If theſe may paſſe in that eſtimate, but for bloſſomes it will
<pb facs="tcp:15042:3"/>
be more then they demerite. And if your Lordſhip ſhall conceive them worthy to bee communicated to the world, I moſt humbly crave leave that they may paſſe under Dedication to your Lordſhip, which grace and favour will give them life and acceptation, and very much incourage and comfort</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Moſt noble Lord, To Your thrice humble and moſt obliged ſervant, IOHN PHILIPOT.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Summerſet Herald.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:4"/>
            <head>To my very loving friends, the Maſter and Wardens of the Company of <hi>Stationers,</hi> at <hi>Stationers</hi> Hall in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> theſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et the Catalogue of the Chancellors of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Lord Keepers of the great Seale, and Lord high Treaſurers of <hi>England,</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>Iohn Philipot</hi> Summerſet, be printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Arundell <hi>and</hi> Surry.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Arundell Houſe</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 16. of</hi> March, <hi>1635.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>CANDIDE ET CONSTANTER</q>
                  <figDesc>Coventry family coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>MErcedem meritis poſtponis, legibus aurum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Quod nunc prodigii pondus &amp; inſtar habet.</l>
               <l>Conſilio multis, opibus ſuccurris egenti,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:5"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Catalogue or Series of the Chancellors of <hi>England</hi> hath beene with much care and diligence laboured by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Glover, Somerſet</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld of Armes, and after him by <hi>Francis Thinne, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter</hi> Herauld; whoſe M. S Collections J have by me, and in them a thankfull commemoration is made of Mr. <hi>Thomas Talbots</hi> kinde aſsiſtance, hee being Clerke of the Records in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> where the Charters and their Dates that afford the exacteſt teſtimonies of them are to be found for many Ages paſt. So that J ſhall not neede to cite the vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and proofes at large. Neither will I be ſo falſe to my ſelfe or my Reader, as to conceale that the worthy and reverend Antiquarie S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Spil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Knight, in his Gloſſary hath ſummarily menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned them: The nature of the Office is moſt accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed by him in that worke, and alſo by <hi>Mr.
<pb facs="tcp:15042:6"/>
William Camden, Clarenceux</hi> King of Armes, in his Hiſtory of Great Brittaine, in the deſcription and definition of the ſeverall Courts of Juſtice in this Kingdome, to which J referre thoſe that deſire to be particularly informed in that kinde. <hi>Pollidor Virgill</hi> would perſwade us the Office and name of Chancellor was not known in this Kingdome till after the Norman Conqueſt, and the Author of the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Biſhops, is poſitive in that opinion, ſpeaking of <hi>Swithen</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> (the opinion of whoſe piety procured him the title of a Saint.) But the contrary is moſt cleere and evident as by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities hereafter mentioned will appeare, to which I referre my Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catalogue_of_Chancellors">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15042:6"/>
            <head>A CATALOGVE OF THE CHANCELLORS of England from the time of the <hi>SAXON</hi> Kings.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rketill</hi> was Chancellor to King <hi>Ethelbald,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his reigne in the yeere 718. this <hi>Turketill</hi> gave ſix Mannors to the Abbey of <hi>Croiland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Swithen,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> was Chancellor and chiefe of Councell to the great Monarch King <hi>Egbert,</hi> who began his reigne about the yeere 802.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15042:7"/>
               <hi>Wolfinus,</hi> was Chancellor to King <hi>Athel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> who began his raigne in the yeare 924. This King inriched the Monaſtary of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesbury</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> with large and ample indowments, and beſtowed great immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities upon the Towne. And in the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and grant of thoſe Liberties; ths <hi>Wolfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is a witneſſe with the title of Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turketill,</hi> was Chancellor to the ſaid King <hi>Athelſtone,</hi> and ſo continued under King <hi>Edmund,</hi> who began his raigne in the yeare 940. and after the death of King <hi>Edmund,</hi> he was Chancellor to King <hi>Edred,</hi> the ſpace of two yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adulthus,</hi> Chancellor to King <hi>Edgar;</hi> who began his raigne in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 959. Of this man ſpeaketh <hi>Hugo Petro Burgenſis,</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> calleth this <hi>Adulph, Cancellarium &amp; Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grammatum,</hi> Chancellor or chiefe Secretary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſius</hi> or <hi>Aelſius,</hi> the ſecond Abbat of <hi>Elie,</hi> Chancellor to King <hi>Ethelred,</hi> who began his raigne in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 979. This man being by <hi>Ethelwold</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> conſecrated
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15042:7"/>
Abbat, by the appointment of the ſaid King <hi>Ethelred,</hi> or <hi>Egelred,</hi> and being then Abbat of <hi>Elie,</hi> when <hi>Ethelred</hi> gave out his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that the Abbat of <hi>Elie,</hi> ſhould then, and for ever be Chancellor, I doubt not to place him here amongſt the Chancellors, the proofe of which matter I have here <hi>verbatim</hi> ſet downe out of the ſecond booke of the hiſtory of <hi>Elie. Statuit</hi> (which was <hi>Ethelred) atque conceſſit quatenus eccleſiam de Elie, ex tunc &amp; ſemper in regis curia cancellarij ageret dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quod etiam alijs, ſancti videlicet, Auguſtini &amp; Glaſconiae eccleſijs conſtituit, ut Abbates iſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum caenobiorum vicisſim adſignatis ſuccedendo, temporibus annum trifarie dividerent, cum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarijs, &amp; caeteris ornamentis miniſtrando, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leofricus Bathonicus</hi> Chancellor to <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1045. and ſome yeares before, this man was Biſhop of <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> in <hi>Cornewall,</hi> which ſee was after tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated to <hi>Exceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wifinus,</hi> or <hi>Wolfinus,</hi> Chancellor to <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> in the latter end of the ſaid yeare 1045, being the third yeare of his raigne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15042:8"/>
               <hi>Reſenbaldus,</hi> or <hi>Rembaldus,</hi> (for I take them both by many and ancient authorities to be all one man,) was Chancellor to <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> and Seale-bearer, witneſſe amongſt others, to many Deedes, which I have ſeene of the <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> ſome dated in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1066 and ſome otherwiſe, he was buried at <hi>Ciren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> or <hi>Ciceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mauricius,</hi> Chancellor to <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1067. being the firſt, and part of the ſecond yeare, of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oſmundus,</hi> after Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> Chancellor to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1067, and after in the yeere 1075, about <hi>Anno</hi> 9 of the Kings reigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arfaſtus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Helmane,</hi> who tranſlated his See from <hi>Helmane</hi> to <hi>Thetford,</hi> was Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1068, being in the ſecond and third yeere of the Conqueror, and alſo in the yeere 1077, being about <hi>Anno</hi> 10. of <hi>William</hi> the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, <hi>Mauricius</hi> was againe Chancellor.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15042:8"/>
               <hi>Hirmanus,</hi> that was firſt made Biſhop of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> or <hi>Wilton,</hi> and tranſlated his See from <hi>Wilton</hi> to <hi>Shirborne,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Sarum;</hi> He is that <hi>Hirmanus,</hi> which (I ſuppoſe) was Chancellor to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, and called <hi>Hirmanus,</hi> and that wrote the life and miracles of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edmund</hi> King of the Eaſtangles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Welſon,</hi> or <hi>Wilſon,</hi> borne of a Noble houſe, Chaplain and Chancellor to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, (as hath <hi>Robertus Montenſis</hi>) ſucceeded <hi>Arfaſtus</hi> in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Thetford,</hi> to whom by the gift of <hi>William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,</hi> ſucceeded in that See <hi>Herbertus Loſinga</hi> Abbat of <hi>Ramſey,</hi> which tranſlated the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops See to <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Gifford,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> was Chancellor in the time of the Conqueror, and of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Henry,</hi> who made him Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1100, and was conſecrated in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1107, though it ſeemeth that <hi>Robert Bluet</hi> came in place of this <hi>William Gifford,</hi> removed about the fourth yeere of the ſame <hi>Rufus,</hi> from his Office of Chancellorſhip, (as I ſuppoſe will bee well
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15042:9"/>
prooved,) but after placed againe in that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Of the death of this <hi>William</hi> is much contrariety; for <hi>Matthew Weſtminſter,</hi> placed it three ſeverall yeeres, <hi>viz</hi> in <hi>Annis</hi> 28 <hi>&amp;</hi> 29, <hi>Henry</hi> 1, and againe in the yeere of Chriſt, 1142, being the ſeaventh yeere of King <hi>Stephen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Bluet, Bloit,</hi> or <hi>Bloſcit,</hi> made Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1090. being <hi>Anno</hi> 4. of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> he was made Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1092. but as it appeareth by ſome authority, that I have ſeene he did exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that Office, being Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> he dyed at <hi>Woodstocke,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1123. being about the 23. yeare of the raigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, whoſe Epitaph <hi>Henry Huntington</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citeth in this manner.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Pontificum Robertus honor, quem ſama ſuperſtes</l>
               <l>Perpetuare dabit, nec obiturus obit,</l>
               <l>Hic humilis, dives (res mira,) potens, pius ultor,</l>
               <l>Compatiens, mitis, quum pateretur erat,</l>
               <l>Noluit eſſe ſuis dominus, ſtuduit pater eſſe,</l>
               <l>Semper in adverſis, murus, &amp; arma ſuis,</l>
               <l>Jn decima Jani mendacis ſomnia mundi</l>
               <l>Liquit, &amp; evigilans vera perhennè vidit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15042:9"/>
               <hi>Ranulphus</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the time of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> which might be that man, which was after Chancellor, in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Waldricus</hi> Ch ncellor to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1103. being <hi>Anno</hi> 3. of his raigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Gifford,</hi> aforeſaid was againe Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herbertus,</hi> Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 4. <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1104. as appeareth by an Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nymall pamphlet in written hand, of whom I am not yet reſolved, whether this were <hi>Herbertus Loſinga,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> or noe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> whom <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, called a meet Chaplaine to ſerve ſouldiers, was Chancellor to King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1101. being the firſt yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1107. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſeaventh yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choſen Biſhop, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1102. and conſecrated in the yeare 1107.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galfridus Rufus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to a Deed, wherein <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15042:10"/>
to the priory of Chriſt church, a peece of ground without Aldgate, called <hi>Knighton guild,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Geofry Chancellor, Geofry Clinton,</hi> and <hi>William Clinton,</hi> hee was Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 22. <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and ſo untill <hi>Anno</hi> 33. <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and then was made Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> which <hi>Geofry</hi> dyed about the yeare 1141.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robertus Ranulphus,</hi> called by <hi>Matthew Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, Ranulphus</hi> Chancellor to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Richard</hi> the Chaplaine, keeper of the great Seale, being at one time. This <hi>Ranulph</hi> was Chancellor in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1116. being the ſixteenth of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, In which Office I ſuppoſe that he continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1123. being in <hi>Anno</hi> 23, of the ſaid King, In which yeare this Chancellor, (for ſo is he then called) fell from his Horſe, and brake his necke on an hill, not far from <hi>Dunſtable,</hi> where the King kept his Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richardus Capellanus,</hi> was keeper of the Seale under this <hi>Ranulph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reginald</hi> Chancellor to King <hi>Henry</hi> the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15042:10"/>
firſt, (as <hi>Leland</hi> hath ſet him downe,) wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in this ſort, in his notes of <hi>Montacute</hi> Abbey, <hi>Reginaldus Cancellarius,</hi> ſo named (belike) of his Office, he was a man of great fame, about King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, hee fell to Religion, and was Prior of <hi>Montacute,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged it with great buildings, &amp; poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas,</hi> Chancellor after this <hi>Regnaild,</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to a Charter of the Church of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> againe Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, in the latter end of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and in the begining of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1136, which <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, dyed in the yeare 1135, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 35, of his raigne. This <hi>Roger</hi> died in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1139, being about the 4 yeer of King <hi>Stephen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Godfrey,</hi> Chancellor to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, (as I gather out of <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> in the life of <hi>William Corbel,</hi> or <hi>Corbris</hi>) the 36 Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to which dignity this <hi>William</hi> was advanced in <hi>Anno</hi> 23, <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1123, of which <hi>Godfrey,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Matthew</hi> further writeth in this ſort, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> the Archbiſhop, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from Rome with the Pall. <hi>Deinde A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrum
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15042:11"/>
Lincolnienſem epiſcopum Cantuariae, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridum Regni Cancellarium, Bathonienſem epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum Londini conſecravit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> (as may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort gathered out of <hi>Wilhelmus Paruus, lib:</hi> 1, <hi>cap.</hi> 6. being Coſin or Nephew to <hi>Roger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) was Chancellor, the words of which <hi>Wilhelmus Paruus</hi> be theſe. <hi>Eodem</hi> (that was to King <hi>Stephen) quoque ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limato in regem, ſe</hi> (that was <hi>Roger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury) talem exhibuit, ut obſequiorum gratia praeclaram apud illum habere fiduciam videretur. Tantis ille beneficijs ingratus, &amp; in ipſum epiſcopum, (cujus opera nunquam epiſcopalia fuere) ultor divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus ordinatus, eundem tanquam exigui hominem momenti primo carcerati cuſtodia, poſtmodum etiam ſibi inopia, &amp; nepoti ejus (qui Cacellarius fuerat regis) intentato ſupplicio ita coarctavit, ut duo illa praeclara caſtella</hi> (which were the caſtles of Viſe, otherwiſe called the deviſes, and the caſtle of <hi>Shirborne) in quibus theſauri ejus erant repoſiti reſignaret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in the time of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> but I find not in what yeare, becauſe the Charter is without date, neither
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15042:11"/>
can I learne what he was, becauſe I know not his ſurname.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip,</hi> Chancellor to King <hi>Stephen,</hi> about the fourth yeare of his raigne, being in <hi>Anno dom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1139. witneſſe to many Deeds, which King <hi>Stephen</hi> made to the Monkes of <hi>Elie,</hi> and to <hi>Nigellus</hi> the Biſhop of that See.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reinold</hi> Abbat of <hi>Walden,</hi> whom I have ſeene in one anonymall briefe Chronicle, <hi>M, S<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to be termed Chancellor, but in what time he lived, or what other name he had, I doe not yet know, but by the courſe of the hiſtory, much about this time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> made Chancellor, (as ſome write) in the firſt yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, others ſay in the fourth yeare, but the beſt authours agree, that he gave over the Seale in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1162, being in the eight yeare of the victorious Prince, King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, againſt the will of the Prince, he dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1170.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ralphe Warnevile</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Roane,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15042:12"/>
and Treaſurer of the Church of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was made Chancellor about the yeare 1173, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Anno</hi> 8, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, Of this man ſpeaketh <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> and <hi>Matthew Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walterus de Conſtantijs,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom,</hi> 1182, from whence he was advanced in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1184, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 31 <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arch-biſhopricke of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geofry,</hi> the baſtard ſonne to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, after he had ſurrendred the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> whereof he was never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate Biſhop, but kept the place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the revenues, was made Chancellor much about <hi>Anno</hi> 26, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1181.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Longchampe,</hi> the proud Biſhop of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> Legat of <hi>England,</hi> for the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> cheife Iuſtice of the South, and Weſt, parts of <hi>England,</hi> Deputy of that part of the Realm, when <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, went to the warres of the holy Land, was made Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 1 <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, being in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15042:12"/>
1191, of the ſumptuous feaſt, of whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thronization, thus writeth <hi>Ferthulphus,</hi> or <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culphus,</hi> by the way of compariſon,
<q>
                  <l>Praeviſis alijs, Elienſia festa videre,</l>
                  <l>Eſt quaſi praeviſa noste videre diem.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He dyed in the yeare of Chriſt, 1197, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Abbey of <hi>Pimie;</hi> being of the Charterhouſe order, about which time in <hi>Anno</hi> 6, <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, there was a Vice-chancellor called <hi>Malus Catulus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> Deane of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> was Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>England,</hi> being elected Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> in the third Ides of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 9 <hi>Richard</hi> 1, Of whom thus writeth <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> in the life of <hi>Hubert</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> contrary to that which others affirme; writing that <hi>Euſtachius</hi> ſucceeded <hi>William Longchampe</hi> in the Office of Chancellor, and in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Ely.</hi> The words of <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> in the life of <hi>Hubert</hi> be theſe. <hi>Hubertus depoſito magiſtratu ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili, eccleſiae curae totus vacabat, conſecravitque poſtea Robertum de Solopesbi, epiſcopum Bancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſem, &amp; Euſtachium, qui in cancellarij munere ei ſucceſsit Elienſem epiſcopum, VVeſtmonaſterij de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15042:13"/>
accepta ab utroqueſubjectionis profeſsione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hubert Walter,</hi> or <hi>Walter Hubert,</hi> for ſuch a tranſmutation of the name, is uſed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, being firſt Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was made Chancellor ſhortly after the Coronation of King <hi>John;</hi> which was in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1199, at what time a certaine Nobleman ſaide unto him in ſcorne, I have often ſeene, of a Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor made a Biſhop, but I never before ſaw an Archbiſhop made a Chancellor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon;</hi> or rather <hi>Hugh,</hi> of which is more hereafter, Arch-deacon of <hi>Wels,</hi> in the firſt yeare of King <hi>John,</hi> after (as I ſuppoſe that <hi>Hubert</hi> had left the Office, being ſo diſgraced and abaſed, as he thought) was witneſſe to a Deed, in which King <hi>John,</hi> granted to the Cittizens of <hi>Yorke,</hi> a guildhall, hanſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liberties, as I have ſeene noted in the Copy of the ſame Charter, for which cauſe, I have ſet it downe as another man, although in truth I am fully reſolved, that this <hi>Simon,</hi> and the <hi>Hugh</hi> following, were all one perſon, leaving it yet for every mans Iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15042:13"/>
               <hi>Hugh de Wels</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Wels</hi> witneſſe to the Deed, in which King <hi>John,</hi> in the ſixt yeare of his raigne confirmed to the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Weſtminster, Giſtſlep,</hi> or <hi>Iſlep</hi> in <hi>Oxford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> in which houſe <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor was borne, he was made Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 10, of the raigne of King <hi>John,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1209, and dyed in the yeare of our Lord 1235.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Gray,</hi> choſen Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1210, was Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and after Biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> a man of extream age, was made Chancellor in the ſeaventh yeare of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> as one anonymal Chronicle ſaith, to hold that Office during his life. Others ſay that he was made Chancellor in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1209, being the tenth yeare of King <hi>John,</hi> after <hi>Hugh de Wels.</hi> But I ſuppoſe hee ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred that Patent; to hold it during his life, when he came to be Biſhop of <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard de Mariſcho,</hi> whom <hi>Mathew Paris,</hi> termeth <hi>Tholenarius,</hi> as it were Toll-gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or Treaſurer (if you liſt,) being Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> was Chancellor in the fourth yeare of King <hi>John,</hi> as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15042:14"/>
by a Deed that I have ſeene, and further he was made Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 15, of King <hi>John,</hi> in which Office he continued to the 17 yeare of the ſaid King, and as ſome do write, during King <hi>John</hi> his life, and died about the kalends of <hi>May,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom,</hi> 1226, in <hi>Anno</hi> 10, of the long raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, as ſome have; but the Booke of <hi>Durham</hi> ſaith; that he was made Biſhop of that See, by <hi>Gwado</hi> the Legat, and conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Walter Gray,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1214. being about <hi>Anno</hi> 16, of King <hi>John,</hi> and dyed ſodainely at <hi>Peterborough</hi> the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1226, being the t nth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, after that he had beene Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> nine yeares.</p>
            <p>For whom this formall Epitaph was made,
<q>
                  <l>Culmina qui cupi tis laudes pompaſque ſui tis</l>
                  <l>Et ſedata ſi tis ſi me penſare veli tis</l>
                  <l>Qui populos regi tis memores ſuper omnia ſi tis</l>
                  <l>Quod mors immi tis non parcit honore poti tis</l>
                  <l>Vobis praepoſi tis ſimilis fueram bene ſci tis</l>
                  <l>Quod ſum vos eri tis ad me currendo veni tis</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ralphe Nevill,</hi> was confirmed Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, as it ſeemeth by the whole conſent of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15042:14"/>
Nobility in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1226, being about <hi>Anno</hi> 10 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, after which he was made Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 11 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1227, or as hath <hi>Mathew VVeſtminſter,</hi> he was made Biſhop of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1223, being before Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, after which the King in <hi>Anno</hi> 22 of his raigne, offended with <hi>Nevill,</hi> tooke from him the great Seale, and delivered it to <hi>Geofry</hi> of the Temple, as hath <hi>Mathew Paris,</hi> and <hi>Iohn de Lexington,</hi> although that the ſaid <hi>Nevill</hi> remained ſtill Chancellor, and received the profit thereof, to whom the King would have regiven the ſeale in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1229, being the three and twentieth yeare of his raigne, but <hi>Nevill</hi> would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it This man dyed in the yeare of Chriſt 1243, being <hi>Anno</hi> 27 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, at his Palace at <hi>London,</hi> not farre from the new Temple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geofrey</hi> the Templer and <hi>John de Lexington,</hi> were made keepers of the great Seale, but ſhortly af er this <hi>Geofrey</hi> had the Seale taken from him, becauſe he grew in diſlike of the Nobility in continually provoking them to anger.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15042:15"/>
               <hi>Hugh Pateſhall,</hi> Cannon of <hi>Pauls,</hi> is by <hi>Mathew Paris, Fol</hi> 656, called Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 23 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, Which I much doubt to be true, of his man ſhall be more ſaide in the Treaſurers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon</hi> the <hi>Norman</hi> keeper of the great Seale, in <hi>Anno</hi> 23 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1229, he had the Seale ſhortly taken from him, and was baniſhed the Court, becauſe he would not ſeale the Patent, whereby <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Flanders</hi> might take foure pence for every Sacke of Wooll, that came out of <hi>England</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Flanders,</hi> This <hi>Simon</hi> dyed in the yeare of Chriſt 1249, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 33 <hi>Henry</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Graſſe</hi> or <hi>Groſſus,</hi> Abbat of <hi>Eveſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> (the ſaid <hi>Simon</hi> expelled) had the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the great Seale in <hi>Anno</hi> 23, <hi>Henry</hi> 3, he kept the Seale three yeares, and being choſen Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> hee reſigned the Seale in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1242, being the 26, yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, he dyed (being wiſe and learned in the Canon Law,) in the ſame yeare in <hi>Gaſcoigne,</hi> in a Citty called in Latine <hi>Riola</hi> or <hi>Rigula,</hi> where he was buried.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15042:15"/>
               <hi>John de Lexington,</hi> was againe made keeper of the Great Seale in <hi>Anno</hi> 26 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1242, to execute that Office, <hi>Ralphe Nevill</hi> being in life, and ſtill Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, but in the Kings diſgrace, ſhortly after which, this <hi>Nevill</hi> dyed. This <hi>Iohn Lexington</hi> dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1252, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 41, <hi>Henry</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ranulfe Briton,</hi> as I read, is ſaide to be Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and Treaſurer of the Chamber, about the 37 yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 124<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I ſuppoſe that he only had the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the great Seale, as the reſt had before him, during the life of <hi>Raphe Nevill,</hi> and ſo I leave him to the judgement of others, ſith <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> continually nameth him Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, and once Chancellor, who ſodainly dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after dinner, beholding players at Dice, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1246, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 30 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, Of whom thus writeth the ſaide <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> in his greater hiſtory <hi>Fol.</hi> 934, <hi>Ranul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Brito quondam Dominus familiariſsimus Regi &amp; Reginae multis poſthabitis nobilibus &amp; ejuſdem Cancellarius ſpecialis, quum poſt menſalem refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, aleatores certatim inſpexiſſet colludentes, lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalis
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15042:16"/>
apoplexia, inexpectato vulnere corruit ſugil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Silveſter de Everſden,</hi> received the great Seale in <hi>Anno</hi> 29 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1246, he was Vice-chancellor, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Biſhop of <hi>Carleil,</hi> (being a man moſt cunning in the cuſtome of the Chancery) in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1247. being in <hi>Anno</hi> 31 <hi>Henry</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Manſell</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Maidſtone</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> Parſon of <hi>Wigan,</hi> Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>Paules,</hi> Maſter or Ruler of <hi>Beverley,</hi> Chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England,</hi> one of the privy Counſell to <hi>Henry</hi> the third, his Chaplaine, Ambaſſador into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and a worthy ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, croſſed to goe to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> who at one feaſt, had two Kings, two Queenes, and I know not how many Noblemen, and whoſe ſpirituall livings were about 4000 Markes, of yearely revennewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s I have gathered) he was at the will a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtance of the King made keeper of the great Seale, as Vice-chancellor, for <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſigilli regij accepit Cancellarij vices acturus &amp; officium,</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 31 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1247, he built an houſe of regular Cannons
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15042:16"/>
at <hi>Rumney,</hi> one of the Cinque Ports in <hi>Kent;</hi> To this man King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in <hi>Anno</hi> 30 of his raigne, did grant that his Towne of <hi>Wigan</hi> ſhould be a Burrough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John de Lexington,</hi> being after chiefe I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtice of the Forreſt, from the River of <hi>Trent</hi> South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, was againe keeper of the great Seale, untill ſome part of the 32, yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1248.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Manſell,</hi> againe keeper of the great Seale, who at <hi>Woodstocke,</hi> in the 32 yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, did receive the great Seale of the ſaid <hi>John Lexington,</hi> which he kept (as I ſuppoſe, and that with ſome good proofe) untill the 33 yeare of the ſaid King, being in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1248, Of which <hi>John Manſell,</hi> thus writeth, an old anonymall Chronicle, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Barons warres. <hi>Sed &amp; Johannes Manſell multarum in Anglia eccleſiarum Rector, ſeu potius incubator, reddituum quoque quorum non erat numerus poſſeſſor magnificus, ita quod ditior eo clericus non videbatur in orbe epiſcopali, puta digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate minime inſignitus, metu Baronum aufugit, &amp; latenter ultra mari de Turri London, in qua Rex Angliae, &amp; Regina ſua tunc temporis tenuerunt ſe.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15042:17"/>
Quem quum Henricus filius regis Alemaniae fugien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inſequeretur, &amp; ipſe capitur quum applicuiſſet Bononiae, a Magiſtro Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ardo, de fines procuratore ut putabatur reginae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Radulphus de Diceto,</hi> was Chancellor as I reade and ſuppoſe, much about this time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> being a modeſt, wiſe, and faithfull man, learned in the Canon and Civill Lawes, was made keeper of the great ſeale in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1250. being in <hi>Anno</hi> 34 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, He was elected to the Biſhopricke of <hi>Elie,</hi> as ſaith the Hiſtory of <hi>Elie,</hi> the 18 Calends of <hi>September,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1255, being about <hi>anno</hi> 39 <hi>Henry</hi> 3. But others ſay, that he being then Vice-chancellor, was elected Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1254, being <hi>anno</hi> 38 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, after that he had faithfully, and to his great commendation, uſed and borne the great ſeale, he was conſecrated to that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1255, and dyed in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1256, being about <hi>anno</hi> 41 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, whoſe heart was buried at <hi>Elie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry de Wingham,</hi> was made Chancellor in <hi>anno</hi> 39 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, and continued in <hi>annis</hi> 41
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15042:17"/>
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 42 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, in which yeare (as ſome have) and in the 43 of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, (as others have) he was choſen Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> upon condition that he ſhould give place to <hi>Athelmer,</hi> halfe brother to King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and ſonne to <hi>Hugh Brunne,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marſhe,</hi> and of <hi>Eleanor,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the third his Mother, being baniſhed by the Barons, if that he ſhould againe come into <hi>England,</hi> and then leave the biſhopricke of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> unto him, which he did upon the comming againe of the ſaid <hi>Athelmer</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and for that cauſe was after choſen Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1259, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 33 <hi>Henry</hi> 3. and ſtill Chancellor, and is buried in <hi>Pauls,</hi> on the South ſide of the Quire, (next to <hi>Euſtachius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi>) in a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Marble, with this inſcription on the wall to tell who it was. <hi>Hic jacet Henricus de Wingham quondam epiſcopus hujus eccleſiae qui mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta bona contulit miniſtris eccleſiae ſancti Pauli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Merton</hi> Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 44 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, being in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1260.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas</hi> of <hi>Elie,</hi> made Chancellor by the Barons in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1260, and <hi>Walter Merton</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15042:18"/>
diſplaced. But King <hi>Henry</hi> the third diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to have Officers appointed him by his ſubjects, did in the month of <hi>October</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1260. or rather 1261, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the ſaid <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and replaced the ſaid <hi>Walter Merton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Merton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time made Chancellor, as before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John de Cheſill,</hi> Arch-deacon of <hi>London,</hi> and Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> was made keeper of the great ſeale in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1264, in <hi>Anno</hi> 48 <hi>Henry</hi> 3. This man was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1274, the third Kalends of <hi>May,</hi> as hath <hi>Matthew Weſtminſter,</hi> he dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1279, the fourth Ides of <hi>February,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 7, of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas de Cantelupe,</hi> borne of the noble houſe of the Lords <hi>Cantelupes,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>William Cantelupe</hi> and <hi>Millecent,</hi> which (as ſaith <hi>Leland</hi>) drew her originall from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes of <hi>Yorke,</hi> being Arch-deacon of <hi>Stafford,</hi> was Doctor, and afterward Biſhop of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1276, and before that made
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15042:18"/>
Chancellor, after the feaſt of <hi>S. Peters</hi> Chaire, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1265, being in <hi>anno</hi> 49, <hi>Henry</hi> 3, he dyed beyond the Seas, comming from the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1278, being in <hi>anno</hi> 6 <hi>Edward</hi> 1, or more truely (as others have,) in <hi>anno</hi> 1283, being <hi>anno</hi> 11 <hi>Edward</hi> 1, whoſe bones were brought to <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Gifford</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wels,</hi> whom many doe call <hi>William,</hi> did injoy the ſtate of the Chancellor, in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1266, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>anno</hi> 50, <hi>Henry</hi> 3, he was tranſlated from <hi>Bath</hi> to <hi>Yorke</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1259, being in <hi>anno</hi> 49 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, and dyed the 7, kalends of <hi>May,</hi> in the xij, yeare of his Biſhopricke in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1277, being in <hi>anno</hi> 6, <hi>Edward</hi> 1, or as <hi>Nicholas Trivet</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1279. being the 7, yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geofry Gifford,</hi> was Chancellor alſo in <hi>anno</hi> 51 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, being in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1267, This man was Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> about <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1299 where he ſate 34, yeares, 4 moneths, 4 dayes, and dyed in the yeare 1304, being about the 32, yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John de Cheſill,</hi> was the ſecond time ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15042:19"/>
with the place of the Chancellor in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1268, being the 53 yeare, of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard de Middleton,</hi> ſo ſurnamed of the place where he was borne, was advanced to the Office of the Chancellorſhip in the ſaid <hi>anno</hi> 53 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, in the moneth of <hi>July</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1268, and was alſo, (as appeareth by a Charter which I have ſeene,) witneſſe to the ſame Deed, in <hi>anno</hi> 54 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, who as farre as I can gather) dyed in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1271, being <hi>anno</hi> 56 of the long governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John de Kirby,</hi> after the death of <hi>Richard Middleton,</hi> was made keeper of the great ſeale, in the ſaid <hi>anno</hi> 56 <hi>Henry</hi> 3, It is very probable that this was the ſame <hi>John Kirby,</hi> which after was Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> and Treaſurer of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Merton,</hi> the third time made Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1273, being the firſt yeare of the raigne of that famous Prince King <hi>Edward,</hi> the firſt of that name, He was Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and founded Merton Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and dyed the yeare of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15042:19"/>
Chriſt, 1278, being the ſixt yeare of the raign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Burnell,</hi> the eleaventh Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wels,</hi> (after the uniting of thoſe two Sees, in one, by <hi>Iohn de Toures,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1272, was made Biſhop of <hi>Bath,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord, (as ſaith <hi>Everſden</hi>) 1274, choſen Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1278, but rejected by the Pope. He was Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 2 <hi>Edward</hi> 1, in which place it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that he long continued, of whom thus writeth an anonymall Chronicle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dominus Edmundus Comes Cornubiae fundavit novum ſtudium ordinis Ciſtercienſis apud Oxonias, &amp; monachos de Thame primo ibidem introduxit, &amp; dedit eis prima donatione Manerium de Erdington, &amp; ſecit dedicare locum Abbatiae Tertij Jdus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cembris, per Dominum Robertum Burnell epoſcopum Bathon &amp; Wels, Cancellarium regis, &amp; poſuit fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum novae eccleſiae eodem die Northoſneiae.</hi> This Biſhop was required, with the ſonne of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Gilbert de Clare</hi> Earle of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, to bee delivered for pledges for <hi>Lheweline,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> for his ſafe returne, if he came
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15042:20"/>
to the parliament, whereunto he was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, by the ſaid King <hi>Edward,</hi> In the time of this Chancellor, the Court of Chancery, was kept at <hi>Briſtow.</hi> This man dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1293, being <hi>Anno</hi> 21, <hi>Edward</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John de Langton,</hi> was made Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1293, being the 21 yeare of the victorius King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in which office he remained untill the death of the ſaid King, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1302, He was made Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Annis</hi> 26 or 27, <hi>Edward</hi> 1. being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1298, or rather 1299, And in the ſaid yeare 1299, he was before choſen Biſhop of <hi>Elye,</hi> but rejected by the Pope, who made him Archdeacon of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> From which <hi>Langton</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> did take the great ſeale in the thirtieth yeare before ſaid, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to <hi>John Drokenford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Drokenford</hi> keeper of the Wardrope was made keeper of the great Seale in the thirtieth yeare as before, in which office he continued from about the 15 day of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> untill <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15042:20"/>
               <hi>William de Grinefeild</hi> Deane of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> and Canon of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was advanced to the place of Chancellor in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1302. being about <hi>Anno.</hi> 30. <hi>Edward</hi> 1. which Office was given unto him at Saint <hi>Radigunds</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus M.S.</hi> He was after choſen Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1303. who in the yeare of our Lord 1308 buried the body of the ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> though the King dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1307. This Biſhop dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1315 being about the ſixt yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, at <hi>Cawood,</hi> after that he had beene Biſhop nine yeares, eleaven moneths and two dayes, and was buried in S. <hi>Nicholus</hi> Porch at <hi>Yorke,</hi> receiving his conſecration at <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1305, (after that he had beene there two yeares) of Pope <hi>Clement;</hi> This <hi>Greinfeild</hi> was a man very eloquent, and pithie, and Prudent in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de Hamilton,</hi> Deane of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was created Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1305, being the 33, yeare of that noble prince, King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt; this <hi>William</hi> dyed in <hi>Anno dom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1307, being about <hi>Anno</hi> 35,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15042:21"/>
of the ſaid King at the Abbey of Fontneſſe in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> being a man that well deſerved of the Common wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ralphe de Baldocke,</hi> choſen Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1303, was confirmed at <hi>Titne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall,</hi> by <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Winchelſey</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and conſecrated at <hi>Lyons</hi> by <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alba,</hi> the third Calends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>February,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1305, Hee was made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> after the death of the ſaid <hi>William Hamilton,</hi> in the ſaid 35, yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and received the great Seale, in the <hi>Rogation</hi> weeke follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being ſome foure or five weekes, after he was advanced to that Office, at the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, ſhortly after which dyed King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, for which cauſe the ſaide <hi>Baldocke</hi> ſent the great Seale to King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond then at <hi>Carliel,</hi> by reaſon of his fathers death. This <hi>Baldocke</hi> dyed, on <hi>S. James</hi> Eeve in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1313, being <hi>anno</hi> 7, <hi>Edward</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Langton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> againe made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1307. being the firſt yeare of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of <hi>Carnarvàn</hi> in which office it ſeemeth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15042:21"/>
that he continued untill <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1310 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Anno</hi> 3 <hi>Edward</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Melton</hi> having two others joyned with him had the great Seale delivered unto them for a certaine time, to execute all ſuch things as were to be done therewith, during the Kings pleaſure. This man was a Canon of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Provoſt of <hi>Beverly,</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Anonymus M.S.</hi> He was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he tarried two yeares for the ſame, he was a man never wearied with travell. He firſt of all the Biſhops of <hi>Yorke,</hi> after a long controverſie betwixt the Deane and Cannons of <hi>Yorke,</hi> viſited the chapter by due order, he was wiſe, rich, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in correction, gentle, familiar and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he finiſhed the <hi>Weſt</hi> part of the Church of <hi>S. Peters</hi> in <hi>Yorke,</hi> with 300 pound, he was Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> 22 yeares, five, or ſixe moneths, and two dayes, he dyed at <hi>Cawood,</hi> on <hi>S<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Georges</hi> Eeve, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1330, and was buried in the Minſter of <hi>Yorke</hi> neere the Font.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Reinolds</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:15042:22"/>
was made keeper of the great Seale, and Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> on the ſixt of <hi>July<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Anno dom.</hi> 1310, being <hi>anno</hi> 3 <hi>Edward</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John de Sandall</hi> Clerke, Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> and Treaſurer, was at <hi>Yorke</hi> made Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1314. being <hi>anno</hi> 8 <hi>Edward</hi> 2, in which place, he continued two yeares and more, ſome part thereof being after that he was made Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> (as I gather) and then delivered backe the ſeale at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1317, being in <hi>anno</hi> 11 <hi>Edward</hi> 2, Of this man is more ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Treaſurers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Hotham</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> was created Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1317, being in <hi>anno</hi> 11 <hi>Edward</hi> 2, In which Office he continued untill <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1319, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>anno</hi> 13 <hi>Edward</hi> 2, During whoſe governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the See of <hi>Elie,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1341, the ſteeple fell downe, which made ſuch a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble noiſe, and ſhaking of the ground, that it was ſuppoſed to be ſome earth-quake. He dyed of the palſey in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1336, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>anno</hi> 10 <hi>Edward</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15042:22"/>
               <hi>John Salmon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to be Chancellor in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1319, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>anno</hi> 13 <hi>Edward</hi> 2, againſt whom the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles rebelled, for the miſdemenour of <hi>Piers Gaveſton,</hi> (the <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi>) Earle of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> In this yeare 1319, (as ſaith one Anonymal Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicler <hi>M.S.</hi>) was <hi>William Airemine,</hi> Keeper of the ſeale, Vice-chancellor, taken priſoner by the <hi>Scots.</hi> The words of the which Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for the more certainety thereof, we have here ſet downe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiſcopus Eborum, epiſcopus Eliae theſaurarius, Abbas beatae Mariae Eborum, Abbas de Selbie, Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Eborum, Dominus Willielmus Arymanee Vice-Cancellarius Angliae, ac dominus Johannes Dabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, cum</hi> 8000 <hi>ferme hominum, tam equitum quam peditum &amp; Civibus properanter, civitatem egredien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, quoddam flumen Swale nuncupatum ſparſis cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis tranſeuntes, &amp; indiſpoſitis, ſeu potius confuſis ordinibus, cum adverſarijs congreſsi ſunt. Scoti ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem in Marte gnari amplitudinem eorum exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus caute regentes, in noſtris agminibus ſtrictis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacter irruerunt, noſtrorum deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in brevi laceratis cuneis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſsipatis, corruerunt ex noſtris, tam in ore gladij quam aquarum ſcopulis ſuffocati, pluſquam</hi> 4000. <hi>&amp; capti ſunt domini Johannes de Pabeham,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15042:23"/>
&amp; dominus Willielmus de Arymenee, ut praefertur de Cancellaria &amp;c.</hi> Which <hi>William Ayrmenee</hi> was alſo in the ſaid 15 of <hi>Edward</hi> 2. one of the Keepers of the great Seale, as I have ſeene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Baldocke,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Middleton,</hi> a man evilly beloved, and whom the old Engliſh Chronicle remembers, with ill at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, was made Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 17 <hi>Edward</hi> 2, at the Caſtle of <hi>Pickering</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> he was after made Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> and did his fealty for reſtitution of his Temporalties in <hi>anno</hi> 19, of the ſaid King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſecond, at <hi>Woodſtocke,</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> he was apprehended in <hi>anno</hi> 20 <hi>Edward</hi> 2 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1326, or as others have in the yeare 1325, And firſt committed to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody of <hi>Adam Tarleton,</hi> or <hi>de Orleton,</hi> biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and after was put in the priſon of the <hi>Newgate,</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> in which 20 yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, the great ſeale was againe delivered to <hi>William Arymenee,</hi> who (as I ſuppoſe was then alſo made Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> and this <hi>Baldocke</hi> depoſed from that ſee. Of which <hi>Baldocke</hi> thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15042:23"/>
a <hi>Polythronicon</hi> of <hi>Durham. Robertus de Baldocke Cancellarius anno</hi> 1325, <hi>captus cum Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonibus de Deſpenſers, quia clericus fuit &amp; ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos in nova porta Londiniarum, poni fecit Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Princeps &amp; Iſabella mater ejus, ubi pro nimia miſeria mortuus fuit infra breve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Hotham</hi> biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> the ſecond time was at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> made Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1326, being the firſt yeare of the Raigne of that King, that intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> but he continued not long in the ſame Office, for he was removed in the ſecond yeare of the ſaid King, being in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1328, He was elected Biſhop in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1316, in which place he ruled twenty yeares, and died in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1336, of the palſey, at <hi>Summerſham,</hi> being buried in the Church of <hi>Elie,</hi> under a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly monument of ſtone, with the Image of a biſhop carved out of Alabaſt r upon his Tombe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Cliffe,</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, had the charge and Keeping of the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> in the ſaid yeare of Chriſt, 1328, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15042:24"/>
third, and was the Kings Chancellor alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry de Burgh, Burghwaſh,</hi> or <hi>Burghurſt,</hi> Nephew to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bartholmew Bladiſmere</hi> baron of <hi>Leedes</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> having beene Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> enjoyed the honour of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, in the ſecond yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1328. and was made Chancellor at <hi>Northampton,</hi> which Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he did not long enjoy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Stratford</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and ſometime Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> was made Chancellor of the Realm, in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1330, being in <hi>anno</hi> 4 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, who being ſent in the ſixt yeare of his raigne, in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1332, Ambaſſador beyond the Seas, about the affaires of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, did not like Cardinall <hi>Woolſey</hi> the Chancellor, (in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8,) preſumptuouſly carry the great Seale with him beyond the ſeas, but left the ſame in his abſence with others, who both could and would anſwere the well or evill uſing thereof whiles he was in <hi>France,</hi> This man continued in the Office, untill the Eight yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15042:24"/>
               <hi>Richard de Bury,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Richard de Angervile,</hi> being borne in a little village be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>S Edmundſbury</hi> commonly cald the <hi>Bury</hi> Abbey, was ſo ſurnamed <hi>Bury</hi> of that place, had to his Father S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Richard Angervile</hi> Knight, This man being firſt kept at ſchoole by his Vncle S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn VVillobie</hi> Prieſt, was afterward Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> Chancellor, and Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> to which place of Chancellor-ſhip, hee was advanced in the yeare 1334 being in <hi>anno</hi> 8 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, which office he received by the Kings gift at <hi>VVeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> in which yeare he was inthronized, being firſt conſecrated Biſhop in <hi>anno do.</hi> 1333, in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham,</hi> by <hi>William Cowton Prior</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> He kept the See 11 yeares, two moneths, and twelve dayes, and died in the yeare 1345, and was buryed in the <hi>South</hi> angle of the Church at <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Stratford,</hi> the ſecond time Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, being now Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was inſtalled therein at <hi>York,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1335, being the ninth yeare of the Raigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert de Stratford</hi> or <hi>Strafford</hi> (as ſome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15042:25"/>
have written) but as I thinke corruptly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Archdeacon of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (which Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was firſt ordeined by <hi>Anſelme,</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the ſaid Citty) was made Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> on the 24 day of <hi>March, anno dom.</hi> 1336, being in <hi>anno</hi> 11 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, He was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter made Biſhop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> deſiring to be remooved from that office of Chancellor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which was granted unto him, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſurrendred up the Seale unto the ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> 3, in the 12 yeare of his Raigne, being in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1338.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard de Bintworth,</hi> choſen Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and confirmed by <hi>John Stratford,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> the tenth ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lends of <hi>Iune</hi> 1338, was at <hi>Waltham</hi> advanced to the honour of Lord Chancellor, in the moneth of <hi>July,</hi> in the ſaid yeare 1338, being the 12 yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Stratford</hi> the third time Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> in which Office he did not long continue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> being the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Robert Stratford,</hi> was againe made Lord
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15042:25"/>
Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1340, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>anno</hi> 14 of the raigne of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, who was put out of that Office, and ſhould with the Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> have beene ſent into <hi>France</hi> for a pledge for the payment of certaine ſommes of money.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert de Bourchier,</hi> borne of the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houſe of the Lord <hi>Bourchiers,</hi> was in the Towre of <hi>London,</hi> made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>December</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 14 <hi>Edward</hi> 3 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1340, though ſome ſay, hee was made Chancellor in <hi>anno</hi> 15 of the ſaide King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Perning, Pernicke,</hi> or <hi>Pernwicke,</hi> alſo Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> was made Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1341, bing in <hi>anno</hi> 15 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, he dyed in the yeare 1343, being in <hi>anno</hi> 17 of the ſaid King, This man was a Serjant in the third yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third when he began to plead as a Serjant, in which he continued untill <hi>anno</hi> 11 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, and was after that, Iuſtice, Treaſurer, and Chancellor, and dyed in the common plees being Chancellor, ſitting and arguing amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the Iuſtices, as appeares in the Law books
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15042:26"/>
of thoſe yeares, of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, of whom is laſt mention made in the 17 yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, where hee is named Chancellor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert de Saddington</hi> Knight, was inveſted with the dignity of Lord Chancellor, after the death of <hi>Perning</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1343, and in <hi>anno</hi> 17 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, He was elected to be Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and ſo was inſtalled, but never received the Pall. There was alſo one <hi>Richard Saddington</hi> Knight, Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> of whom I have ſpoken in my diſcourſe of the Lord Treaſurers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Offord</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>fford,</hi> Deane of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> was made Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1345. being <hi>anno</hi> 19 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, Hee dyed in the moneth of <hi>May,</hi> in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1349, being the 23, yeare of the Raigne of that victorious King, <hi>Edward</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Thorſby</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Cardinall, was inſtalled in the ſeat of the Lord Chancellor, in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1349, being <hi>anno</hi> 23 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, who at his great ſuit was diſcharged of the Office
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15042:26"/>
of Chancellor, by delivery of the great Seale in <hi>November</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 30 of the ſaid King, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1356, after hee had kept that place, almoſt by the ſpace of 7 yeares, He in the 10 yeare of his Biſhopricke, on the third kalends of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> beganne the frame of the Quire in S <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Yorke,</hi> and laid the firſt ſtone thereof, to which he gave an Hundred poundes, He dyed at <hi>Thorpe,</hi> and was buryed at <hi>Yorke,</hi> in <hi>anno dom</hi> 1363, or as others have, 1373, after that he had beene Archbiſhop, one and twenty yeares, and one and twenty dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de Edington,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> was made Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>November,</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1356, in <hi>anno</hi> 30 of King <hi>Edward,</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon Langham,</hi> Abbat of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of <hi>England,</hi> was made Lord Chancellor in <hi>February</hi> in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1363, being the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and thirthieth yeare of the governement of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third. Of this <hi>Simon</hi> were theſe verſes, made when he was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15042:27"/>
from <hi>Elie</hi> to the Biſhopricke of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Exultent caeli quia Simon tranſit ab Eli</l>
               <l>Cujus in adventum flent in kent millia centum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Of whom alſo becauſe he richly endowed the Abbey of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with great gifts, of ſingular coſt and value, a certaine Monke compiled theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Res es de Langham, tua Simon ſunt data quondam</l>
               <l>Octingentena librarum millia dena.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Of this man is more ſpoken in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, of the Lord Treaſurers of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de Wickeham,</hi> ſo called of the place of his Birth, whom <hi>Leland</hi> maketh Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> which by any poſſible meanes cannot be ſo, for any thing that I can yet learne, This man being Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> and advanced to that place in <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1367, in <hi>anno</hi> 41 <hi>Edward</hi> 3, in which place he ſate ſeaven and thirty yeares, was ſometime kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the privie ſeale, and made alſo Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1367, being
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15042:27"/>
the 41 yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which Office he remained about foure yeares, and in <hi>March<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in the yeare 1371, being the 45 of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, did deliver up the great Seale, to the King at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> Hee was buried in the body of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> Church, which he new built, with the other places about it, of whom were theſe verſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, for the building of his Colledges, the one at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the other at <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Hunc decet eſſe pium fundatis collegiorum</l>
               <l>Oxoniae primum ſtat Wintoniaeque ſecundum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Thorpe</hi> Knight, being before Iuſtice of the Law in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1370, was after at <hi>Westminſter</hi> advanced to the Chancellorſhip in <hi>March,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 45, <hi>Edward</hi> 3, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1371, Who going home to his owne houſe, left the great ſeale with foure of the Guardians, or Maſters of the Chancery, whereof the one was called <hi>Walter Power,</hi> to keepe and uſe as need required.</p>
            <p>Sr. <hi>John Knivet</hi> or <hi>Knivell,</hi> (as ſome books have by the tranſcriber corrupted) was made Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>July,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15042:28"/>
1372, being the 46 yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which Office hee continued (as I gather) untill the 50 yeare of the ſaide King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which yeare (as here at hand appeareth) came in place, the Biſhop of <hi>S. Davids.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam de Houghton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Menenia,</hi> or of S. <hi>Davids</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> was advanced to the office of Lord Chancellor in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1376, being the 50 yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, who in the 51 yeare of the ſaide King, was with the Earle of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> ſent Ambaſſador beyond the ſeas. And here I thinke it not amiſſe to ſet downe the originall of the Rolls in Chancery Lane in this ſort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the third did build an houſe for the Iewes converted to the faith of Chriſt, which houſe is at this day, (and hath beene long before this time) appointed for the keeping of the Kings Rolles and recordes, being now called and knowne by the name of the Rols in Chancery Lane, beſides Lincolnes Inne. In which houſe the maſter of the Rolles (for the time being) hath his dwelling. In which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15042:28"/>
alſo there is a faire Chappell, called the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of the Rolles, being a place commonly appointed wherein men accoſtome to pay money upon contracts.</p>
            <p>The grant of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, for erecting of the houſe of Converts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rex archi epiſcopis &amp;c. Sciatis nos intuitu Dei, &amp; pro ſalute animae noſtrae &amp; animarum anteceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; haeredum meorum conceſsiſſe, &amp; hac charta noſtra confirmaſſe pro nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris domum quam fundari fecimus in vico, qui voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Newſt eet, inter vetus Templum &amp; novum London, ad ſuſtentationem fratrum converſorum, &amp; convertendorum de Judaiſmo ad fidem catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, in auxilium ſuſtentationis eorundem fratrum in eadem domo converſantium, domos &amp; terraes quae fuere Johannis Harbeton in London, &amp; ſunt in manu noſtra, tanquam eſchaeta noſtra, excepto Gardino, quod fuit eiuſdem Iohannis in vico praedicto de New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, &amp; quod prius per Chartam noſtram conceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus venerabili patri Radulpho Ciceſtrenſi epiſcopo Cancellario noſtro, &amp; omnes alias eſchaetas, quae tempore noſtro per feloniam, vel quacunque ex cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa nobis accident in civitate noſtra, vel in ſuburbio
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15042:29"/>
infra libertatem civitatis noſtrae London. Quare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus &amp; firmiter praecipimus pro nobis &amp; haeredibus nostris quod praedicta domus habeat &amp; teneat libere &amp; quiete Bene &amp; in pace, ad ſuſtentationem fratrum converſorum &amp; convertendorum de Judaiſmo; ad fidem catholicam, in auxillium ſuſtentationis eorun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fratrum, in eadem domo converſantium, domos &amp; terras, quae fuerunt Johannis Harbeton in London, &amp; ſunt in manu noſtra, tanquam eſchaeta noſtra, excepto gardino quod fuit eiuſdem Iohannis in vico praedicto de Newſtreet, &amp; quod prius per chartam nostram con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſsinus venerabili patri Radulpho Ciceſtrenſi epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copo Cancellario nostro, &amp; omnes alias eſchaetas, quae tempore noſtro per feloniam vel quacunque ex cauſa nobis accident in civitate noſtra, vel in fuburbio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra libertatem civitatis nostrae London, ſicut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum est, His testibus venerabilibus patribus W. Kaerl. &amp; W. Exon, epiſcopis. H: de Burgo Comite Kantiae. Radulpho filio Nicholai, Godfrido de Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe Iohanne filio Philip. Amaurico de ſancto Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundo, Will: de Picheford, Galfrido de Cauz &amp; alijs. Dat. per manum Ve: P: R: Ciceſtrend: epiſcop. Cancellar. noſtri apud Weſtmin.</hi> 19. <hi>die Aprilis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15042:29"/>The Grant of Edward the third whereby the ſaid houſe was in the one and fiftieth and laſt yeare of the ſaid <hi>Edward,</hi> converted to the cuſtody of the Rolles and records of the Chancery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rex omnibus ad quos, &amp;c. ſalutem. Sciatis quod nos, conſiderantes qualiter domus converſorum in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbio Civitatis noſtrae London, de patronatu noſtro exiſtens, &amp; capella, aedificia, &amp; clauſur: ejuſdem, tempore quo delectus noſter</hi> Will. Burſtall <hi>cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ejuſdem domus ex collatione noſtra primo habuit, per negligentiam &amp; incuriam aliorum qui ante prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum</hi> Will. <hi>cuſtodiam domus illius habuerunt, &amp; ibidem, morari ſeu inhabitari non curaverunt, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter &amp; quaſi totaliter in ruina exſtiterunt, &amp; quod praedictus</hi> Will. <hi>tempore ſuo de bonis ſuis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prijs, grandes coſtas &amp; expenſas ſuper recuperatione &amp; emendatione domus, capellae, aedificiorum, &amp; clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. praedict. ac etiam ſuper factur: novar domorum ibidem. Nos ut domos converſorum, capella, aedificia, clauſur. &amp; novae domus ſupradict<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> competenter ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtententur &amp; cuſtodientur in futurum, ad ſupplicatio. nem praedicti</hi> Willielmi, <hi>qui cuſtos Rotulorum Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellariae noſtrae existit, in praeſenti concesſimus, de gratia noſtra ſpeciali, pro nobis &amp; haeredibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15042:30"/>
quod post mortem ejuſdem</hi> Willielmi, <hi>dicta do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus converſorum, cum ſuis juribus &amp; pertinentibus quibuſcunque remaneat &amp; moretur in perpetuum Clerico Cuſtod, Rotulorum Cancellar noſtrae &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redum noſtrorum pro tempore exiſtente, &amp; ſimiliter annex. eidem officio in perpetuum, &amp; quod Cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius Angliae vel cuſtos ſive cuſtodes magni ſigilli noſtri &amp; haeredum noſtrorum Angliae pro tempore exiſtentium, post mortem ipſius</hi> Willielmi <hi>habeat, &amp; habeant potestatem ad quamlibet vocationem dicti officij cuſtodis Rotulorum, per mortem cesſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, vel mutationem perſonae, quocunque tempore fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo, inſtitutum ſuccesſivè cuſtodes Rotulorum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorum in dicta domo converſorum, &amp; Cuſtodes il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los ponend. in poſſesſionem ejuſdem cum ſuis juribus et pertinentibus quibuſcunque. In cujus, &amp;c. T. R. apud Shene.</hi> 11. <hi>Aprilis, Anno</hi> 51. Edw. 3.</p>
            <p>But after the death of this King <hi>Edward,</hi> the ſaid <hi>William Burſtall</hi> Maſter of the Rolls, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like not ſuppoſing this to bee a ſufficient grant) procured this houſe by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the firſt yeare of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, to be more ſtrongly eſtabliſhed to the uſe of the Maſter of the Rolles for the time. After which <hi>John de Waltham,</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, after Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15042:30"/>
of <hi>England,</hi> procured King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond in the ſixt yeare of his raigne, by his Letters Patents to confirme the ſaid houſe to the ſaid <hi>William</hi> and his ſucceſſors Maſters of the Rolles. And whereas by the Patent of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, the Maſter of the Rolles was appointed and inſtalled in that houſe by the Chancellor, it is to be noted, that the ſame manner of induction and inſtalment continued as long as the Maſter of the Rolles was of the Clergy, as I have ſeene ſet downe by others, and as the Preſidents of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalments, and the Writts themſelves extant of record doe well prove.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Scroope</hi> Knight Lord of <hi>Bolton,</hi> having beene Lord Treaſurer in the time of the deceaſed King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, was now in <hi>October</hi> about the latter end of the yeare, 1378 or the beginning of the yeare 1379. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond yeare of the after depoſed King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, made Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and had the great Seale delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, who in the third yeare of the ſaid King at a Parliament, did ſurrender up his office. Of this man is more ſet downe in the diſcourſe of the Treaſurers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15042:31"/>
               <hi>Simon Sudbury</hi> ſo ſurnamed of the place of his birth, but by deſcent called <hi>Tibold</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nicholas Tibold,</hi> deſcended of a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman like race dwelling at <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke.</hi> This <hi>Simon</hi> was Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, and made Chancellor about the yeare of Chriſt, 1380. in the third yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and was by the Rebells beheaded in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> in the fourth yeare of the diſquieted government, of that unfortunate, but valiant King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond. After whom in the fifth yeare of the ſaid King, was <hi>R.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> whereof I have ſeene and taken a note, which Biſhop was (as I conjecture, and have ſome authority to prove) <hi>Robert Braybrooke</hi> which followeth, and was made Chancellor againe after Sir <hi>Richard Scroope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> Chancellor the fifth yeare of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, at which time <hi>Robert Braybrooke</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Scroope</hi> Knight, Lord of <hi>Bolton,</hi> made Chancellor againe about the latter end of <hi>November,</hi> by the Lords of the Parliament
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15042:31"/>
(as I take it) in the fifth yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> laſt mentioned, and was the yeare following, being about <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1383, againe depoſed from his office, and the King receiving the ſeale, kept it a certaine time, and therewith ſealed ſuch grants and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings as pleaſed him, and in the end delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſame to <hi>Robert Braybrooke.</hi> Of this man ſee more in the Treaſurers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Braybrooke</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> made Lord Chancellor in <hi>September</hi> following the moneth of <hi>July</hi> when Sir <hi>Richard Scroope</hi> was depoſed, was advanced to that dignity on S. Matthews Eeve, in the ſixt yeare of the raigne of the ſaid King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, in which he continued not longer then the <hi>March</hi> following, (as hath <hi>Anonymus, M.S.</hi>) he was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> the fifth of <hi>January, Anno dom.</hi> 1381, he dyed the 17. of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1404, being the fifth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michael de la Poole,</hi> or at <hi>Poole,</hi> as hath <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Walſingham,</hi> was made Chancellor in the moneth of <hi>March<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 6. of the ſaid King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and was made Earle of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15042:32"/>
               <hi>Suffolke</hi> in the ninth yeare of the ſaid King, being after depoſed from his office of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellorſhip at his owne and earneſt requeſt, in the tenth yeare of the ſaid King. This man having fled the Realme, for that he was purſued by the Nobility, dyed at <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>Ann.</hi> 13. of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1389, of whom that worthy Poet Sir <hi>John Gower,</hi> living at that time, in his Booke intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Vox Clamantis,</hi> compoſed theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Eſt comes elatus, fallax, cupidus, ſceleratus,</l>
               <l>Fraudes per mille ſtat Cancellarius ille</l>
               <l>Hic proceres odit, &amp; eorum nomina rodit</l>
               <l>Morſibus a tergo, fit tandem profugus ergo;</l>
               <l>Sic Deus in caelis mala de puteo <hi>Michaelis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Acriter expurgat ne plus comes ille reſurgat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Arundell,</hi> of the noble houſe of the Earles of <hi>Arundell,</hi> was firſt Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> and then of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and laſtly of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> he was made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 10, of the raigne of the unfortunate King <hi>Richard</hi> 2, which was about <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1386, in which office he remayned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15042:32"/>
               <hi>William Wickham,</hi> was againe made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 12 <hi>Richard</hi> 2, but was in the end remooved from thence in <hi>September,</hi> in the 15 yeare of the troubleſome governement of the ſaid King <hi>Richard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Arundell</hi> aforeſaid, was the ſecond time created Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in the ſaide 15 yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> 2, in place of <hi>William Wickham,</hi> in which office he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about five yeares, and was depoſed and baniſhed the Realme in the 20 yeare of the ſaid King <hi>Richard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Scarle, Scirlee,</hi> or <hi>Serle,</hi> Maſter of the Rolles of the Chancery, and Keeper of the great Seale, hee was Chancellor or in the place of Chancellor in the firſt yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1399.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edmund Stafford,</hi> Keeper of the Privie Seale, Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> and ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and laſtly Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and borne of the noble houſe of the <hi>Staffords,</hi> was made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> about the moneth of <hi>March</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:15042:33"/>
in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1400, being about the ſecond yeare of the uſurping King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, in which Office hee continued untill <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1403, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 4 of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, he being Keeper of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Seale, was made Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> the 20 of <hi>June,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1395, being the 21 yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> 2. Hee was conſecrated at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and kept the See of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> three and twenty yeares. Hee increaſed two fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in <hi>Stapletons</hi> Inne, in <hi>Oxford,</hi> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Statutes of the houſe, and called it <hi>Exceſter</hi> Colledge. Hee died the fourth of <hi>September,</hi> in the ſeaventh yeare of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fift, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1419.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Beuford,</hi> the ſon of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> by <hi>Katherine Swineford,</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1398, as hath <hi>Ypodigma,</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the dignity of Chancellor in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1403, being the fourth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth his elder Brother, by the daughter of the Earle of <hi>Hereford,</hi> in which office, he was in the fift yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and ſixt of the ſame King, (as our Chonicles doe remember) he was made Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1404, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15042:33"/>
the fift yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Langley</hi> Prieſt and Biſhop of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> was at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> made Chancellor in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1405, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 6. of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, in which office he continued (as far as I know) untill he was made Biſhop of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> which was on the 7. of <hi>May</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 7. of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1406, he was Biſhop one and thirty yeares, and dyed in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1437, being the 16. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt. See more fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Fitzalen,</hi> brother to <hi>Richard</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell,</hi> being returned out of exile, with <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bullingbruke,</hi> Duke of <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and after King of <hi>England,</hi> by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, was againe Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and continued therein about two yeares being removed from that place about <hi>September,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 11 of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1410.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Beauford</hi> Knight, the ſonne of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> ſonne to King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and brother to King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, was made Lord Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 11 of the ſaid
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15042:34"/>
King, being in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1410, in which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice hee remained not full three yeares, but left the ſame office, and was created Earle of <hi>Dorcet,</hi> and laſtly, Duke of <hi>Exceter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Wakering</hi> Clerke, Maſter of the Rolles was made keeper of the great Seale, when <hi>Thomas Beauford</hi> left the office of Chancellor, which Seale hee kept about the ſpace of a Moneth, for in <hi>January</hi> after that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Seale, there was a Chancellor cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Fitzallen,</hi> or <hi>Arundell,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was the fourth time inveſted with the Chancellorſhip in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1412. being in <hi>Anno</hi> 13. of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, in which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he continued during the life of the ſaid King, who dyed in the fourteenth yeare of his Raigne, and in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1413.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Beauford</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Cardinall in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vnckle to King <hi>Henry</hi> the fift then reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was the ſecond time made Chancellor in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1413. being in <hi>Anno</hi> 5, of <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15042:34"/>
the fift, in which place he remained untill the fift yeare of the reigne of the ſaid King, being in the yeare of our Lord 1417.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Langley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> was the ſecond time made Lord Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the ſaid yeare of our Lord 1417, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 5, yeare of that worthy Conqueror King <hi>Henry</hi> the 5, Which office hee received at <hi>Southwicke,</hi> and continued in that honor (as farre as I can learne) by the ſpace of ſix yeares or more, whereof five yeares were fully ended in the life and death of the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> the 5, and the ſixt yeare ended in the laſt of the firſt, or beginning of the ſecond yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Beauford</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> before named, was the third time made Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> in the ſecond yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being about <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1423, or 1424, for the ſecond yeare of that King fell partly in the one and partly in the other of the ſaid yeares of our Lord. In which office he continued about the ſpace of foure yeares, untill he was made Cardinall in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1426.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:15042:35"/>
               <hi>John Kemp</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> was made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> in the fourth yeare of that King <hi>Henry,</hi> who in his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt yeares was crowned firſt King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and then King of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> in which office he remained (as I ſuppoſe) about ſix yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Stafford</hi> Deane of Saint <hi>Martin</hi> and of <hi>Wels,</hi> Prebend of <hi>Milton</hi> in <hi>Lincolne</hi> Church, Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> Lord Chancellor and Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi>) was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in the moneth of <hi>February,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1431, falling in the tenth yeare of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſixt, he remained in that office, untill <hi>John Kempe,</hi> was againe made Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, which was about <hi>Anno</hi> 6 of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, And here I thinke it not unmeet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that ſome have noted <hi>William Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet,</hi> that was Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to be Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> when he built <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 25 <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, which poſſibly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, ſith this <hi>Iohn Stafford,</hi> held that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from the tenth of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, untill
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15042:35"/>
the eight and twentieth of the ſame King, which was eighteene yeares, during which time they place this <hi>Wanfleet</hi> to be Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>England,</hi> which error I ſuppoſe they have committed, in that they finding him Chancellor, at the time of the building of his Colledge in the ſaid 25 yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, have taken him to be Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> when he was then but Chancellor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> although indeed afterward he was Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 35, of the ſaid King, as after ſhall appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Kempe,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Cardinall was the ſecond time made Lord Chancellor in the 28 yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1450, in which office he dyed, being Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in <hi>Anno do</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Matthew Parker</hi>) 1453, being the 32 yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt. This man was firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> next of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> thirdly of <hi>London,</hi> then of <hi>Yorke,</hi> where he ſate ſate 28 yeares, and laſtly he was Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Cardinall by the title of Saint <hi>Rufind,</hi> which preferments are breifly expreſſed in this verſe.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:15042:36"/>Bis primas, ter praeſes &amp; bis Cardine Functus.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Nevill,</hi> Earle of <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> the ſon to <hi>Raphe Nevill,</hi> Earle of <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> and father to the valiant <hi>Richard Nevill,</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> was after the death of <hi>Iohn Kempe,</hi> by Parliament made Lord Chancellor in the 32 yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make it to be in the 33 yeare of the ſame King, In which place hee continued not long, for in the yeare following, another was ſubſtituted and he remooved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Bourchier,</hi> brother to <hi>Henry Bourchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was made Chancellor in <hi>Anno</hi> 33 <hi>Henry</hi> 6, in which he remained much about 2 yeares in whoſe time (as ſaith <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Parker</hi>) about <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1461, was the Art of <hi>Printing</hi> invented at the Citty of <hi>Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torat</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi> About which matter, and eſpecially for the exact and certaine time thereof, many writers, although their count about one time doe diſagree: yet at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of that worthy thing, were theſe verſes compoſed, in commendation of the ſame moſt excellent Art.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:15042:36"/>
               <l>O faelix noſtris memoranda impreſsio tectis</l>
               <l>Inventore nitet utraque lingua tuo</l>
               <l>Deſierat quaſi totum quod fundis in orbe</l>
               <l>Nunc parvo doctus quilibet eſſe poteſt</l>
               <l>Omnes Nunc homines igitur te laudibus ornent</l>
               <l>Te duce quando ars haec mira reperta fuit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>William Patan</hi> or <hi>Paten,</hi> borne of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly Family, being commonly called <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Wanfleet,</hi> of the place of his birth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provoſt of <hi>Eaton,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> was Lord Chancellor in <hi>Annis</hi> 35, <hi>&amp;</hi> 36, <hi>&amp;</hi> 37, of the unfortunate King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, as have the Records, of the Exchequor. By which appeareth the error of thoſe, as I have before noted, that miſtaking the 25. of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, in which time hee was but Chancellor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> for the 35. of the ſaid King, in which hee was Chancellor of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Nevill</hi> (the ſonne of <hi>Richard Nevill</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and brother to <hi>Richard Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi>) being made Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> came to that See, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1455. in which See he continued tenne yeares, and was removed to <hi>Yorke</hi> in <hi>Anno dom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1465, hee
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15042:37"/>
was made Lord Chancellor in the 38. yeare of the raigne of the depoſed King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, in which office hee remained about 8. yeares, and then was remooved in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1467, He was a great friend to S. <hi>Albons,</hi> and procured <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in the fourth yeare of his raigne, to give and confirme to <hi>John Whethamſtead</hi> Abbat of Saint <hi>Albons,</hi> the Priory of <hi>Pembrooke.</hi> This Biſhop <hi>Nevill</hi> did after in the 13 yeare of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth, grow in ſuch diſgrace with the King, that he was ſpoyled at one time of twenty thouſand Pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Kirkham,</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, was made Lord Keeper of the great Seale, upon the removing of <hi>George Nevill,</hi> in the month of <hi>July,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1467, being the ſeventh yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Stillington,</hi> Doctour of the Lawes, Keeper of the privy Seale in <hi>Anno</hi> 3 <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wels;</hi> being made Chancellor in the ſeaventh yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, did ſtill ſo continue untill <hi>Anno</hi> 13, of the ſaid King.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:15042:37"/>
               <hi>Henry Bourchier,</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and firſt advanced to that title of honour by King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth, came in place of the laſt Chancellor, about the 13 yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4, in which place he remained not much more then one Trinity tearme, for in the ſaid 13 yeare, about the Moneth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> was Biſhop <hi>Booth,</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawrence Booth,</hi> ſometime Maſter of <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke</hi> Hall, Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> and after of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was made Lord Chancellor about <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> or rather before, betweene that and Trinity tearme, (after <hi>Henry Bourchier</hi>) in the ſaid 13 yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4, after his redemption of the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi> This Biſhop being brother to <hi>William Booth,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> did build the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> his houſe at <hi>Batterſey,</hi> which Mannor he before bought of <hi>Nicholas Stanley,</hi> whom <hi>Leland</hi> the minſer and refiner of all <hi>Engliſh</hi> names, doth moſt curiouſly in Latine call, <hi>Nicholaum Stenelegium.</hi> Hee continued in the See of <hi>Yorke,</hi> three yeares and nine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and died at <hi>Sowthwell,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1480 being in <hi>Anno</hi> 20 <hi>Edward</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:15042:38"/>
               <hi>Thomas Scot,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Rotheram,</hi> becauſe of the Towne of <hi>Rotheram,</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> where he was borne and bred up, was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and then of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> where he ſat nine yeares, and after that was Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> whereunto he was inſtalled firſt at <hi>Yorke,</hi> then at <hi>Ripon,</hi> being Provoſt of <hi>Bever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> he was made Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1474, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 14, <hi>Edward</hi> 4. This Biſhop in <hi>Anno</hi> 15 of the ſaid King, went over the Sea, with the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> 4, when he went to have an <hi>interveiw</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King, of which meeting <hi>Monſieue de Argentine,</hi> (by name <hi>Philip Comineus</hi>) beſides our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chronicles, doth make mention, as a perſon that bare a part in that Solemnity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Alcot</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> was made Chancellor during the abſence of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Rotheram,</hi> being before Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Privy Seale, was after his returne out of <hi>France,</hi> the ſecond time made Lord Chancellor, about the time, in which the ſaid King had gotten <hi>Berwicke</hi> from the <hi>Scots,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Anno</hi> 20 <hi>Edward</hi> 4, For the free gaining
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15042:38"/>
of the Towne was not ſo much before his death. In which Office this <hi>Rotheram,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued all the life of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4, and in the time of the Reigne of the guiltleſſe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered young Prince King <hi>Edward</hi> the 5, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it was aſcribed to him for over much lightneſſe, that he had delivered in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the rebellious government of the protectorſhip of the bloody and unnaturall <hi>Richard,</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> the Seale to the Queene, to whom it did not appertaine, and from whom he received it not. Hee founded a Colledge at <hi>Rotheram,</hi> dedicated it to the name of Ieſus, and endowed it with great poſſeſſions, and ornaments, and annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereto the Churches of <hi>Langhton</hi> and <hi>Almanbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Ruſſell</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> a grave and learned man, had the Seale delivered to him by the ſaide Protectour of <hi>England,</hi> during the time of the ſhort Raigne of the yong King <hi>Edward,</hi> when the ſame Seale was taken from <hi>Rotheram,</hi> and ſo this <hi>Ruſſell</hi> was made Chancellor in the moneth of <hi>June</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1483, being the firſt yeare of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15042:39"/>
King <hi>Richard</hi> the third. This <hi>Ruſſell</hi> is bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Church of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> in a Chapell caſt out of the upper wall of the <hi>South</hi> part of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Barow</hi> Maſter of the Rolls, was made Keeper of the great Seale, which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, was in the third and laſt yeare of the ſaid King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, for in that yeare he was Maſter of the Rolles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Rotheram,</hi> made againe Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor in the firſt entrance of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeaventh, into the governement, but very ſhortly after he was diſplaced, and the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> placed in that roome, he was Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> 19 yeares and ten mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, he was very beneficiall to all his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and advanced ſome with marriages, ſome with poſſeſſions, and ſome with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall livings. He dyed the 29 day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1500, being the 16 yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, at <hi>Cawood</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> the morrow after the Aſcenſion, being of the age of threeſcore and ſixteene yeares, or more. He was buried in <hi>Yorke Minſter,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> ſide, in our Lady Chapell, in a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15042:39"/>
tombe of Marble, which hee cauſed to be made whileſt he was living.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Alcot,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> made in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1476, was Lord Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1 <hi>Henry</hi> 7, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1485 ſhortly after the entrance of the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> into the governement of <hi>England,</hi> for though <hi>Rotheram</hi> were Chancellor, when he got the victory, for that he had beene ſo before, and for that the King was neither provided, nor minded ſodainely to have a man, not meet for that place to execute the ſame, yet this Biſhop <hi>Rotheram</hi> kept not that roome many months, but that Biſhop <hi>Alcot</hi> came in place, becauſe the King found Biſhop <hi>Alcot</hi> a meeter perſon to execute the ſame office, anſwerable to the diſpoſition of the Kings humour. All which notwithſtanding, whether for malice of others, or for his owne deſerts, or both, or for the more ſpeciall truſt, that the King put in Doctour <hi>Moorton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> who had beene the meanes to bring him to the Crowne, this Biſhop <hi>Alcot,</hi> fell ſhortly in the Kings diſgrace, was diſplaced of his Office, and Doctour <hi>Moorton</hi> came in his roome. So
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15042:40"/>
that in this firſt yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, there ſeemed to be three Chancellors in ſuccesſion, one after another, All which before <hi>Moorton,</hi> in this firſt yeare of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſeaventh, may perhaps more properly be termed, Keepers of the great Seale, then Chancellors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Moorton</hi> Doctor of the Civill Law, an Advocate in the Civill Courts, and of the Counſell of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and to <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, to whom alſo he was Maſter of the Rolles, was made Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1478, and Lord Chancellor, of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> at his returne from beyond the Seas, in the firſt yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, being in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1485, after which he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the Arch-biſhopricke of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> he dyed in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1499, in <hi>Anno</hi> 15 of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeaventh, as hath <hi>Matthew Parker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Warham,</hi> Advocate in the Arches, Maſter of the Rolles, Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was before his advancement to the See of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> made Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeaventh, in which office he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15042:40"/>
until about the latter end of the ſeaventh yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight. At what time ſurrendring the Seale, by reaſon of his age and weakeneſſe, the ſame was delivered to <hi>Thomas Woolſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Woolſey,</hi> ſometimes Chapleine to <hi>Henry Deane,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> after the Kings Almoner, and Abbat of S. <hi>Auſtins,</hi> who poſſeſſing many other Abbies, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprickes, was advanced to the government of the great Seale, about the beginning of the 8, yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, being in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1516, to hold the ſame during his life, (as I gather) in which office yet he continued not above thirteene yeares, untill <hi>Anno</hi> 21 of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8, being in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1529. During which time of his Chancellorſhip in <hi>Anno</hi> 19 of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, being <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1527. he went into <hi>France,</hi> repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Perſon, to ſet order for the delivery of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeaventh, and <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, at what time he carried the great Seale over the Seas, to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> Which Seale hee left with Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, to keepe the ſame at <hi>Calis</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:15042:41"/>
untill the Cardinalls returne out of the <hi>French</hi> Dominions. He died in <hi>Leiceſter</hi> Abbey, not without ſuſpicion of poiſon, as was thought, which he had prepared for himſelfe, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his <hi>Apothecary</hi> to deliver when hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for it, the two and twentieth of King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the eight in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1530.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas More</hi> Knight, Chancellor of the <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> was advanced to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chancellorſhip of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1529, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 21 of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, In which office this rare witted Knight (to uſe <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his epitheton) and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chancellor continued not ful three yeares, but in <hi>Anno</hi> 24 of the ſaid King, with much labour and earneſt ſuit, he left his office. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which it will not be impertinent to ſet downe the words of <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> in the lives of the Biſhops of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the life of <hi>Thomas Cranmer,</hi> writing after this manner. <hi>Interearex dum Papae meditabatur excidium, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum de papali authoritate ſenſus iudiciis haud obſcuris collegit. Inter quos Thomas Morus quia regis conatus pontificiis valde ſuſpectus fuit, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellarii munere, venia regis aegre impetrata, ſeſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicavit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:15042:41"/>
               <hi>Thomas Audeley,</hi> Atturney of the <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Serjant at the law, (as moſt affirme) and ſpeaker of the Parliament, was made Knight, and Keeper of the great Seale, the fourth of <hi>June,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 24, of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>32, not long after which he was made Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> This man in the tenth yeare of his Chancellorſhip, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1542, and <hi>Anno</hi> 35, <hi>Henry</hi> 8, changing the name of <hi>Buckingham</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> did name it the Colledge of S. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and endowed it with ſome poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He dyed on <hi>May</hi> Eeve, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1544 being in <hi>Anno</hi> 35 <hi>Henry</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Wriotheſly,</hi> Knight of the Garter, Sonne to <hi>William Wriotheſly, Yorke</hi> Herald, and Grand-childe to <hi>John Wriotheſly,</hi> Garter King of Armes, being created Baron at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, on the firſt day of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> in the 35 yeare of the Reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1543. was after advanced to the honour of the great ſeale, and Chancellor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>England,</hi> about the beginning of <hi>May</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 36 <hi>Henry</hi> 8, being in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1544,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15042:42"/>
in which office hee did continue untill the death of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, And in the beginning of the raigne of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixt, he was the ſixt of <hi>March</hi> remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the ſeale was delivered to <hi>William Paulet,</hi> Lord <hi>S. John</hi> of <hi>Baſing.</hi> This <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Wriotheſly,</hi> being created Earle of <hi>Southampton,</hi> by King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, died at his houſe of <hi>Lincolne</hi> place in <hi>Holborne,</hi> the 30 of <hi>Iuly</hi> in the 4 yeare of the ſaid King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> in the yeare 1550, and was buried at <hi>S. Andrewes</hi> in <hi>Holborne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Paulet</hi> Knight, being firſt Steward of the lands of the Biſhopricke of <hi>Winchester,</hi> then Treaſurer of the houſhold, Lord <hi>Sent-John</hi> of <hi>Baſing,</hi> Lord great Maſter of the Kings houſe, afterwards Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire, Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> being of the Privie Councell to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> had the keeping of the great ſeale committed unto him the ſeaventh day of <hi>March,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1547, being the firſt yeare of the raigne of the young King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15042:42"/>
ſeale he had in Cuſtody, about ſeaven mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, untill the 23, or 24, of <hi>October</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at what time S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Richard Rich,</hi> was made Lord Chancellor.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Rich,</hi> Knight, A Gentleman well deſcended and alyed in <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lord <hi>Rich,</hi> was advanced to the dignity of Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> about the 23, of <hi>October,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1547, being the firſt yeare of the raigne of the noble King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſixt, in which place he remained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Goodericke,</hi> or <hi>Godericke,</hi> being Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> had the great Seale delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and was made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> the 20 of <hi>December,</hi> (as <hi>John Stow</hi> hath noted in his Chronicle) in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1551 being <hi>Anno</hi> 5 <hi>Edward</hi> 6, in which office he continued all the life of the ſaid King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> who died in <hi>Iuly, Anno dom.</hi> 1553, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeaventh yeare of his raigne, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout one moneth after, untill the 13, or 14, day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in which Queene <hi>Mary</hi> made <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> her Chancellor.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:15042:43"/>Sir <hi>Nicholas Hare,</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, had at the comming of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> to the Crowne the great Seale, after the death of King <hi>Edward,</hi> as Lord Keeper by the ſpace of a fortnight, and ſhortly after was <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> made Chancellor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> was in <hi>Auguſt</hi> in <hi>Anno dom</hi> 1553, being the firſt yeare of the raigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> made Chancellor of <hi>England.</hi> This man going in ambaſſage unto <hi>Calis,</hi> left the great ſeale in the cuſtody of <hi>William Paulet, Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> which Biſhop after his returne into <hi>England,</hi> continued in that office all the time of his life, which he ended the 19, of <hi>November</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1555, being the third yeare of Queene <hi>Mary.</hi> After which the great ſeale, lying in her Majeſties cuſtody, ſhee on the <hi>New-yeares day</hi> following, made a new Chancellor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas Heath,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to the King, Ambaſſador into <hi>Germany,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Preſident of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was upon <hi>New-yeares day,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1555, being the third yeare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15042:43"/>
of the raigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> advanced to the honorable dignity of Chancellorſhip; But Queene <hi>Mary</hi> deceaſing on the 17 day of <hi>November,</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1558, and the ſixt yeare of her governement, this <hi>Heath,</hi> upon the placing of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> upon the throne of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> governement, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooved from his Office, and Maſter <hi>Bacon</hi> advanced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas Bacon</hi> Eſquire, Atturney of the Court of <hi>Wardes,</hi> was made Knight, and Lord Keeper of the great ſeale, the 22 of <hi>December</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1558, being the firſt yeare of Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Which name of Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he ſtill kept during his life, and the time of his Office. In whoſe time there was an Act of Parliament eſtabliſhed, to make the power of the Keeper of the great ſeale equall with the authority of the Chancellor. This man continued in this office, and worthily executed the ſame, being a man of rare wit, and deepe experience during the time of his life, which continued untill the 20 of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1578. after the Accompt of <hi>England,</hi> being the one and twentith yeare
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15042:44"/>
of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which place this man kept eighteene yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Bromlie,</hi> the generall Sollicitor of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a Councellor of the Law, and one of the Inner Temple, was advanced to the dignity of Lord Chancellor, on the 25 day of <hi>Aprill</hi> in <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1579, being in <hi>Anno</hi> 21 <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Hatton,</hi> being Vice-chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> was conſtituted Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> and Keeper of the graat ſeale, upon Sunday the 29. day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the 29 yeare of the ſaid Queenes raigne. <hi>Anno dom.</hi> 1587.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Puckring,</hi> Serjant at law, was made Knight, and ſworne of the privy Councell, at <hi>Greenewich,</hi> upon Sunday the 28. day of <hi>May,</hi> in the 34. yeare of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and at the ſame time was made Lord Keeper of the great ſeale of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Egerton,</hi> Knight, being Maſter of the Rolles, had the great ſeale of <hi>England</hi> delivered unto him, at <hi>Greenewich,</hi> and ſworne of the Privy Councell, upon the 6 of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15042:44"/>
               <hi>May</hi> 1596, being in the 38. of Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and ſo continued in both thoſe places till the firſt yeare of King <hi>James,</hi> who crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him Baron of <hi>Elſmere</hi> at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court 21 <hi>Iuly</hi> 1603, and made him Lord Chancellor, and laſtly created him into the dignity of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Brackley,</hi> the 7. day of <hi>November<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1616, but ſevered the place of Maſter of the Rolles, which was given to <hi>Edward Bruce,</hi> Lord <hi>Kinloſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> Knight, Atturney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to King <hi>Iames,</hi> and at the ſame time of the Privy Councell; ſecond ſonne of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Bacon,</hi> ſometime Lord Keeper of the great ſeale, upon the 7 of <hi>March</hi> 1616 in the 14 yeare of King <hi>James,</hi> a few dayes before the death of the former Lord Chancellor, had the great ſeale committed to him, and being created a Baron by the title of Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> at <hi>Wanſted</hi> the 12 of <hi>July</hi> 1617, was made Lord Chancellor the 4 of <hi>January</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and made Vicount of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Alban</hi> the 20 of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1620.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:15042:45"/>Vpon the removall of the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Bacon</hi> who was diſplaced by the Parliament, in Lent the 18 yeare of King <hi>Iames.</hi> The keeping of the great Seale, was committed to <hi>Henry, vicount Mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile,</hi> Lord Preſident of the Councell, <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> and <hi>Lenox,</hi> Lord Steward of the Kings houſe, <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine of the Kings houſe, and Sir <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> Knight, Maſter of the Rols, who continued the cuſtody thereof till <hi>July</hi> following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Williams,</hi> Doctor of Divinity, Deane of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and one of the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and after that conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> was made Lord keeper of the great ſeale of <hi>England,</hi> the 10 day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> in the 19 yeare of King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Coventry</hi> Knight, eldeſt ſonne to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Coventry</hi> Knight, one of the Iuſtices of the Common pleas, being the Kings Atturney Generall, was made Lord keeper of the great ſeale of <hi>England,</hi> the firſt day of <hi>November,</hi> in the firſt yeare
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15042:45"/>
of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and Created Baron <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry</hi> of <hi>Allesborough</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> the 10 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the 4 yeare of King <hi>Charles;</hi> whoſe exempler vertues in the execution of this great office, to the honour of his Majeſtie, and the generall good of the Kingdome, I cannot menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without due Attributes, and fearing as I juſtly may, that I ſhall rather ſhew mine owne defects, than be able to ſet them forth in due characters; I ſhall with much ſecurity diſcharge my ſelfe in this kinde, by reciting the preamble of his Majeſties Letters Patents, for Creating his Lordſhip into the dignity of a Baron and Peere of this Realme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rex &amp;c. Archiepiſcopis, Ducibus, &amp;c. ad quos praeſentes literae provenerint Salutem Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio &amp; curae Regali nihil magis arbitramur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire, quam virtutum praemia viris illuſtribus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itè diſponere, ac illos Honoribus attollere qui de Rege &amp; Republicâ optimè meruerunt: Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus enim Coronam noſtram Regiam quam plurimum honorari, &amp; locupletari, cum viros cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datos Conſilio, prudentiâ, virtutibus, illuſtres, ac
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15042:46"/>
praeſertim in adminiſtrandâ Juſticia ſtrenuos &amp; inſignes ad Honoris &amp; dignitatis gradus voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; erigimus. Nos igitur in perſonâ praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecti, &amp; per quam fidelis Conſiliarij noſtri</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Coventry, <hi>Militis, Cuſtodis Magni Sigilli noſtri Angliae, gratiſsima &amp; digniſsima ſervitia quae idem Conſiliarius noſter tam praechariſsimo Patri noſtro Jacobo Regi beatae memoriae per multos annos, quam nobis ab ipſis Regni noſtri primis auſpicijs fideliſsimè &amp; prudentiſsimè prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitit &amp; impendit, indieſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>; impendere non deſiſtit. Nec non circumſpèctionem, prudentiam, ſtrenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, dexteritatem, integritatem, industriam, conſtantiam, &amp; fidelitatem ipſius</hi> Thomae Coventry <hi>Militis, erga nos &amp; Coronam noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Animo benigno &amp; Regali intimè r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>colentes pro gratiae noſtrae, erga praefatum Conſiliarium pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore. Nec non virtutum &amp; benemeritorum ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem encomio poſteris ſuis relinquendum, ipſum, in Procerum hujus Regni noſtri Angliae numerum aſcribendum decrevimus, Sciatis ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>; quod nos de gratia noſtrâ ſpeciali, ac ex certâ ſcientia &amp; mero motu noſtris praefatum</hi> Thomam Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry <hi>Militem, ad ſtatum, gradum, dignitatem &amp; Honorem Baronis</hi> Coventry <hi>de</hi> Alesbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15042:46"/>
               <hi>in Comitatu noſtro</hi> Wigornienſi <hi>erex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imus, perficimus, &amp; creavimus. Jpſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>;</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Coventry <hi>Militem, Baronem</hi> Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try <hi>de</hi> Alesborough <hi>praedicta tenore prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium erigimus, perficimus, &amp; creamus. Jn cujus rei &amp;c.</hi> T. R. <hi>apud</hi> Weſtm. <hi>decimo die Aprilis, Anno Regni Regis</hi> Caroli <hi>quarto, per ipſum Regem.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:47"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:15042:47"/>
            <head>Cuſtodes Rotulorum.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">23. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>DAM de Oſgodby <hi>Clerke,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.</note>William Ayremyne <hi>after Keeper of the great Seale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">17. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.</note>Richard de Ayremyne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">20. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2.</note>Henry de Clyffe <hi>Clerke, after keeper of the great Seale died the</hi> 7 <hi>of King</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>the third.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>Michael de Worth Ianuary 20.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">11. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>Iohn de <hi>Saint</hi> Paul Aprill 28.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>Thomas de Eveſham, <hi>Tueſday after the feaſt of Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>David de Wollere</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">45. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>William Burſtall, Iuly 22.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2.</note>Iohn de Waltham <hi>Clerke, after Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Salisbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8. <hi>Ri.</hi> 2.</note>Iohannes de Burton, <hi>Clerke</hi> Octo. 24</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ri.</hi> 2.</note>Thomas Stanley <hi>Clerke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Ri.</hi> 2.</note>Iohn Scarle <hi>or</hi> Serle, <hi>after keeper of the great Seale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.</note>Nicholas Bubwith <hi>Septem</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15042:48"/>
               <note place="margin">6. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.</note>Iohannes Wakering <hi>Clerke, after kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the great Seale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Hen.</hi> 5</note>Simon Garnaſtead <hi>Clerke</hi> Iune 3.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6</note>Iohannes Franke <hi>Clerke</hi> October 18</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">17. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6</note>Iohannes Stopinden <hi>Clerke</hi> Nov. 13</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6</note>Thomas Kirkby, <hi>had the Reverſion</hi> March 29, <hi>he was in</hi> 28 <hi>and</hi> 33 H. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.</note>Robert de Kirkham <hi>Clerk</hi> December 23 <hi>after Lord Chancellor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">49. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6</note>William Morland <hi>Clerke</hi> Februa. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 14</note>Iohn Alcocke <hi>Deane of the free Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell at S.</hi> Stevens <hi>in</hi> Weſtminſter, Aprill 29, <hi>after Lord Chancellor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">12. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.</note>Iohn Morton, <hi>Clerke, Doctor of Law,</hi> March 16, <hi>made Biſhop of</hi> Ely 18 <hi>of</hi> Edward 4, Ianuary 4, <hi>after Lord Chancellor, and Archbiſhop of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">18. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4</note>Robert Morton <hi>Clerke,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. <hi>Hen.</hi> 7</note>William Kliot.</p>
            <p>Iohn Blithe <hi>Clerke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thomas Barow, <hi>Doctor of Law after keeper of the great Seale as ſome have it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">9 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7</note>William Warham <hi>Clerke, after Lord Chancellor, and Archbiſhop of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:15042:48"/>
               <note place="margin">17 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7</note>William Barow <hi>Doctor of Law, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Glaſſe window, in the Chappell of the Rolles</hi> 1503.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">20 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7</note>Chriſtopher Beinbrig <hi>Clerke,</hi> No<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</note>Iohn young <hi>Clerke,</hi> Ianuary 12.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</note>Cuthbert Tunſtall <hi>Clerke, after Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Dureſme, March 12,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">14 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8</note>Iohn Clerke <hi>Clerke,</hi> October 20,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">15 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8</note>Thomas Hanniball <hi>Clerke,</hi> Octo. 19</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">19 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8</note>Iohn Taylor <hi>Clerke,</hi> October 19.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">26 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8</note>Thomas Cromwell <hi>Eſquire after cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Earle of Eſſex, &amp;c.</hi> October 6</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">28 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8</note>Chriſtopher Hales <hi>Eſquire, after Knighted,</hi> Iune 10,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">33 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8</note>Robert Suthwell <hi>Eſquire,</hi> Iuly 1,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6</note>Iohn Beaumont <hi>Eſquire,</hi> Decem. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6</note>Robert Bowes <hi>Knight,</hi> Iune 16.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>M.</hi> Q.</note>Nicholas Hare <hi>Knight,</hi> September 18, <hi>keeper of the great Seale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 &amp; 5 <hi>Phi.</hi> &amp; <hi>M.</hi> 23 <hi>Eli.</hi> Q.</note>William Cordell <hi>Knight,</hi> Novem. 5,</p>
            <p>Gilbert Gerard <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thomas Egerton <hi>Knight, after keeper of the great Seale, and Lord Chancellor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Edward Bruce, <hi>Lord</hi> Kinloſſe.</p>
            <p>Thomas Phillips <hi>Knight, Serjant at Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:15042:49"/>Iulius Caeſar <hi>Knight, Chancellor of the Kings Exchecker, which place he left when he was Maſter of the Rolles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dudley Digges, <hi>of</hi> Chilham <hi>Caſtle, in the County of</hi> Kent, <hi>Knight.</hi> 1636.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:49"/>
            <p>Honoratiſſimo &amp; Reverendiſſimo Dom. in Chriſto Patri, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Guilielmo Iuxon,</hi> Speciali Dietatis providentia Praeſuli <hi>Londinenſi</hi> Totius <hi>Angliae</hi> Archithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurario. Et è Secretioribus regiis Arcanis Conciliario.</p>
            <p>Pientiſsimo virtutis Aſſertori, ſtrenuo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litioris literaturae vindici &amp; Religionis ſyncerae, propugnatori Acerrimo.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioh. Philipot</hi> Fecialis Regius a Provincia <hi>Sommerſet tenſi</hi> Denominatus.</p>
            <p>Dignitatis veſtrae cultor humilimus Hanc Theſurario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Seriem DICIT, DEDICAT, CONSECRAT.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catalogue_of_Lord_Treasurers">
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:50"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15042:50"/>
            <head>A CATALOGVE OF THE LORD TREASVRERS OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vnſtane,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> was Treaſurer to <hi>Eadred</hi> or <hi>Eldred</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> who began his raigne in the yeare nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred forty and ſixe, of whom thus writeth <hi>Matt. Parker,</hi> in his booke of the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the life of <hi>Odo Severus</hi> the two and twentieth Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of that ſee. <hi>Edmundo</hi> (the King of <hi>England) defuncto. Eadredus corona regia ab Odone redimitus, &amp; rem publicam administrans, Dunſtanum (ut in ejus vita patebit) tam ſingulari amore proſequutus eſt, ut omnes regni theſauros illius cuſtodiae commendaret.</hi> This man was canonized a Saint, and the <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths</hi> of <hi>London</hi> are incorporated into the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and fellwoſhip of Saint <hi>Dunſtan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15042:51"/>
               <hi>Hugolme,</hi> was Treaſurer and Chamberlaine to <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, hee gave <hi>Deane</hi> and <hi>South-bright</hi> to <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> which <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor did afterward confirme to that houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Odo,</hi> halfe brother to <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror Earle of <hi>Kent,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Baieux</hi> and chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England</hi> was Treaſurer in the time of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, who had at his death; as ſaith <hi>Anonymus. M. S.</hi> Sixtie Thouſand Pounds. <hi>Excepto auro &amp; gemmis, &amp; vaſis, &amp; Palijs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geofry Clinton,</hi> Treaſurer and Chamberline to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt: Hee about the thirteenth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, in the yeare of our Lord One Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand one Hundred and Twelve, did found the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory of <hi>Kenelworth,</hi> and was after accuſed of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in the one and thirtieth yeare of the raigne of the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt; but (as it ſeemed) reſtored (in ſhort time after) to the Kings favour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ranulph,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> was Treaſurer to the King, whom <hi>Florenſius Wygornienſis</hi> calleth <hi>Praecipuum Regis placitatorem, &amp; Regni exactorem,</hi> whoſe laſt word, <hi>Exactor,</hi> ſome men doe engliſh Treaſurer. Of this man is more ſaid in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sarisbury,</hi> Treaſurer and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler of <hi>England,</hi> as appeareth by <hi>Leland,</hi> writing in this ſort, <hi>Roger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> Treaſurer and Chanceller to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, made the Caſtle of <hi>Vies</hi> ſuch a coſtly, and ſo ſtrong a fort as was never before nor ſince ſet up by any Biſhop of <hi>England.</hi> The Keepe or Dungeon of it ſet upon a hill caſt by hand, is a peece of worke of incredible coſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15042:51"/>
which to prove the ſame <hi>Roger</hi> Treaſurer at the later end of the Raigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>William de Pontlearch</hi> at the entring of King <hi>Stephen</hi> into <hi>England:</hi> Thus writeth one, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymall chronicle. M. S. Stephanus cum intravit Angliam, Rogerum Sarisburienſem &amp; Willielmum de Pontlearijs Cuſtodes Theſaurorum ad ſe traduxit.</hi> Which <hi>William de Pontlearch</hi> was a witneſſe with <hi>William Stigill</hi> to a certaine Charter which <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulph</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> made to the Monkes of <hi>Durham</hi> commonly called S. <hi>Cuthberts Monkes,</hi> wherein he confirmed to them <hi>Blakeſtone, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropp,</hi> and <hi>Sandropſhire,</hi> with the wood of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> on the Eaſt part of <hi>Mareburne,</hi> as farre as it goeth to the Sea. This <hi>Roger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> died in the yeere of our redemption One Thouſand one Hundred Thirtie and Nine, being about the fourth yeare of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> of whom, mention is made in the Chancellers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nigellus,</hi> the ſecond Biſhop of <hi>Elye,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Roger</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> and Treaſurer to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, was advanced unto that Biſhoppricke of <hi>Elie,</hi> in the yeere of our redemption One Thouſand one Hundred Thirtie and Three, the firſt Calends of <hi>Iune,</hi> being the Three and Thirtieth yeere of the raigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, at whoſe going downe to be inſtalled in the ſaid Biſhopricke, hee was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with ſuch joy, that all the whole ſtreet of <hi>Ely,</hi> through which hee ſhould paſſe, was hanged with curtaines and carpets, with ſeates ſet on each ſide, and the Monkes Cannons, and Clerkes meeting him with proceſſion with divers other Prieſts ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15042:52"/>
round about them. After his inſtallation he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the diſpatche of the affaires of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, committing the charge of his Biſhoppricke to one <hi>Ralph,</hi> ſometime a Moonke of <hi>Glaſtenbury,</hi> and now become an Apoſtata. Great contention was betweene this man and King <hi>Stephen.</hi> Hee bought the Treaſurerſhip for the Summe of Foure Hundred Markes of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond for his ſonne <hi>Richard, filius Nigelli,</hi> or <hi>Fitz Neale,</hi> otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Elie.</hi> He governed the Biſhoppricke Sixe and Thirty yeeres, as ſome ſay, and builded Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge. Trivet</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that he died in the yeere of Chriſt One Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand One Hundred Sixty and Nine, and the Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, after that he had governed Sixe and Thirty yeares, he was honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly buried in the Church of Saint <hi>Ethelred</hi> of <hi>Elie,</hi> before the Altar dedicated to the Holy Croſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Elie,</hi> or <hi>Fitz Neale</hi> ſonne of the ſaid <hi>Nigellus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> was made Treaſurer to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, by the purchaſe of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Nigellus</hi> when the King went to the warres of <hi>Tolous.</hi> Of whom the Hiſtorie of <hi>Elie</hi> writeth: That after the buriall of <hi>Nigellus</hi> his Father, this <hi>Richard</hi> being alſo an enemy of the Church of <hi>Elie,</hi> as his father had beene before, made haſt to paſſe over the Seas to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, fearing that ſome evill would be prepared againſt him, if the Church ſhould have ſent any other thither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. At whoſe comming to the King, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the Monkes of many things, and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſo edge the King againſt them, that the King
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15042:52"/>
ſending into <hi>England,</hi> charged by <hi>Wunndrus,</hi> one of his Chaplens, that the Prior of <hi>Elie</hi> ſhould bee depoſed, and the Moonkes with all their goods to be proſcribed &amp; baniſhed. This man being Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the Treaſure of the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond at his death came unto One Hundred Thouſand Markes, notwithſtanding the exceſſive charges of the King many waies. Which <hi>Richard</hi> being Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> by the name of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, and the Kings Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer was choſen to that See, in the yeare of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, One Thouſand Eightie and Nine, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt yeere of King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, and was conſecrated Biſhop at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> by <hi>Baldwine</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt 1190. He died the fourth Ides of <hi>September,</hi> in the yeare of grace 1198. being the Ninth yeere of King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Elie,</hi> being of kinne to the laſt <hi>Richard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> was Treaſurer to King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, and to King <hi>Iohn.</hi> To which <hi>William</hi> then Treaſurer, <hi>Richard</hi> his kinſman, the Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don An. Do.</hi> 1196. being the ſeventh yeere of the raigne of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, and the ſaid number of yeares of the governement of the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> in the Biſhoppricke of <hi>London,</hi> did give all his houſes in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which the ſaid <hi>William</hi> did long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter give to the Abbat, and Moonkes of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> as by the Charter thereof appeares, in this ſort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vniverſis Chriſti fidelibus, ad quos praeſens ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pervenerit. Gulielmus de Elie quondam Regum
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15042:53"/>
Angliae Theſaurarius ſalutem. Noverit univerſitas veſtra me dediſſe, &amp;c. Deo &amp; Monachis Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, &amp;c. pro animabus Richardi &amp; Iohannis Regum Angliae &amp; pro amima Richardi London Epiſcopi, &amp;c. Domos meas &amp; curiam cum pertinentibus in villa Weſtminſter, &amp;c. quas habui ex dono Richardi Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi London, &amp; quae ſunt de feodo Weſtminſter, &amp;c. Testis Euſtachius Fauconbridge Domini Regis The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauraius, &amp;c.</hi> He dyed in the yeare of Chriſt One Thouſand Two Hundred Twenty Two, being the Sixt yeare of the long reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third: As noteth <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who write that then. <hi>Objit Gulielmus Elienſis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae Theſaurarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Deane of <hi>Pauls</hi> was Treaſurer to the King as appeares by <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> in the life of <hi>Hubert</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> writing after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Eodem tempore</hi> (which was a time between the creating of <hi>Hubert</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1194. being the ſixt yeere of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, and the death of the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, which fell in the yeare of Chriſt 1199. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Paulina Decanus aerarij regi cuſtos fuit, ſive (ut vocant) Theſaurarius,</hi> and ſo goeth on with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his miſerable death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Gray,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> whom ſome call Treaſurer in the Eleventh of King <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geffery,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Norwich</hi> Treaſurer to King <hi>Iohn,</hi> who forſooke his Maſter the King bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excommunicated by the Pope, as writeth <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Parker</hi> in the life of <hi>Stephen Langton</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15042:53"/>
of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in theſe following words. <hi>Inter quos</hi> (meaning the Biſhops, which durſt not openly publiſh the excommunication of the King, but ſecretly caſt libels about the high waies, which gave notice thereof) <hi>quam ad fiſcum Regium Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridus Norvicenſis Archidia conus negotijs regijs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendens ſediſset, coepit aſsidentibus exponere excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municationis ſententiam in Regemjam latam, affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non eſſe tutum, Capellanis &amp; Eccleſiaſticis digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus, beneficijſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> affectis ſervire Regi amplius. Ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aulam deſerens, ad Eccleſiaſtica beneficia (quae Regis ſervitio acquiſierat) ſeceſsit. Rex hunc tam proditorie a ſe deficientem, per Willielmum Talbot, Militem prehendi, &amp; ad ſe reduci fecit, cum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in publica cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ſervatum, (donec ſive paenae ſiue conſcientiae taedio pertaeſus vitae fuit &amp; expiravit) detinuit,</hi> whoſe manner of death is in this ſort ſet downe by <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> Pag. 305. that he was committed to priſon, <hi>Vbi poſt dies paucos Rege praefato</hi> (which was King <hi>Iohn) jubente capa indutus plumbea, tam victualium penuria, quam ipſius capae ponderoſitate compreſſus, migravit ad dominum.</hi> Much about this time (as I ſuppoſe) which was <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1209. being about the Eleventh yeere of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Chequer was by the King removed from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> (in hatred of the <hi>Londoners</hi>) untill Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Ruthall, Cuſtos Officij Theſaurarij,</hi> as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of the Records of the Exchequer, had that office the third yeere of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in the yeare 1219.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eustachius de Fauconbridge,</hi> a Iuſtice to receive
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15042:54"/>
               <hi>fines,</hi> Chanceller of the Exchequer, and Treaſurer to <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, was by the Biſhop of <hi>Rochester</hi> conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1221. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fifth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third: which <hi>Euſtachius</hi> in the yeere 1222. with the Deane and Chapiter of <hi>London</hi> had great ſuites againſt <hi>William Abbat</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> he was Treaſurer in the third yeere of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, being about <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1219. he died the day before the Kalends of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1228. being the 13. of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and is buried on the ſouth ſide of the Queere of <hi>Pauls</hi> (beſides <hi>Henry Wengham</hi>) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a faire Monument of Marble, over whom on the wall is this inſcription. <hi>Hicjacet Euſtachius de Fauconbridge quondam Epiſcopus hujus Eccleſiae, qui multa bona contulit miniſtris eccleſiae ſanccti Pauli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohannes de Fontibus,</hi> or <hi>Iohn defontnes</hi> was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> and Treaſurer in the Ninth and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth yeares of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and before (as I take it) this man being Abbat of <hi>Fontnes,</hi> and (as authors ſay) <hi>Vir ſimplex &amp; juſtus, ac recedens a malo,</hi> was at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1220 hee died after that hee had beene Biſhop five yeeres and odde monethes in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1225. being the Ninth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and was buried in the Church of <hi>Elie,</hi> toward the Altar of Saint <hi>Andrew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Malclarke,</hi> or <hi>Lacke latine;</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Carleil</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1223. being about the ſeventh yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, who in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1233. being the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15042:54"/>
of the ſaid King, was by the counſell of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter de Laroches</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from his office of Treaſurerſhip, but alſo put to the fine of 100. markes, which he paid with the loſſe of certaine holdes, given him by Charter during his life: After which hee would have fled beyond the Seas, but entring the Shippe at <hi>Dover,</hi> hee and all his were ſtaid, and evilly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by the Kings ſervants. This man in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1246. being the 30. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, did on the day of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Oxenford,</hi> enter into the habit of the Fryer preachers: After which in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1248. being about the 32. of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, he ſurrendred his ſoule to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ranulph Briton,</hi> by ſome is made Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> but untruely (as I ſuppoſe) for in truth, he was but Treaſurer of the chamber, for any thing I can learne, and removed from that place in the ſixteenth yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1232. in whoſe place came, <hi>Peter de Rivall.</hi> Of this <hi>Ranulph</hi> is mention had in the Chancellers. Beſides which, about this time I reade, that <hi>Hubert de Burgo</hi> was Treaſurer, for thus writeth <hi>Iohannes Londonienſis. Rex</hi> (about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1232.) <hi>fecit ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum</hi> (which was <hi>Hubert de Burgo) ſuum Inſtitiarium principalem totius Angliae, &amp; poſtea Theſaurarium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter de Oriall,</hi> in Latine called <hi>Petrus de Rival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> was Treaſurer of the Chamber, and Treaſurer of the King, Chamberline of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Guardian of all the Forreſts of <hi>England,</hi> of all the Eſcheats, of all the Ports of the ſea, and of all the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15042:55"/>
Priſes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> being ſo deare to the King, (as ſaith <hi>Matthew Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>) that <hi>Expulſis caſtrorum cuſtodibus per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ferè Angliam, Rex omnia ſub ipſius Petri cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia commendarat.</hi> This man was made Treaſurer after <hi>Walter Malclarke</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1233. being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 17. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and in the 18. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, who as I gather was together with <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Stephen de Segrave,</hi> and <hi>Robert Parſlew,</hi> called to accounts in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1234. for the Kings trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and ſeale evilly imployed and kept, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Peter de Revallis</hi> hid himſelfe in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester</hi> and <hi>Peter de Rivallis,</hi> the King removed by the perſwaſion of <hi>Edmund</hi> of <hi>Abindon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as they before had removed <hi>Walter Malclarke.</hi> After which it ſeemeth, that growing in o favour againe, this <hi>Petrus de Rivalis,</hi> was in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1257. being the 41. of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, made Treaſurer of the Chamber; For thus writeth <hi>Matthew Paris. Circa feſtum ſancti Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elis,</hi> which in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1257. <hi>Mortuo Hurtaldo Domini Regis conſiliario &amp; clerico ſpeciali, ac The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurario de camera Regis, ſubrogatur Petrus de Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallis;</hi> Vnder this <hi>Peter de Rivallis</hi> did <hi>Robert Paſſelew</hi> keepe the Kings Treaſure; Touching which <hi>Robert Paſſelew</hi> writeth <hi>Matthew Parker. Quo etiam tempore,</hi> (which was in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1244. being about the 18. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third) <hi>Robertus de Paſſelew qui in theſauris regiis cuſtodiendis &amp; augendis totus verſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s eſt, co<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nomine Regi charus, ab Eccleſiae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedralis
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15042:55"/>
Ciceſtrenſis canonicis, qui Regi placere ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duerant, Ciceſtrenſis Epiſcopus electus eſt. Quod Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifacius Cantuarienſis Archiepiſcopus indigne tulit, &amp; Epiſcopis provinciae ſuae convocatis, in difficillimis quibuſdam &amp; nodoſis quaeſtionibus per Lincolnien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem Epiſcopum compoſitis ſerio examinavit, deinde electione reſciſſa hunc Robertum repulit, &amp; Richar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quendam de Wiz loco ſuo, (inconſulto Rege) ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit.</hi> Next writeth <hi>Matthew Westminſter,</hi> that in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1233. being the 17. of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, the Nobility accuſed many of the Kings Counſellors, amongſt whom they placed, <hi>Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Paſselew Theſaurarium.</hi> Againe, a little after he ſaith, <hi>Et ſic abſondit ſe iterum Robertus Paſſelew, qui poſt Walteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Carleolenſem officium theſaurarij admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtraverat.</hi> Of whoſe death <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> writeth thus; <hi>Eodem quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> anno,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was 1252. being the 35. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, <hi>Octavo Idus Iunij, obijt apud Waltham Robertus Paſſelew, archidiaconus Lewis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugh Pateſhall,</hi> Treaſurer of the Exchequer, which was Treaſurer of the greene wax, or of the Seale, was alſo treaſurer to the King in the 18. and 19. yeares of his raigne, and after made Iuſtice of all <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> hath ſet downe in theſe words. <hi>Rex autem fretus conſilio ſaniori</hi> (in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1234. being the 18. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third) <hi>Hugonem de Pateſhall clericum filium videli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet Simonis de Pateſhall, qui quando<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habenas mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabatur totius regni Iuſtitiarij, virum fidelem &amp; hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, loco praedictorum,</hi> which were <hi>Stephen Segrave,</hi> chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Peter de Rivallis</hi> Treaſurer) <hi>ſubrogavit Adminiſtraverat enim idem
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15042:56"/>
Hugo officium Scaccarij antea laudabiliter, ſecundum quod appellatur ſecretum ſigillum cuſtodiendo, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitam pecuniam a vicecomitibus recipiendo, quare plenior fides est ei adhibita, paterna fidelitate teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium fidei perhibente.</hi> Hee was confirmed Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1240. being the 24. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, (who having beene the Kings Treaſurer before did now with great ſolemnity take his leave of the Barons of the Exchequer with teares, and they all roſe up and kiſſed him. Of whoſe election (in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1230.) to that Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, thus further writeth the ſaid <hi>Matthew</hi> touching the Moonkes of <hi>Coventry. Eligerunt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum praedictam formam dominum Hugonem de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſhall. &amp;c. canonicum ſancti Pauli London, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis Cancellarium in Epiſcopum, &amp; custodem animarum ſuarum.</hi> Concerning whom I collected this note out of the Regiſter of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that <hi>Phillip Coleville</hi> Knight the ſonne of <hi>William Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Agnes Foliot</hi> gave to <hi>Richard Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> all his part of the inheritance which was <hi>Robert Foliots,</hi> brother to the ſaid <hi>Agnes,</hi> in <hi>London, Mortan,</hi> and <hi>Chalneie,</hi> witneſſes <hi>Raph</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> Chanceller, and <hi>Hugh Pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall</hi> Treaſurer in the 19. of the reigne of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, which <hi>Pateſhall Matthew Westminster</hi> in the yeare of grace 1234. calleth <hi>Summum theſaurarium</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galfridus Templarius,</hi> whom ſome will have Treaſurer, but this man is more ſpoken of amongſt the Chancellors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Haverhull,</hi> a Cannon of <hi>Pauls</hi> Church
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15042:56"/>
in <hi>London</hi> was made Treaſurer to King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1240. being the 24. yeare of the raigne of the ſaid King <hi>Henry,</hi> in which place he continued in the 28. yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1244 he dyed at <hi>London</hi> in <hi>An.</hi> 1252. being the 36. yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, as ſaith the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> fol. 1128. After which the ſaid Author, fol. 1226. laied his death in the yeare 1256. being the 39. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, ſuch error is crept into Hiſtories by the negligence of the tranſcriber, but I ſuppoſe the firſt note of his death to bee the truer, becauſe the ſame is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Matthew Weſt.</hi> ſpeaking in the ſaid yeare 1252. of the death of this man, for whoſe Epitaph, theſe following verſes were made.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hic jacet Haverhulle jaces prototheſaurarie Regis,</l>
               <l>Hinc Haverhulle gemis non Paritura talem</l>
               <l>Fercula culta dabas, empyrea vina pluebas</l>
               <l>A modo ſit Chriſtus, cibus &amp; eſca tibi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I have alſo read a note of one <hi>William Haverhull,</hi> (which might be this man) which ſaith that <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Haverhull,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Brithmarus de Haver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hull,</hi> gave houſes in <hi>Cheapeſide</hi> to the Abby of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and that one <hi>Thomas de Haverhull,</hi> was the ſonne and heire of <hi>William Haverhull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard de Barking,</hi> Abbat of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> as witneſſeth the lives of the Abbats, was one ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Counceller to <hi>Henry</hi> the third, Chiefe Baron of the Exchequer, and Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> who I ſuppoſe did follow <hi>William Haverhull,</hi> for his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15042:57"/>
death which happened on the 23. day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> in the 30. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1246. after that he had beene Abbat 24. yeares, muſt needes prove him to be Treaſurer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Phillip Lovell,</hi> yea and peradventure, (which is moſt likely) before <hi>Hugh Pateſhall,</hi> yet <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> ſpeaking of the death of <hi>Haverhulla,</hi> wil needs have <hi>Phillip Lovel</hi> to ſucceed <hi>William Haverhul,</hi> as after ſhall appeare. This <hi>Richard de Barking</hi> was buried in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Church, before the middle of the Altar, in our Ladies Chappell in a tombe of Marble, which after in the time of <hi>William Colec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſter</hi> Abbat of that place, was pulled downe by Fryer <hi>Combe,</hi> a ſacriſt of that houſe of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who laid a faire plaine Marble ſtone over him, with this preſent Epitaph thus inſcribed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Richardus Barking prior &amp; poſtinclitus Abbas</l>
               <l>Henrici Regis, prudens fuit ille miniſter</l>
               <l>Hujus erat prima laus, inſula rebus opima</l>
               <l>Altera laus eque Thorp, cenſus, Ocham decimae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Tertia Mortone caſtrum, ſimili ratione</l>
               <l>Et regis quarta de multis commoda charta</l>
               <l>Clementis feſto mundo migravit ab iſto</l>
               <l>M. Domini C. bis xl. ſexto<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſub anno</l>
               <l>Cui detur venia parte pia vergo Maria.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip Luvell</hi> or <hi>Lovell</hi> was in this order advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the office of Treaſurer, as appeareth by the words of <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> upon the death of <hi>William Haverhull. Et cum crederetur quod Dominus Rex Iohannem Franciſcum officio Wilhelmi,</hi> (which was <hi>Haverhull) ſubrogaret, fabricatis rumoribus, quod
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15042:57"/>
idem Iohannes in partibus remotis Angliae Boreali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, (ut contra quoſdam religioſos plantaverat) obiiſſet, conſtituit Dominus Rex Philippum Lovell clericum virum prudentem, foecundum, &amp; generoſum in loco memorati Wilielmi, ſuum theſaurarium, quod factum eſt apud ſanctum Albanum, procurante (ut dicitur) Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanne Manſell amico Philippi ſpeciali.</hi> This man was Treaſurer in the 35. and ſo untill the 42. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and was in the ſame yeare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Barons, Hee dyed at <hi>Hameſley</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1259. whoſe executors were <hi>Philip Lovell,</hi> and <hi>Robert de Mercenton.</hi> But his goods after his death, the King commanded to be confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> and <hi>Matthew Weſtminſter,</hi> mention who were the Queenes Treaſurers about that time, thus <hi>obijt &amp; Walterus de Brudelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdem Reginae theſaurarius,</hi> which hee placeth in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1255. being the 39. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third. Of the ſecond perſon <hi>Chacepore</hi> thus writeth <hi>Matthew Weſt.</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1254. <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens autem Rex ad mare, nec ventum habens proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum apud Boloniam moratus eſt invitus, vbi obijt Petrus Chaceporc, natione Pictavenſis, Reginae the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurarius &amp; Regis clericus &amp; conſiliarius ſpecialis.</hi> Theſe two Treaſurers of the Queenes, are ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſome, (but not rightly) to have beene the Kings Treaſurers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Crackhall,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Bedford</hi> was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in 42, 43, 44. yeares of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, to whom the King in the 44. of his raigne, being in An. Dom. 1260. gave a Prebendary, wherein being inveſted, he was from thence removed by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15042:58"/>
a former collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof made to one <hi>Iohn Le Gras.</hi> The ſame <hi>Crackhall</hi> after died the ſame yeare at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Abbot</hi> of <hi>Peterborough</hi> was by the Barons in the 44. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third made Treaſurer as the other Officers of the King alſo were. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> of <hi>Ely</hi> was then made Chanceller, and <hi>Hugh de Spencer</hi> chiefe Iuſtice, which Office of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurerſhip this <hi>Iohn</hi> continued in the 46. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, 1262.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas de Elic</hi> ſo called, becauſe he was Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Elie,</hi> was Treaſurer to the King in the 47. of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, being the yeare of our Lord 1263. whereof I have ſeene this note of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. <hi>Memorandum quod in Craſtino Paſchae.</hi> Anno 47. <hi>Hen. Regis</hi> 3. <hi>in praeſentia Rogeri le Bigot Comite Norfolke &amp; Mareſchalli Angliae. Hugo le Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, Arnoldi de Berkeley Baronis de ſcaccario magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, Iohannis de Chiſull Cancellar. regis, &amp;c. rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit Magiſter Nicholaus archidiaconus Elienſis The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurarius, ſubſcripta in Theſauraria domini regis, &amp;c.</hi> This man as before appeareth, had beene Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler, of whom is mention made in the catalogue of the Chancellers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Wimundham:</hi> This man being chiefe Chanter of <hi>Lichfield,</hi> was by the Barons in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1258. in the 41. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, made Treaſurer (at the Exchequer) at the Seale or place where the Writts be ſealed with greene waxe, after which hee was Treaſurer to the King in the 50, 51, and 52. yeares of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15042:58"/>
               <hi>Iohn Chiſull</hi> ſometime Chanceller, was Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in the 54. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, being about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1269. He was Deane of <hi>Pauls,</hi> choſen Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1273. and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to that place in the yeare of Chriſt, 1274. in which place he continued about five yeares, and died in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1279. being in the ſeventh yeare of the raigne of the victorious Prince, King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt of that name. See more of this <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull</hi> in the Chancellors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phillip de Elie</hi> was treaſurer as appeareth by the Records of the Exchequer, in the 56. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third; and in the firſt yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, partly falling in the yeare 1272. and 1273.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſeph de Chancy,</hi> whom on anomynall author calleth <hi>Iohn Chancy,</hi> but not rightly, as I ſuppoſe, was Treaſurer in the ſecond yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1274.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Gifford,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bathe</hi> and <hi>Welles,</hi> was Treaſurer to <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, hee was removed to <hi>Yorke,</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1275. This man is by many Chronicles and that perhaps moſt truely called <hi>Walter Gifford;</hi> He dyed in the 7. yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, being <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1279. as hath <hi>Nicholas Trivet</hi> Of this man ſee more in the Chancellers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Burnell,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bathe</hi> and <hi>Welles,</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler of <hi>England,</hi> and Treaſurer to King <hi>Edward</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15042:59"/>
the firſt, is by the Welſh-hiſtory, pag. 328. called chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England. Leland</hi> reporteth that an Abbat told him, how that a Biſhop <hi>Burnell</hi> built the Caſtle of <hi>Acton Burnell:</hi> Of this man more is ſpoken in the Chancellors of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſeph de Chancy,</hi> the ſecond time Treaſurer to King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in the ſixth yeare of the ſaid King in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1278. was alſo Prior of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in <hi>Anglia</hi> as I take it, and by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother name called the Lord of Saint <hi>Iohns,</hi> or of the Knights of the Rhodes in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Becke,</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Dorceſter</hi> was Treaſurer in the ſeventh yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1278. as ſome have, but 1279. as other have, by the witneſſe of <hi>Leland,</hi> out of a Moonke of <hi>Glaſtenbury</hi> in his booke <hi>De aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Arthuri,</hi> reciting the words of the ſaid Moonke in this ſort. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1267. <hi>Edvardus Rex Henrici Tertij filius venit cum Regina ſua Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coniam. Die vero Martis proxima ſequenti, fuit Rex &amp; tota Curia accepta ſumptibus Monaſterij. Quo die in crepuſculo fecit apperiri ſepulcrum inclyti Arthuri, ubi in duabus cïſtis imaginibus &amp; armis eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> depictis, oſſa dicti Regis mirae groſsitudinis ſeparata invenit. Imago quidem Reginae coronata, imaginis regiae corona fuit proſtrata, cum abſciſsione ſiniſtrae auriculae, &amp; vestigijs plagae unde moriebatur. Inventa eſt ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſuperhis ſingulis manifesta. In craſtino, viz. Die Mercurij Rex oſſa regis, Regina oſſa reginae, pallijs pretio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is revoluta, in ſuis ciſtis recludentes, &amp; ſigilla
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15042:59"/>
ſua apponentes, praeceperunt idem ſepulchrum ante majus altare celeriter collocari, retentis externis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitibus, propter populi devotionem, appoſita hujuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſcriptura. Haec ſunt oſſa nobiliſsimi Regis Arthuri quae Anno Dominicae incarnationis</hi> 1278. <hi>decimo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Calendas Maij per Dominum Edvardum Regem Angliae illustrem hic fuerunt ſic collocatae, praeſentibus Leonora ſereniſsima ejuſeum Regis conſorte, &amp; filia Domini Ferandi Regis Hiſpaniae, Magiſtro VVilliam de Middleton nunc Norwicenſi electo, Magiſtro Thoma de Becke Archidiacono Dorſitenſi, &amp; predicti regis Theſaurario, Domino Henrico &amp; Laſciae Comite Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colniae, Domino Amideo comite Subaudiae, &amp; multis magnatibus Angliae.</hi> Thus farre the Moonke of <hi>Glaſtenbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Warren</hi> or <hi>de Ware,</hi> Abbat of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> was made Abbat about <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1260. being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 44. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, who was made Treaſurer as hath <hi>Iohn de Everſden, An. Dom.</hi> 1280. being the 8. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, which yeare 1280. ſome doe falſely make to fall in 10. ſome in 11. of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, which contrariety hath onely riſen by the default of the tranſcriber. But moſt certaine it is, that he was Treaſurer in the 9. 11. and part of 12. of the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt. This man going to <hi>Rome</hi> for his conſecration brought from thence certaine workemen and rich purphury ſtones whereof and by whom hee made that rare pavement containing a diſcourſe of the whole world, which is at this day moſt beautifull, and to be ſeene at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> before the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15042:60"/>
table, a thing of that ſingularity, curiouſneſſe, and rareneſſe, that <hi>England</hi> hath not the like againe, in which pavement are circularly written in letters of braſſe, theſe Ten verſes following.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Si lector poſita prudenter cuncta revolvat</l>
               <l>Hinc finem primi, mobilis inveniet</l>
               <l>Sepes trina canes &amp; equos, homines ſuper addas</l>
               <l>Cervos &amp; corvos, aquilas immania cete</l>
               <l>Mundum quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſequens praeeuntis triplicat annos</l>
               <l>Sphericus archetypum globum hic monſtrat microcoſmum</l>
               <l>Chriſti milleno, bis centeno duodeno</l>
               <l>Cum ſexageno ſubductis quatuor anno</l>
               <l>Tertius Henricus, Rex, urbs Odoricus &amp; abbas</l>
               <l>Hos compegere purphyreos lapides.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which Abbot with thoſe workemen, and thoſe ſtones did alſo frame the ſhrine of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, with theſe verſes carved out of ſtone and alſo guilded ſet about the ſame Shrine or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Anno milleno Domini cum Septuageno</l>
               <l>Et bis centeno, cum completo quaſi deno</l>
               <l>Hoc opus eſt factum, quod Petrus duxit in actum</l>
               <l>Romanus civis, Homo, cauſam noſcere ſi vis</l>
               <l>Rex fuit Henricus, ſancti praeſentis amicus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This Abbat died the ſecond day of <hi>December</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1283. being the 12. of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, after that hee had governed the Monaſtery 23. yeares and more, and was buried there at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> in the aforeſaid plaine pavement of Purphury
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15042:60"/>
on the North ſide neere unto the Tombe (as is yet well to be ſeene) of <hi>Odomer</hi> or <hi>Aimer de Valence</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> on which grave is ingraven this briefe <hi>Epitaph</hi> here inſuing.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Abbas Richardus de Wara qui requieſcit</l>
               <l>Hic portat lapides, quos hic portavit ab urbe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Wenlocke</hi> Abbat of <hi>Westm.</hi> whom <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Weſtm</hi> calleth <hi>William de Wenlock,</hi> was made Abbath of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> after the death of <hi>Richard de Ware,</hi> and was Treaſurer to King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, as hath the Regiſter of the lives of the Abbat of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and other records that I have ſeene. Which office it ſeemeth hee had meane time be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tweene the 12. and 14. yeares of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, as I ſuppoſe. This man after that he had beene Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat 26. yeares lacking ſixe dayes, died the 25. day of <hi>December</hi> on the Chriſtmas day at night in his mannor of <hi>Piriford</hi> in <hi>Glouceſterſhire</hi> in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Edward</hi> (which was <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1307. and was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> beſides the high Altar then ſtanding without the South dore of Saint <hi>Edwards</hi> Shrine before the Presbiterie there under a plaine pavement, &amp; a Marble ſtone decently ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this Epitaph to his high commendation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Abbas Walterus jacet hic ſub marmore tectus</l>
               <l>Non fuit Auſterus, ſed mitis, famine rectus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A Biſhop of <hi>Coventrie</hi> and <hi>Lichfield</hi> was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15042:61"/>
of <hi>England</hi> in the 14. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, being <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1286. in whoſe place the ſame yeare came <hi>Iohn Kerkbie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Kerkbie</hi> Deane of <hi>Winburne</hi> and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Coventrie</hi> and Treaſurer to King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, was on the ſeventh Kalends of <hi>August</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1286. being the 14. yeare of the ſaid <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> (then at <hi>Paris</hi>) made Biſhop of <hi>Elye,</hi> whom <hi>Leland</hi> the Refiner of all names doth in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon his ſong of the Swan, in the word <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelſega,</hi> thus terme <hi>Iohannes Chirchebius Epiſcopus Anguillarinus Regi a theſauris.</hi> This man was Treaſurer in the 16, 17, and part of 18, of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in which yeare (as it ſeemeth) being part of <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1290. This Biſhop died the 7. Kalends of Aprill, after that hee had beene Biſhop three yeeres ſome moneths and ſome dayes, and was buried by <hi>Walpoole</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> in the Church of <hi>Elie,</hi> on the north part of the queere, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de Marchia</hi> or <hi>Gulielmus Martius,</hi> was Treaſurer in Eaſter terme in the 18. of <hi>Edw.</hi> the firſt, in which office he continued about 5. yeares, &amp; was removed from that place in the 23. of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> Baron of the Exchequer, with the two Chamberlaines executed al functions of that office untill a new Treaſurer was made this <hi>William de Marchia</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Bathe</hi> and <hi>Welles</hi> in <hi>An.Do.</hi> 1293. being the 22. of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in which See hee remained almoſt 10.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15042:61"/>
yeares; and died in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1302. being about the 32. of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, &amp; was buried in the Church of <hi>VVells</hi> in the wall, betweene the doore of the Cloiſter, and the Altar of Saint <hi>Martin,</hi> at whoſe Tombe in times paſt (as the nature of that cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous age did haſtily beleeve) were many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles done, as ſome have left in memory to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VValter Langhstane</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry</hi> was made Treaſurer after <hi>William de Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia</hi> in 23. <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in which office he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued (as I gather) during the life of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, which fell in the 35. of his raigne being <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1307. and was then removed and impriſoned in the Tower with two men onely by <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond then comming to the Crowne, becauſe the ſaid <hi>Walter Langstone</hi> had cauſed <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt to impriſon, and as ſome have to baniſh this new King, for breaking downe the Parkes of the ſaid Biſhop. During the time that this <hi>Peter de Willeby</hi> was under-Treaſurer or Livetenant of the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for the words be <hi>Locum tenens theſaurarij</hi> in 30. 31, and 32. <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, this <hi>Walter</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1295. being 23. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and the ſame yeare that he was made Treaſurer: he died about <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1321. being about the 14. yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the ſecond to which Biſhop the Barons of <hi>Cobham</hi> were heires, being deſcended from <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> the Siſter and heire of <hi>Iohn Peverell,</hi> the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and heire of this <hi>Walter Langhſtane,</hi> which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15042:62"/>
               <hi>Margaret</hi> was married to Sir <hi>William de La Poole</hi> of <hi>Aſhby</hi> Knight, from whom the Lord <hi>Cobham</hi> iſſue. In this mans time of being Treaſurer dyed King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, for whom were theſe verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dum viguit (Rex) &amp; valuit tua magna poteſtas</l>
               <l>Fraus latuit, pax magna fuit, regnavit honeſtas</l>
               <l>Scotos Edvardus dum vixit ſuppeditavit</l>
               <l>Tenuit, afflixit, depreſsit, dilaniavit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Reynolds,</hi> Schoolemaſter to <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> &amp; after of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and Chanceller of <hi>England</hi> was advanced to the place of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1307. after which in the yeare 1308. hee was made Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> he continued in the office of Treaſurer untill ſome part of the 4. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, at what time came in his place <hi>Iohn Sandall,</hi> who was Livetennant unto the ſaid <hi>Walter</hi> in place of the Treaſurer, as appeareth by many writs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected unto him by the name of <hi>Iohn Sandall Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum tenenti Willimi Epiſcopi Wigorniae.</hi> Of him is more ſpoken in the Chancellors of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn de Sandall</hi> being Clerke <hi>Scutifer Regis,</hi> Chanceller of the Exchequer, and Chanceller of <hi>England</hi> having beene before under Treaſurer, or Deputy for the high Treaſurer, came now in the fourth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, to bee made chiefe Treaſurer, and entred into that office in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15042:62"/>
               <hi>Eaſter</hi> tearme about the beginning of the 4. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. But in the yeare following, which was in the fifth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, hee gave place to another. Hee was choſen Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in the ninth yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, being in <hi>An Do.</hi> 1316. Of whom thus writeth <hi>Anonymus, M.S. Obierunt Epiſcopus Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton &amp; Elie viri ſacra profeſsione inſigniti, quorum primo ſucceſsit Iohannes de Sandall Cancellarius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae vir cunctis affabilis &amp; neceſſarius communitati; Secundo ſucceſsit Iohannes Hothum ſcaccar. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, vir ſi quidem ſcientiae penitus ignarus, qui ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim epiſcopatus aſcenſo culmine ad honorum pariter &amp; officij theſaurarij Rex in ſui favorem ſublimavit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter Norwich</hi> Knight Treaſurer in the 5. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. and afterward in Eaſter tearme in the 8. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. did on the third of <hi>October</hi> receive the office of Treaſurerſhip, and tooke his oath before the Barons &amp; Chamberleynes of the Exchequer, to behave himſelfe well and faithfully in the ſame office which he had received by Letters Patents dated at yorke the 26. of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> in the eight yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which he kept not long at that time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Sandall,</hi> was the ſecond time Lord Treaſurer in ſixt and ſeventh yeare of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the ſecond: This man being Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> was Treaſurer. Of him ſee more in the Chancellers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter de Norwich</hi> being Treaſurer as before in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15042:63"/>
the eight yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond did not long enjoy the ſame, but as I ſuppoſe grave place to <hi>Iohn Drokensford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Drokensford</hi> the 14. Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> had as I have read the great ſeale delivered unto him, and was alſo Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> but becauſe I finde not as yet in what yeare, although it were in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, I cannot ſet downe the certainety. Of whom thus writeth the Regiſter of the Biſhops of <hi>Bath. Iohannes Drokensford Theſaurarius,</hi> 14. <hi>Bathon Epiſcopus poſt Walterum Haſelſhawes, ſucceſsit in Epiſcopatum Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon, annis.</hi> 19. <hi>iſte epiſcopatum pluribus aedificijs inſignivit, francheſias per regis epiſcopatus conceſſas, non ſolum litterarie renovavit, ſed etiam ampliavit, &amp; quo additationem &amp; exaltationem parentelae ſuae fere fuit aequalis praediceſſori ſuo Roberto Bornell, &amp; Welliae ſepelitur ante altare ſancti Iohannis Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Hothum</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie,</hi> as is before noted out of one anonymall Chronicle, obteyned the place and honour of Treaſurerſhip in the 11. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, which hee did not long enjoy, for in the Michaelmas Tearme in the the 12. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, came <hi>William VValwaine.</hi> Of this <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> is mention made in the diſcourſe of the Chancellers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVilliam VValwaine,</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 12. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, about <hi>An.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15042:63"/>
Dom.</hi> 1318. was (as it ſhould ſeeme) for his negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and unworthines removed at the Parliament at yorke, in ſuch ſort as he poſſeſſed not that place (as I conceive) above halfe a yeare: for in the ſame twelfth yeare came the Biſhop of <hi>VVincheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Stratford,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>VVincheſter,</hi> upon the removing of <hi>VValwaine</hi> was in the 12. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, admitted into the office of Treaſurerſhip, untill the King ſhould otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. Which Biſhop found out in the Treaſury above Twenty nine Pound Seventeene ſhillings eight pence, which might bee the cauſe of diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of <hi>VValwaine,</hi> who had over prodigally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed the Kings Treaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VValter Stapleton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi> was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in the 13. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1319. In which I ſuppoſe he contynued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the 15. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1321.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VValter Norwich</hi> Knight, was the Third tyme made Treaſurer, which place he enjoyed in 15. <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1321. or thereabouts, <hi>VValſingham</hi> ſaith, that in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third. <hi>Obijt VVilliam de Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger Northborrow Scutifer</hi> or keeper of the ſeale being taken by the <hi>Scots</hi> at the battell of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocsbourne</hi> about the ſeventh yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1313. was alſo Clerke of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15042:64"/>
Wardrobe, and Treaſurer in the ſixteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 2. being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1322. Of whom thus writeth one <hi>Anonimall</hi> Cronicle. <hi>M.S. An. Do.</hi> 1321. <hi>Obijt VValterus de Langtone Epiſcopus Ceſtren cui ſucceſsit in epiſcopatus honore per viam impreſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; ambitionis Rogerus Northburgh Clericus de regis garderobia, ſibi regis in cunctis faventibus aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilio &amp; voluntate.</hi> I have read of one <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Northburgh</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> that died in thirty three yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1359, which perhaps ſhould bee this <hi>Roger North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow. Godfrey</hi> being by the tranſcriber placed in ſtead of <hi>Roger,</hi> but I will not at this time define a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certainety thereof, although I finde another note of one <hi>Roger Northburgh</hi> conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1321. who ſate in that See 38. yeares, which 38. yeares ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the other in which this <hi>Roger</hi> was made Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop doe make up the number of 1359. in which it is ſaid that <hi>Godfrey Northborow</hi> died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VValter Stapleton,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi> the ſecond tyme Treaſurer in the 18. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and before was removed in Eaſter Terme in the ſame yeare. In which Eaſter Terme was <hi>VVilliam</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> alſo made Treaſurer, as is proved by the <hi>Pell</hi> of <hi>Exitus,</hi> that Terme being thus intituled. <hi>De Termino Paſchae An.</hi> 18. <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. <hi>tam tempore VV. epiſcopi Exon, quam VV. archi-Epiſcopi Eborum.</hi> This Walter being elected to the Biſhoppricke of <hi>Exeter</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1307. did ſit in that place twenty yeares, and was beheded at the comming into <hi>England</hi> of Queene <hi>Iſabell</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15042:64"/>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond in the yeare 1326. The cauſe of whoſe beheading was, for that hee had procured the baniſhment of the ſaid Queene <hi>Iſabell</hi> and of her ſonne Prince <hi>Edward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVilliam Melton</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> made Lord Treaſurer in Eaſter Terme in the 18. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond kept the ſame office untill the depoſition of himſelfe from that place, and of his Maſter from his Kingdome in the twentieth yeare of the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, and then gave place to <hi>Iohn Stratford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Stratford,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>VVincheſter</hi> was the ſecond time made Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 20. yeare of the depoſed King <hi>Edward,</hi> after the death of <hi>VValter Stapleton,</hi> This <hi>Iohn</hi> the 14. day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> in the twentieth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, comming into the Exchequer brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kings patent or open Writ, or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, under the ſeale of <hi>Edward</hi> the Kings eldeſt ſon, to witnes his election &amp; creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that place of Treaſurer, the tenor of which writt, I have thought good to ſet downe, becauſe it was done by the ſon, in the fathers name, and under the Teſte of the ſon, the father yet being King in ſhew, but the ſonne indeede as governer of the Realme, which title hee enjoyed, untill that hee moſt unnaturally, by the malice of his mother, the ambition of himſelfe, and the flattery of his followers, had depoſed his father. The tenor of which writt, was in theſe words as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15042:65"/>
               <hi>Edwardus Rex Angliae, &amp; dominus Hiberniae, baronibus &amp; camerarijs ſuis de ſcaccario ſuo ſalutem. Quum pro eo quod venerabilis pater. VV. archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus Eborum nuper theſaurarius ſcaccarij praedicti, circa diverſa negotia in partibus borealibus eſt occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, quo minus intendere poſsit ad ea quae ad officium illud in dicto ſcaccario pertinent exercenda. Conſtitue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus venerabilem patrem Iohannem Wintonienſem epiſcopum, tenentem locum theſaurarij ſcaccarij prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicti, quouſque de officio illo aliter duximus ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Percipendo in eodem officio (dum illud ſic tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit) feodum conſuetum prout in literis noſtris paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus epiſcopo praefato inde confectis plenius contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Vobis mandamus quod ipſum epiſcopum ad offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um admittatis, &amp; ei in his quae ad officium praedictum pertineant intendatis in forma praedicta. Teſte Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardo filio nostro primogenito cuſtode regni noſtri, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Hereford Sexto die Novembris, anno regni noſtri viceſsimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam Tarleton,</hi> or <hi>de Orleton,</hi> borne in <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-ſhire,</hi> being <hi>Decretorum Doctor,</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Hereford</hi> by the Pope at <hi>Avinion</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1317. about the 10. or 11. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, being hee that made the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for the depoſition of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and wrote the amphibologicall Epiſtle for the death of the King, conteyning theſe words; <hi>(Regem occidere nolite timere bonum eſt)</hi> which hath by a comma or point made at <hi>Timere,</hi> one ſenſe, and by a comma made at <hi>Nolite,</hi> another ſence. Which <hi>Adam</hi> was made Lord Treaſurer in the firſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15042:65"/>
yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1326. in which office he continued not long, for in the Eaſter terme of the ſaid King, came <hi>Henry</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lincolne.</hi> This man was made Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1335. being the ninth of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which ſeate he ſate 12. yeares The death of which <hi>Adam,</hi> (who gave <hi>Heming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> parſonage to the Church of <hi>Hereford</hi>) Sir <hi>Thomas De la More,</hi> doth moſt plentifully ſet forth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Burwaſh,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> deſcended of the Lord <hi>Burghurst</hi> his Family called Lord <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſh,</hi> was Lord Treaſurer in Eaſter terme in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1327. in which office he continued untill 2. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and was afterwards removed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hereford</hi> injoyed the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable office of Lord Treaſurer in the third yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1329. but in the yeare following another came in place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Woodhouſe</hi> poſſeſſed the roome of the high Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fourth yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1330. And was alſo Treaſurer ſome part of Michaelmas terme in the fift yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, who in the yeare following did give place to another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> was againe Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fift yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1331. and enjoyed that place
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15042:66"/>
ſome part of Michaelmas Terme in the ſaid yeare, after whom came the Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> was made Treaſurer in Michaelmas Terme in the fift yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which tearme there had beene three Lord Treaſurers ſucceſſively, (a thing ſeldome or never heard, which office this Biſhop kept all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas Tearme in the ſixt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1332. and ſomewhat more in the end, yet yeelding that honour to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert le Ailſtone,</hi> being Lord Treaſurer in the ſeventh yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third being <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1333. continued in the ſame office untill the tenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1336. which was about three yeares, the ſame being a longer time then any other had poſſeſſed that place, ſince the beginning of the raigne of the ſaid King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Burwaſh,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> was againe Treaſurer the tenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1336. in which yeare (as hath <hi>Scala cronicorum</hi>) the King holding his Parliament at <hi>London,</hi> was adviſed by his Counſell to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his title to the Crowne of <hi>France.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon King <hi>Edward</hi> ſent Ambaſſadors, to the Duke of <hi>Bavier</hi> Emperor, which had married the other ſiſter to the Earle of <hi>Hannalt,</hi> (as King <hi>Edward</hi> the third had married one) for ſurety of aliance, and to retaine noble men about him with no ſmall charge,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15042:66"/>
which ambaſſadors were <hi>Henry Burgwaſh</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> and the Earles <hi>William Mountacute</hi> of <hi>Sarum,</hi> and <hi>William Clinton</hi> of <hi>Huntington,</hi> who returned to the Parliament at <hi>London</hi> with their anſwer well liked. Of this man ſee more in the Chancellers, being yet after his ambaſſage Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer for ſome part of the 11. yeare of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard de Bury,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> did enjoy the honour of Lord Treaſurer in the 11. yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third, hee was a man of great gravity and much eſteemed of the nobility and gentlemen of the North. Of this man is more ſoken of in the Chancellers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de la Zouch,</hi> borne of the noble houſe of the Lord <hi>Zouch</hi> was Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> in the 12. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1338. he being Biſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was vicegerent to the King in the North parts in the 20. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1346. at what time he tooke <hi>David Bruce</hi> King of the Scotts. This man went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and after a long contention between him, and <hi>William Kelſlye, Kelsbie,</hi> or <hi>Kelſey</hi> (for all theſe different names, are found in Authors) touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Archbiſhopprick of <hi>Yorke,</hi> he was after two yeares thus ſpent conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt, after which this <hi>William</hi> in the 11. yeare of his Biſhoppricke being long troubled with a grievous diſeaſe, began the worke of a Chapell on the South ſide adjoyning to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15042:67"/>
Church of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Yorke,</hi> where he purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee buried, but died before it was finiſhed, and lieth interred in the ſaid Church before the Altar of <hi>Edward</hi> the confeſſor.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Sadington</hi> Knight, was Treaſurer in the fourteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1340. There was one Robert Sading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton living about this time, of whom is more men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Chancellors of <hi>England,</hi> but as yet I well know not whether they were both one man or noe, ſith Authors may miſplace <hi>Robert</hi> for <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> as they have often done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Northborow,</hi> being at that time (as I judge) Biſhop of <hi>Coventry,</hi> was Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 14. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1340. in which yeare hee was removed, whom with the Chancellor the King ment afterward (as after ſhall appeare) to have ſent into Flanders as Pledges for money that the King ought there. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whom as I ſuppoſe, that <hi>Sadington</hi> came in place</p>
            <p>A Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> was Lord Treaſure of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the fifteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1341. in which office he did not long continue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Perning</hi> or <hi>Pernicke</hi> was Lord Treaſurer in the Eaſter tearme in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1341. being the fifteenth yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which yeare alſo hee was made Chanceller, and ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15042:67"/>
continued both offices a while untill the ſixteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, as I gather by all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of times, records, and hiſtories, who in the ſeventeenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1343. (as appeareth by the bookes of the Law) being Chancellor, delivered a record with his hands into the Court of the Kings Bench; Of this man more is ſet downe in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger Northborow</hi> (as I take it) being then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Coventry,</hi> did honorably poſſeſſe the place of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the ſixteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1342. Of whom thus writeth <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> in the life of <hi>Iohn Stratford</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury. Ibi</hi> (meaning at the Tower) <hi>concilium initum eſt, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque definitum, ut Archiepiſcopus &amp; epiſcopus Ciceſtreſcis regni Cancellarius &amp; Coventrenſis The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurarius una cum alijs ſatellitibus &amp; lictoribus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſi, ad publicam cuſtodiam rerum a ſe, abſente rege, geſtarum rationem reddituri ducerentur. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne accedunt ſatellites Lametham, ſed archiepiſcopus ei pridie deceſſerat, tum Londinum reverſi, Couentren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem &amp; Ciceſtrenſem epiſcopos cum alijs deſignatis capiunt, captos ad turrim deducunt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de Cuſans</hi> being Lord Treaſurer in the ſeventeenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1343. continued in the ſame office all Michaelmas tearme in the eighteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third and <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1344. Betweene whom and <hi>Thomas
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15042:68"/>
Henley</hi> Abbat of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> was great contention about the Iuriſdiction of the hoſpital of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> in the pariſh of Saint <hi>Margaret</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which Hoſpitall is now a ſtately houſe belonging to the King, and built by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the manner of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> with a Parke walled about.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William de Edington,</hi> Lord Chancellor and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> was Lord Treaſurer in Eaſter Tearme in the nineteenth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1345. in which office he continued untill the 32. yeare o the ſaid King, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1358. being 14. yeares Hee was ſo ſurnamed of the place where hee wa borne, being the Towne of <hi>Edington</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> he was made Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> (as ſome have) about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1347. being about the 21. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third: This man choſen Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (but yet never Biſhop) died (as hath <hi>Walſingham</hi> in the fortieth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1366.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> was Lord Treaſurer in the 32. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1358. in which office hee continued in the 33. and 34. of the ſame King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simon Langham,</hi> being of the Priory of <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> made Abbat of that houſe, was ſhortly after made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> which office he held in the 35. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15042:68"/>
36. who being Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> (as hath <hi>Matthew Parker</hi>) was in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1361. being the thirty fifth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, by the Pope made Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> where he ſate five yeares, and was after in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1366, being in the 40. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, choſen Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and conſecrated in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1367. as ſaith the ſame <hi>Matthew Parker:</hi> On which day of his conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he demanded homage of the Earle <hi>Stafford</hi> of <hi>Thomas Roſſe, Iohn Tirhill, Robert Brockhill,</hi> and <hi>Raphe Sentleger</hi> Knights, for their Lands which they held of the Sea of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Shortly after which in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1368. being the 42. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, he was made Cardinall, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Avimere</hi> the 22 day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1376. being in the 50. yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and was buried beſides <hi>Avinion,</hi> in a place which he had raiſed from the foundation. Three yeares after which, his bones were brought to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where at this day hee hath a worthie Tombe on the ſouth ſide of the Shrine amongſt the Kings, on whoſe Tombe the Moonkes of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> did ſometime place this Epitaphe in the remembrance of him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Simon de Langham ſub petris his tumulatus</l>
               <l>Iſtius Eccleſiae monachus fuerat, prior, abbas</l>
               <l>Sede vacante fuit, electus Londonienſis</l>
               <l>Praeſul &amp; inſignis eligi, ſed poſtea primas</l>
               <l>Totius regni, magnus regis que miniſter</l>
               <l>Nam Theſaurarius &amp; Cancellarius ejus</l>
               <l>Ac Cardinalis in Roma Presbiter iſte</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15042:69"/>Poſt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Praeneſtinus eſt factus epiſcopus atque</l>
               <l>Nuntius ex parte Papae, tranſmittitur iſtuc</l>
               <l>Orbe dolente pater, quem nunc revocare nequimus</l>
               <l>Magdalanae feſto milleno ſeptuageno.</l>
               <l>Et ter centeno ſexto Chriſti ruit anno</l>
               <l>Hunc Deus abſolvat, de cunctis quae male geſsit</l>
               <l>Et meritis matris ſibi caelica gaudia donet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Of this man I have treated in the collection of all the Chancellers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Barret</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1362. being the 36. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third was Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 37. yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third, in which office he continued, being Treaſurer in Michaelmas Tearme in the 38. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, which fell in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1364. and ſo hee continued till the 43. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, ſtill Treaſurer. He was made Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1363. in which Biſhoppricke he remained three yeares, and was by <hi>Vrbane</hi> the 6. then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> tranſlated from <hi>Bath</hi> to <hi>Elie</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1366. being the 40. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. in which place hee ſate ſixe yeares, and being a very old man, and having beene Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer about ſixe yeares, hee died at <hi>Hatfield</hi> the ſeventh Ides of <hi>Iune</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1373. in the 47. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, hee was buried in the Church of <hi>Elie,</hi> beſides the high Altar on the ſouth part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas de Brantington</hi> being Treaſurer for the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15042:69"/>
King in the parts of <hi>Guiſnes martches,</hi> and <hi>Calis</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1367. being in the 41. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, was made Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi> by ſpeciall Letters of the King in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1358. being the 43. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and was Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England,</hi> in the 44. and 45. yeares of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third, which 45. beeing in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1371. he was in a Parliament at the Petition of the Lords removed, at which time alſo there paſſed a Law, that the Chancellor Treaſurer and Clarke of the Privy ſeale ſhould no more be ſpiritual men, but that ſecular men ſhould have thoſe offices.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Scroope,</hi> Lord of <hi>Bolton</hi> and Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>England,</hi> was Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 46. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and then gave place to Sir <hi>Robert Aſton</hi> Knight. This <hi>Richard</hi> made out of the ground the Caſtle of <hi>Bolton</hi> conſiſting of foure great ſtrong towers, &amp; of other ſtately lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which Caſtell was erecting 18. yeares, the charges whereof came yearely unto a Thouſand Marks, which was 18. thouſand Markes, or 12000. pound; which Caſtle hee finiſhed before <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the ſecond died. He bought the heire general of S. <hi>Quintine</hi> that was owner of <hi>Horneby</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Richmondſhire,</hi> which heire hee was content one <hi>Conyers</hi> a ſervant of his ſhould marry, and have the preferment of that ward, &amp; ſo <hi>Horneby</hi> Caſtle came to the <hi>Coniers,</hi> of which the firſt Lord was <hi>William Coniers,</hi> grandfather to him that died in the time of <hi>Queene Mary</hi> without heire male, whereby his inheritance came to his three daughters, which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15042:70"/>
               <hi>William</hi> the firſt Lord <hi>Coniers</hi> of that name did much coſt upon <hi>Horneby</hi> Caſtle being before but a meane thing. I have read of this Lord <hi>Scroope</hi> that hee had a ſonne called <hi>William,</hi> whereof wee will ſpeake more hereafter, that was Earle of <hi>Wiltsſhire,</hi> who being beheaded in his fathers life, left no iſſue behind him. After which the father ſurviving was made Treaſurer to the King, and died in honour; althoug he was not reſtored to his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chancellerſhip, but at what time he ſhould be the ſecond time Treaſurer (after the death of his ſonne <hi>William</hi>) in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. I cannot as yet certainely learne, But it may bee that hee was againe Treaſurer in the ninth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, for that I finde not by any former ſearch who then poſſeſſed that place. It ſeemeth that he had two wives, the one the daughter of the <hi>Lord Spenſer,</hi> the other the daughter of <hi>Michaell de la Poole</hi> Earle of <hi>Suffolke</hi> called <hi>Blanch.</hi> Hee had three ſonnes, for whom hee bought of the King the three daughters and heires of <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Tiptoft,</hi> whereof the eldeſt daughter <hi>Margaret</hi> was marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Roger</hi> his ſecond ſonne, the ſecond daughter was married to <hi>William</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, the third daughter called <hi>Milleſcent</hi> was married to <hi>Stephen</hi> the third ſonne of the ſaid <hi>Richard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert Aſhton</hi> Knight, Conſtable of <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle, and Lord warden of the Cinque Ports, was Lord Treaſurer in the 50. and 51. yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third in Michaelmas terme, which was the laſt Michaelmas tearme wherein the King
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15042:70"/>
raigned, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1376. of which name there was alſo one that was chiefe Baron in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, as I have read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Wake</hi> or <hi>Wakefield</hi> being made Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1375. being in the 49. yeare of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3. was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1376. in the 51. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which office hee continued part of Eaſter terme in the firſt yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1378. he died in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1395. as ſaith <hi>Walſingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Brantington</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter</hi> was made Lord Treaſurer in firſt yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond towards the latter end of Eaſter tearme, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1378. as I compute it, from which place he was ſhortly removed in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Surry</hi> made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the ſecond, whereof part fell in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1378. and part in 1379. continued about One yeare in the ſame, and then gave place to him, which poſſeſſed the ſame place laſt before him, he married <hi>Elizabeth</hi> daughter of <hi>VVilliam de Bohune</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton</hi> and <hi>Hereford,</hi> by whom hee had iſſue Thomas Earle of Arundell, <hi>Ioane</hi> maried to <hi>VVilliam Beuchampe</hi> Lord <hi>Aburgavennie, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> married to <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Mowbray, Margaret</hi> married to Sir <hi>Rowland Lenthall,</hi> and <hi>Alice</hi> married
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15042:71"/>
to <hi>Iohn Charleton</hi> Lord <hi>Powes.</hi> He dyed in the 21. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Brantington,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter</hi> was the third time made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the third yeare of the after depoſed King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and was removed from his office in the 4. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1380. after the account of ſuch, as begin the yeare on the 25. of <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Hales,</hi> chiefe Prior of the Knights of the Rhodes intituled by the name of the Knights of St. <hi>Iohns Ieruſalem</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> was Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fourth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the 2. in which office he continued during his life, for ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after hee came into that place, which I ſuppoſe he held in Eaſter tearme, and ſome monethes after, in the ſaid yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1381. the <hi>Rebels</hi> having ſpoyled the hoſpitall or famous colledge of thoſe Knights of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> by <hi>Smithfield</hi> neere unto <hi>London,</hi> amongſt other did fetch this <hi>Robert Hales</hi> out of the Tower of <hi>London</hi> (where the King then lay) and beheaded him on the Tower hill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugh Segrave</hi> Knight, whom <hi>Walſingham</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Regis ſeneſchallum,</hi> the Kings Steward, was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fifth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, who continued in the ſaid office, the 6, 7, 8. and ſome part of Michaelmas tearme in the 9. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, being in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1385.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15042:71"/>
               <hi>Iohn Fortham</hi> Canon, being Secretary to the King, was made Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> the 29. day of <hi>May</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1381. being in the fourth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and was inthronized in <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> in <hi>An. Dom</hi> 1382. being in the ſixt yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond. This man was made Lord Treaſurer in Michaelmas tearme in the ninth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1385. and ſo continued part of the 10. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, until he was by parliament diſcharged. He was tranſlated from the Biſhoppricke of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to <hi>Elie,</hi> by <hi>Boniface</hi> the Pope the firſt Calends of <hi>October,</hi> as hath the booke of <hi>Durham</hi> 1389. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the 12. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond; but as ſaith the booke of <hi>Elie,</hi> 1388. being in the 13 yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, which both may bee true, becauſe the one may have relation to the yeare of his tranſlation, and the other to the yeare of his inthronization, both which many times hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in ſeverall yeares of many other Biſhops. He was Biſhop of <hi>Elie</hi> 37. yeares three moneths, and foure dayes, and dyed a very old man the 13. of <hi>December</hi> in his Mannor of <hi>Durham</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1425. falling in the fourth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Gilbert,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hereford</hi> was by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made Lord Treaſurer in the 10. yeare of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the ſecond, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1386. in which office hee continued the eleventh and all Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Tearme in the 12. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and the 21. day of <hi>March</hi> following; after which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15042:72"/>
he was againe removed, and then hee with twelve more were appointed by commiſſion to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of the whole Realme under the King, of whom thus writeth on Anonymall Chronicle. <hi>M. S. Is fuit in ordine praedicatorum vir qui plus lingua quam fide regebat.</hi> Which Biſhop (as I ſuppoſe) was removed to Saint <hi>Davids,</hi> after that hee had beene thirteene yeares Biſhop of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Brantington,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter.</hi> I have read that the Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter</hi> was made Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in the twelfth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the removing of <hi>Iohn Gilbert,</hi> which Biſhop of <hi>Excester</hi> could not be <hi>Edmond Gifford,</hi> as ſome falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name him, for there is no ſuch man, as I can find in the catalogue of all the Biſhops of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it <hi>Edmund Stafford</hi> for hee was not made Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter</hi> untill the 20. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1395. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day before King <hi>Richard</hi> began the twenty one yeare of his raigne, which is eight yeares after the time whereof we now intreate. Wherefore it muſt needs bee <hi>Thomas Brantington,</hi> for hee being conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Excester</hi> the tenth day of <hi>March</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1370. being in the 44. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, &amp; governing that See 24. yeares, till <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1395. in which came <hi>Edmund Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Keeper of the Privie Seale, it muſt be that the Biſhop of <hi>Excester</hi> being Treaſurer in the twelfth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond falling in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1388. it was this man <hi>Brantington,</hi> and that he was the fourth time made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:15042:72"/>
about the 18. yeare after that he was made Biſhop of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> who died in the yeare 1395. as hath <hi>Ypodigma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Gilbert,</hi> Biſhop of Saint <hi>Davids</hi> in <hi>Wales</hi> was Lord Treaſurer in the 13. and 14. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond: Of whom there is ſomewhat ſpoken before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Waltham,</hi> of whom there is large mention in the diſcourſe of the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in the life of <hi>Will. Courtney,</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Rolls</hi> in the ſixt yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and keeper of the Privie ſeale, after which he was Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 15, 16, 17, and part of the 18. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, for hee died in Michaelmas Tearme in the 18. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1395. others ſay, 1394. Of whom thus writeth <hi>Walſingham. Hoc Anno</hi> (which was 1395) <hi>obijt Iohannes de Waltham Epiſcopus Sarum, &amp; regni theſaurarius, qui tantum Regi complacuerit, ut etiam multis licet murmuranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus apud monaſterium inter reges meruit ſepulturam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger Walden,</hi> ſometimes Secretary to the King, and Treaſurer of the Towne of <hi>Calis</hi> in the twelfth yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, was made Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in the eighteenth yeare of the ſaid King, about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1365. in which office he continued in the 22. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond. Hee was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and made Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> but after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and depoſed, and thereupon was by Pope
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15042:73"/>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſeventh made Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in the tenth yeare of <hi>December</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1404. being in the ſixt yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, in the which Biſhopricke hee continued one yeare, and died in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1406. being buried at S. <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> Priory in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> who of a poore man (as ſaith <hi>Walſingham</hi>) was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>G.</hi> Biſhop of Saint <hi>Davids</hi> in <hi>Wales</hi> was Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the twentie two yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, which Biſhop I ſuppoſe to bee <hi>Guy de Moone,</hi> whom the booke <hi>Ypodigma &amp; Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Walſingham</hi> call Biſhop of Saint <hi>Davids,</hi> and ſay, that hee died in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1407. writing in this ſort. <hi>Eodem anno Guido de Mone Menevenſis epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus praeſentis lucis ſenſit eclipſim, qui dum vixit mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum malorum cauſa fuit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Scroope</hi> Knight, Vicechamberleine to <hi>Rchard</hi> the ſecond was Lord Treaſurer, hee bought of <hi>William Montacute</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> the Ile of <hi>Man</hi> with the Crowne thereof. Hee was one of thoſe to whom King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, let the Kingdome to farme, he was Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 22. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and was after created Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> in the ſaid 21. yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, in <hi>An. Dom</hi> 1397. Hee was after beheaded at <hi>Briſtow</hi> in the twenty three yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond: Of which <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Scroope</hi> and others, thus writeth that worthy Poet <hi>Iohn Gower</hi> in his hiſtorie of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15042:73"/>
commonly taken as part of his booke intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Vox Clamantis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Dux probus audaci vultu cum plebe ſequaci</l>
               <l>Regnum ſcrutatur, ſi proditor inveniator</l>
               <l>Sic tres exoſos, magis omnibus ambitioſos</l>
               <l>Regni tortores, invenerat ipſe priores.</l>
               <l>Enſe repercuſſi pereunt, Gren, Scrop, quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Buſsi</l>
               <l>Hi qui regales fuerant cum rege ſodales.</l>
               <l>Scrop. comes &amp; miles, cujus Bristolia viles</l>
               <l>Actus declarat, quo mors ſua fata pararat</l>
               <l>Gren quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſorte pari, ſtatuit dux decapitari</l>
               <l>Buſsi convictus ſimiles quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuſtinet ictus</l>
               <l>Vnanimes mente, pariter mors una repente</l>
               <l>Hos tres proſtravit gladius, quos fine voravit</l>
               <l>Sicut &amp; egerunt alijs, ſic hi ceciderunt</l>
               <l>Quo dux laudatur, regnumque per omne jocatur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Northbury</hi> made Lord Treaſurer in the firſt yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1399. and continued in the ſame in the third yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth in which yeare he was keeper of the Privie gardrobe in the Tower alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Bowet</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> about <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1401. being in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, in which biſhoprick he continued 8. yeares, and was after at the Kings inſtance in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1407. about the eight of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth removed to <hi>Yorke,</hi> This man was Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fourth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1403. in which place hee continued not above a yeare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15042:74"/>
               <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Roſſe</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Roſſe</hi> did poſſeſſe the honorable place of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fifth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1404. and ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gave place to the Lord <hi>Furnivall.</hi> Hee marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Margaret</hi> daughter of <hi>Fitzallen,</hi> Lord <hi>Matra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> hee had iſſue <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Roſſe</hi> ſlaine in <hi>France</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1421. about the ninth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and many other Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Furnivall</hi> kept the place and office of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 6, 7. and ſome part of the 8. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, as in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas tearme of the ſaid 8. yeare falling in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1406. after which this Lord <hi>Furnivall,</hi> who had the cuſtodie of the Caſtle and honor of <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> being in the Kings hands by reaſon of the wardſhip and minority of <hi>Edmond Mortimer</hi> Earle of <hi>March,</hi> was (as it ſeemeth) removed from the Treaſurerſhip, in whoſe roome ſucceeded the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>London.</hi> To theſe Lord <hi>Furnivalls</hi> did <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivalls Inne</hi> in <hi>Holborne</hi> ſometime appertaine as their manſion houſe, being now an Inne of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery for young Students of the Law, and Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis, and belonging to <hi>Lincolnes Inne</hi> in <hi>Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas Bubwith,</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1406. being in the eight yeare of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fourth, muſt bee that Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> (as farre as I can yet conceive) who was Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England</hi> in Michaelmas tearme in the 8.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15042:74"/>
yeare, the office of the Treaſurer remained in the Kings hands, and the Accompts of the ſaid terme goe under the ſame title of being in the Kings hands.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Scroope</hi> Lord of <hi>Bolton</hi> (wherof is ſo much ſpoken before) was as I ſuppoſe the ſecond time made Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the ninth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth; whereunto I am induced by this reaſon. That firſt the King would not keepe that office ſo long in his hands as almoſt amounted to Two yeares, but that he would beſtow the ſame upon ſome other: Secondly, for that I reade that this <hi>Richard Scroope</hi> father to <hi>William Scroope</hi> Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> beheaded by this <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, before he came to the Crowne at <hi>Briſtow,</hi> in the laſt yeare of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and in the firſt of this Kings raigne, was after the death of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> made Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> and ſo died in honour. Thirdly for that I cannot ſee how he might be Treaſurer in any yeare ſince the death of the ſaid <hi>William</hi> untill the ninth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. And laſtly, for that I cannot in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord or other author find any other man mentioned to ſupply that place in this yeare, for which cauſes I have attempted to beſtow him here, and that rightly for any thing that I can yet learne.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Tiptoft,</hi> or <hi>Tiptote</hi> Knight did poſſeſſe the place and office of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in Michaelmas tearme in the tenth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1408.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15042:75"/>
               <hi>Henry</hi> Lord Scroope of <hi>Maſham</hi> and of <hi>Flaxfleet</hi> was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in 11. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1410. as hath <hi>Walſingham,</hi> in which office he continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the death of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, which happened in the fourteenth yeare of the ſaid King, and in <hi>Anno Domino</hi> 1412. after the account of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but 1413. after the account of ſuch as doe begin the yeare in <hi>Ianuary.</hi> Hee rebelled againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, and was beheaded at <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton</hi> in the third yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1415. the laſt of <hi>Iuly.</hi> Of which <hi>Henry</hi> ſo conſpiring againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth. I finde theſe verſes in a written booke of parchment, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Extractum breve de cronica Thomae Helmham Prioris Lenton de tempore regis Henrici Quinti.</hi> In which verſes by the capitall letters, are ſet downe the names of the principall conſpirators, and the yeare of our Lord, wherein the ſame was done, being 1413. The greater Roman capitall letters in the third verſe ſerving for the yerae of Chriſt, and for the name <hi>Zore,</hi> derived of this word <hi>Cor</hi> in the 4. verſe, and the Engliſh capitall letters only ſerving for the names of the perſons in this ſort couched together for common capacity.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mox rex navigium parat ut mare tranſeat armis</l>
               <l>Scrop furit Henricus proditione fremens.</l>
               <l>SCrVtans Conſpirat RIMatVr OlenCla Plebi</l>
               <l>Rumpe Iugo COR Avens Res Dabit Vltra Sonum</l>
               <l>EIA Ruit Gens Avita Malis Opus Hoſte Triumphat</l>
               <l>Vota voluntatis ſic ſacre Chriſte tuae</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:15042:75"/>Verſibus his quinque praetactis Traditionem</l>
               <l>Lector ſcire potes, hinc repetendo ſtude</l>
               <l>Hi tres Richardus Zorc, Henry Scrup<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Thomas Gray</l>
               <l>In regem ſurgunt proditione pares</l>
               <l>Munere Francorum corrupti terga dedere</l>
               <l>Iusto munus habet, vindice quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Fitzallen</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> was advanced to the office of the Lord Treaſurer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1413. being the 1. yeare of the raigne of the moſt victorious Prince King <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, in which office it ſeemeth that hee continued the 1, 2, and 3. of <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth. He in the yeare 140<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. being the ſeventh yeare of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the fourth, on the next day of the feaſt of Saint <hi>Katherine,</hi> married <hi>Beatrice</hi> the naturall daughter of the King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> by whom hee had no Iſſue, but left his ſiſters his heires and dyed in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1416. being in the third yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, and was buried in the Colledge at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Roger Leche,</hi> whom ſome call but not rightly as I ſuppoſe; Sir Philip <hi>Lech,</hi> being brother unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> was Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas and Eaſter tearme in the fourth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, being <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1416. He was at the ſeidge of <hi>Rone</hi> with this King <hi>Henry,</hi> in the ſixt yeare of his raigne, being alſo Treaſurer for the warres in that voyage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Fitzhugh,</hi> was advanced to the office
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15042:76"/>
of the Lord Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England</hi> in the fift yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1417. in which office hee continued as I gather untill the death of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the fift which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Auguſt</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1422</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Stafford</hi> Clerke was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the firſt yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1422. in which office hee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in Michelmas tearme in the fourth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt falling in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1425. hee was choſen Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> in the third yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1424. he was Chanceller of <hi>England,</hi> and removed to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> of whom is mention made in my diſcourſe of the Chancellers of <hi>England,</hi> and touching whom I will for this time onely ſet down here, what <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> writeth of him, in the life of <hi>Henry Chichely</hi> an Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Archiepiſcopus</hi> (ſaith he) in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1424. <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarienſis</hi> 12. <hi>Octob. clerum in eccleſia Paulina con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocavit, in ea Henricus Beauford Winton epiſcopus regni Cancellarius, &amp; Iohannes Stafford Bathonien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis electus epiſcopus regni theſaurarius, ad bellum Gallicum opem a clero petivit, &amp; interpoſita pauco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum dierum deliberatione. Wilhelmus Linwood offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialis curiae Cantuarienſis de arcubus hoc reſponſum ab inferiori clero Synodo acceptum epiſcopis declaravit, non poſſe penes cleri procuratores poteſtatem ſubſidium concedendi. Nam cum in dicta Synodo in ſingulis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocaeſibus conſtituti eſſent, clerus de ſolutionibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiendi licentiam expreſſe ademit, quia tantis tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15042:76"/>
diu pendendis ad magnam inopiam &amp; egeſtatem devenit. Itaque Cancellarius a ſuperiori Synodo ad inferiorem tranſiens, longa &amp; diſerta oratione, ac re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis jam minoris neceſsitate, ac de inſtanti in Gallia bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo egit, ac ne quicquam ſuaſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walter</hi> Lord <hi>Hungerford</hi> Knight of the garter the ſonne of Sir <hi>Thomas Hungerford</hi> Knight was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the fourth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1425. in which office hee contynued about ſixe yeares, untill ſome part of Michaelmas terme in the tenth of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, falling in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1431. Hee was alſo one of the Counſell to the ſaid King, of whom is Mention made by <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> in the life of <hi>Henry Chicheley</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>Proximo anno</hi> (which was about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1425) <hi>ſynodus ſub eodem archiepiſcopo</hi> 15. <hi>Aprilis inchoata eſt, Qua Iohanne Kempo Eboracenſi archiepiſcopo &amp; Waltero Hungerfordo Milite Regijs conſiliarijs (ille cancellario hoc theſaurario regni) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nomine poſtulantibus regi decimam conceſsit. Ac eiſdem his petentibus triennio poſt in recenti Synodo media decima regi a clero data eſt.</hi> This Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer married <hi>Katherine</hi> the daughter and heire of <hi>Thomas Peverell</hi> Knight, by whom he had iſſue <hi>Walter</hi> Lord <hi>Hungerford</hi> of <hi>Hatchberry</hi> Knight of the garter, that dyed without iſſue; Sir <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Hungerford</hi> of <hi>Hatchberry, Edmund Hungerford</hi> Knight, that died without iſſue, <hi>Margaret</hi> married to Sir <hi>Walter Rodney</hi> Knight, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Phillip Courtney</hi> Knight, which <hi>Robert</hi> Lord
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15042:77"/>
               <hi>Hungerford</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> his wife, <hi>Iohn Cheiney</hi> of <hi>Pim</hi> Eſquire, <hi>Iohn Mervin</hi> Eſquire, and others did (by the Kings licence granted unto them in the 11. yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth) build the hoſpitall of <hi>Hatchberry</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Scroope</hi> of <hi>Vpſall</hi> and <hi>Maſham</hi> made Lord Treaſurer in the tenth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1431. in which office hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued untill ſome part of the 12. yeare of the ſaid King, as I for this time doe gather. Of whom thus writeth <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> in the life of <hi>Henry Chich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> touching a Synod holden in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1430. at what time of the Clergie hee ſaith, that <hi>Iohannes Stafford epiſcopus Bathonienſis Cancellarius, &amp;c.</hi> D. <hi>Scroope Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarius regni nec non Wilhelmus Lindwood cuſtos pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vati ſigilli, pro rege ſubſidium poſtularunt, &amp; mediam decimam tandem aegre impetrarunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raphe</hi> Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Raph Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> Lord of <hi>Taterſhall,</hi> poſſeſſed the place of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in Eaſter tearme of the 12. yeare of the after depoſed King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1434. and ſo continued in that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice about tenne yeares following as I ſuppoſe in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1444. This man being knight was created Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and was lineally deſcended of one of the heires of <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Taterſhall</hi> that married one of the daughters and heires of <hi>William Dalbeny</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell.</hi> This <hi>Raph</hi> Lord Treaſurer died without iſſue, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15042:77"/>
made his Teſtament in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1454. being in the 33. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, after whoſe deceaſe the Inheritance came to the Three Auntes, being his heires, wherof the firſt was maried to the Lord <hi>Bardoffe</hi> ſtaine at <hi>Braunch ammore</hi> in <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the ſecond was married to Sir <hi>William Fitz-Williams</hi> Knight of the Sepulcher: the third <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> to Sir <hi>Iohn Cliſton</hi> Knight, and after his death to Sir <hi>Edmund Beneſted</hi> Knight, of one Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> I finde this note ſet downe by <hi>Leland. Dominus Radulphus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cromwell &amp; Matilda vxor ejus fundatores Collegij ſanctae Trinitatis de Tater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, quumque Roberti ordine domini erant de Tater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, hos ſequutus eſt Radulphus Comwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Ralphe Butler</hi> Knight of the garter, Lord <hi>Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> deſcended from <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Sudley,</hi> and <hi>William Butler</hi> Baron of <hi>Wem,</hi> which married <hi>Ioane</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and heire to <hi>Iohn Sudley Baron Sudley,</hi> did poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the honorable place of the Lord Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England,</hi> the ſeventh of <hi>Iuly</hi> in the 22. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1444. which office he kept about three yeares, for in 25. of the ſaid King, was the Biſhop of <hi>Carlile</hi> Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer. This <hi>Raphe</hi> Lord <hi>Sudley</hi> builded the Caſtle of <hi>Sudley,</hi> in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth was committed to priſon by the King, firſt ſending for him to come to his preſence. Whereupon hee going to the King, and reſting on an hill, from whence he did behold <hi>Sudley</hi> Caſtle ſaid. It is thou, it is thou, <hi>Sudley</hi> Caſtle, and not I which am the traitor: After which comming to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15042:78"/>
the King, hee reſigned the ſaid <hi>Sudley</hi> Caſtle into his handes. Which Caſtle came after to <hi>Iaſper</hi> Duke of <hi>Bedford,</hi> &amp; is now 1635. in the poſſeſſion of <hi>Giles Bridges</hi> Lord <hi>Shandois.</hi> This <hi>Ralph</hi> being made Baron in the 20. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt married <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the daughter of Sir <hi>Iohn Northberry</hi> by whom he had iſſue <hi>Thomas</hi> his ſon that died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue leaving his Two Siſters to bee his heires, whereof the Eldeſt daughter was married to Sir <hi>Iohn Northberry,</hi> whoſe heire generall was maried to <hi>John Halwell</hi> of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> who had iſſue <hi>Ioane</hi> his daughter and heire married to <hi>Edmund</hi> Lord <hi>Bray,</hi> of whoſe heires generall are deſcended, the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> Lord <hi>Chandos,</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund Verney,</hi> Knight Marſhall, Sir <hi>Percivall Hart</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> The other Siſter married to Sir <hi>Hamond Bellknap,</hi> of whom is deſcended the Lord <hi>Wootton</hi> of <hi>Bocton Maleherbe</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> The which <hi>Ralph</hi> Lord <hi>Butler</hi> of <hi>Sudley</hi> was vexilifer, and high butler of <hi>England,</hi> and ſteward in houſe to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marmaduke</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carlile,</hi> was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 25. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, in which office hee continued, about two yeares in the 27. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1448. (or as ſome have) 1449.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iames Fynes</hi> created at <hi>Bury Baron</hi> and of <hi>Say,</hi> of <hi>Seale,</hi> on the 3. of <hi>March,</hi> in the 25. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1446. was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle, and Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 28. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and was
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15042:78"/>
from thence removed, (as ſome have) in <hi>An.</hi> 29. of the ſaid King: And was by the Rebells of <hi>Kent Iacke Cade</hi> and his fellowes, taken of out the Tower to the <hi>Guildhall,</hi> where hee was arraigned before the Major and other the Kings Iuſtices, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be tried by his Peeres, was by the Rebells forceably taken from the Officers, and beheaded at the ſtandard in Cheape. Which his beheading ſome doe attribute to the 28. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1450. He had iſſue Sir <hi>William Fines</hi> Knight, and one daughter married to Sir <hi>William Cromer</hi> Knight, Sheriffe of <hi>Kent,</hi> beheaded at that time alſo with his father in law. Of which <hi>Cromer,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Cromer</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> Knight deſcended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Beuchamp</hi> a perſon of great worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe poſſeſſed the place of the Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England</hi> in the 29. and 30. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Tiptoft</hi> Earle of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> poſſeſſed the place of the Lord Treaſurer in the 31. and 32 yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt: Of whom is more mention made hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iames Butler</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iames</hi> Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> being Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> and <hi>Ormond,</hi> poſſeſſed the office of the Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 33. of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, falling in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1455.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> Vicount <hi>Bourchier,</hi> borne of the noble
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15042:79"/>
houſe of the <hi>Bourchiers</hi> the ſonne of <hi>William Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chier</hi> Earle of <hi>Ewe</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> was Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 33. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, in which office he did not long remaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Talbot</hi> Earle of Sherwsbury the ſonne of <hi>Iohn Talbot</hi> the firſt Earle of <hi>Shrewesbury</hi> of that name, poſſeſſed the place of the Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England</hi> in the 35. and 36. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and then gave place to the Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi> This Earle was ſlaine at the battle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> in the 38. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1460. He married <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iames Butler</hi> Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and had iſſue <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewesbury, Iames Gilbert, Chriſtopher,</hi> and <hi>George, Anne</hi> married to Sir <hi>Henry Vernon,</hi> and <hi>Margaret,</hi> This man was buried in the <hi>Priory</hi> of <hi>Workſop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iames Butler,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth of that name, Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> was the ſecond time made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> about the 37. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, in which office he continued (as I ſuppoſe) in the 38. yeare of the ſaid King, In which yeare hee conveyed himſelfe out of <hi>England</hi> into <hi>Duchland,</hi> (for feare of the Nobility, as the Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> and others, that rebelled againſt the King) ſending backe his ſouldiers into <hi>England,</hi> which he had before aſſembled upon the Sea, but after he returned into <hi>England,</hi> and was againe put to flight at <hi>Mortimers</hi> Croſſe, by <hi>Edward</hi> Earle of <hi>March,</hi> after King, by the name of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth. He was made Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> in the 39. of <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:15042:79"/>
the ſixt, being his laſt yeare. Hee married <hi>Elinor,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Edmund</hi> Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> &amp; diep without yſſue, being beheaded at <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1461. in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> Viſcount <hi>Bourchier,</hi> was Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> the ſecond time, in the 39. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1460. who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the depoſition of the ſaid King, by <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, was alſo removed from the ſaid office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thrmas Bourchier,</hi> made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>An-Dom.</hi> 1461. continued not long in that office, but gave place to <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Tiptoft</hi> Earle of <hi>Worcester,</hi> the ſecond tyme poſſeſſed the place of the Lord Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England</hi> in the ſecond and third yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edmund</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Ruthine,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Ruthine,</hi> did enjoy the office of Lord Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England,</hi> in the fourth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1464. This man ſecretly in heart forſaking the part of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, for injuries received at his hands ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, and was the chiefe meanes whereby hee attained the Crowne, in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas Tearme in the ſaid fourth yeare of this
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15042:80"/>
King, there was a Sergeants feaſt held in <hi>Holbourne</hi> in the Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> his Houſe, to which the Maior and Aldermen repaired being bidden thither. But when the Major looked to have kept the ſtate in the Hall, forgetting that hee was out of his owne liberties (for the Biſhops place was an exempt place) as it had beene uſed (ſaith <hi>Iohn Stow</hi>) in all places of the City, and liberties of the ſame, out of the Kings preſence, the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Ruthine</hi> then Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> unknowne to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, and againſt their willes (as they ſaid) was placed in the higheſt roome, whereupon the Major Aldermen and Commons departed. This <hi>Edmund</hi> doth <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> in the life of <hi>Thomas Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chier</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> make to be Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer in the Third yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1463. which may well enough ſtand with the former, being Treaſurer to <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in the 3. yeare of the King. For upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of the ſaid Earle in the 3. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. came this Lord <hi>Grey</hi> in place. The words of which ſaid <hi>Matthew Parker</hi> (with a note of <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1463. in the margent) are in this order: <hi>Edwardus Rex duobus jam annis faeliciter geſto regno, parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Weſt monaſterij tenuit, quo etiam tempore, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopus</hi> (which was <hi>Thomas Bourchier,</hi> the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Henry Bourchier</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex) &amp; Clerus in ſynodo convenerunt. In hac ſynodo Iohannes Comes Wigorniae, Henricus Comes Eſſexiae, &amp; D. Edmun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Grey Theſaurarius Angliae, D. Humfridus Cromwell, D. Wenlocke, D. Iohannes Prior ſancti Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis &amp; Robertus Stillington Legum doctor, cuſtos
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15042:80"/>
privati ſigilli regis conſiliarij, allatis literis regijs petierunt a clero decerni regi ad Scotos repellendos ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidium. Quod quidem gratiſsimis omnium animis tam munifico regi conceſſum eſt, qui ſuperiori anno eccleſiae immunitates atque jura iniquis judiciorum calumnijs (uti in Iohanne Stafford antea diximus) convulſa &amp; labefactata diplomate regio reſtauravit.</hi> Beſides which thus writeth <hi>Iohn Whethamſtead,</hi> that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Abbat of Saint <hi>Albons</hi> of this Lord <hi>Grey,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring in what authority he was at firſt, in the daies of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, and then in the raigne of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, His words be theſe. In the 36. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Venerunt tres viri monachi de cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobio Cluniacenſi, quibus ad audiendum eorum nunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, miſsi ſunt epiſcopus Dunelmenſis, cuſtos privati ſigilli, Dominus Edmondus Grey de Ruthine, &amp; Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarius regis, quibus iſti viri dixerunt, eorum adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſſe ob tria. Primo ad aperiendum quomodo reges Angliae, &amp; praecipue Henricus ſecundus fuerunt tam magni benefactores ad eorum eccleſiam ut potius pro nunc dicatur earum patronus &amp; praecipuus funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Secundo venerunt ad petendum poſſeſsionem &amp; confirmationem bonorum illorum quae dicti progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores eis contulerant, &amp; per tempus non paucum jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dudum a manibus eorum detenta &amp; diſtracta erant. Tertio ad impetrandum liberam licentiam ad ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum ſingula loca religioſa ob eorum caenobio depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, &amp; quae per nobiles progenitores reges poſita fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt ſub eorum regimime. Sed nihil hic eis gratum fuit actum, itu at tristes diſcederunt.</hi> Out of which words of <hi>Whethamsted,</hi> may other things bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, beſides the doings of the Lord <hi>Grey,</hi> as that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15042:81"/>
the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and ſpecially <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, have been great benefactors and founders of the <hi>Charterhouſe Monkes,</hi> with many moe matters contained in the ſame, which I referre to the wiſe &amp; learned reader, which made me the willinger to ſet down his words ſo largely; Moreover the ſame <hi>Whethamsted,</hi> continuing the Hiſtorie of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, writeth of the battle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> wherein was this Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> in this ſort. <hi>In praelio Northamptonenſi Edmundus Grey, dominus Ruthine, corpore licet praeſens</hi> (even as the Lord <hi>Stanly</hi> was in the battell fought betwixt <hi>Richard</hi> the third, and <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> after King, by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh) <hi>in campi domini regis Henrici Sexti ſteterat, cor tamen ejus non erat rectum in eo, neque omnino fidelis habitus aut inventus fuit. Nam venientibus turmis dictis ad foſſam circumvallationis &amp; ipſam non multum prompte propter elevationem ver ticis in parte ulteriore aſcendere valentibus, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit ipſis dominus cum ſuis copijs obvians, porrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ipſis dextran, traxit eos per manus in campum Martium, juxta votum ſuum.</hi> Thus much <hi>Whetham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> of <hi>Edmond Grey</hi> Lord <hi>Ruthine,</hi> who was made Earle of <hi>Kent,</hi> in the fifth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1464.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Edmond Grey</hi> being Lord <hi>Haſtings, Weiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and <hi>Ruthine,</hi> (before he had the honour of this Earledome) did by his Deed of Indenture dated the eighteenth of <hi>November</hi> in the 25. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1446. give to <hi>Iohn Pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke</hi> Prior of <hi>Duffefield</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> in <hi>Almes,</hi> during the life of the ſaid Prior, his Feild
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15042:81"/>
called <hi>Challocke,</hi> to keepe the obits of Sir <hi>Iohn Grey,</hi> father to the ſaid Sir <hi>Edmond,</hi> and of Dame <hi>Conſtance</hi> the widow of the Earle Marſhall, and daughter of <hi>Iohn Holland</hi> Duke of <hi>Exceſter</hi> and Earle of <hi>Huntington,</hi> mother to the ſaid Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> with maſſe, &amp;c. as ſuch other Collects, as the ſaid <hi>Edmond</hi> ſhould deliver unto the ſaid Prior.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Walter Blunt</hi> Knight, who was the firſt Lord <hi>Montjoy,</hi> poſſeſſed the place of Lord Treaſurerſhip of <hi>England,</hi> in the fifth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, which fell in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1465. Of this man is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made in the Booke of the Law called <hi>Long Quinto</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth; Hee married the daughter of Sir <hi>Iohn Biron,</hi> and had yſſue <hi>William, Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Iames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Woodvile</hi> Knight Chamberlaine to the King, and Conſtable of <hi>England,</hi> was made Barron on the ninth of <hi>May</hi> in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1424. and was after created Earle of <hi>Rivers</hi> in the fift yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1465. who thus advanced, was after Lord Treaſurer in the 6. 7. and 8. of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth. In which 8. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, <hi>Thomas Cooke,</hi> late Major of <hi>London</hi> was accuſed of Treaſon, and arraigned for the ſame, who after he had beene many times purged theref, was yet at laſt found guilty, and by this Lord <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> then Lord Treaſurer ſo handled, as that hee could not be delivered, untill hee had paid 8000. pound to the king, and 800. pound to the Queene.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15042:82"/>
This Lord Treaſurer married <hi>Iaquet,</hi> the widow of <hi>Iohn Duke</hi> of <hi>Bedford,</hi> daughter to <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenburgh</hi> Earle of Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> by whom hee had yſſue, <hi>Richard</hi> Earle <hi>Rivers, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Scales</hi> in the right of his wife, <hi>Edward Woodvile</hi> Knight ſlaine at the battell of Saint <hi>Albine</hi> in <hi>Britaine</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he third yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, <hi>Lionell</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Salisbury, Margaret</hi> married to <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundale, Margaret</hi> married to <hi>William Herbert,</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntington, Anna</hi> firſt married to <hi>William Bourchier</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and after to <hi>George Gray</hi> Earle of <hi>Kent, Iaquet</hi> married to <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Strange, Elizabeth</hi> married to Sir <hi>Iohn Greie</hi> youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſon to the Lord <hi>Greie</hi> of <hi>Ruthine,</hi> and after the death of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Greie,</hi> to King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Katherine</hi> married to <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham;</hi> Beſides all which I have read of one <hi>Iohn,</hi> which was ſonne to this Earle <hi>Rivers,</hi> which <hi>Iohn</hi> married the old Dutcheſſe of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and was beheaded with his father, the truth wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I leave to further triall. This <hi>Richard</hi> Earle <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> Lord Treaſurer in the ninth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1469. was by <hi>Robert Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard,</hi> who named himſelfe <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Kideſdale,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the forreſt of <hi>Deane,</hi> (as ſome have) others ſay at <hi>Grafton,</hi> and from thence brought to <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton</hi> and there was beheaded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Longſtrother</hi> Prior of Saint <hi>Iohns Ieruſalem</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> poſſeſſed the place of Lord Treaſurer of the Realme in the ninth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1469. for in the ſame yeare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15042:82"/>
hee gave place to the Biſhop of <hi>Elie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Grey,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Elie</hi> was after the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Thomas Bourchier</hi> from <hi>Elie</hi> to <hi>Canterbury</hi> advanced to that See, by <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fifth, then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who gave it to the ſaid Biſhop, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then procurator too for King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. at <hi>Rome</hi> in the yeare of our redemption, 1454. This man was Lord Treaſurer in the ninth yeare of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1469. in which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he continued untill the 11. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, or thereabouts. This <hi>Greie</hi> was borne of the noble houſe of the Lord <hi>Greyes</hi> of <hi>Codnor,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Bale,</hi> and travelled into <hi>Italie</hi> to attaine great learning, where he heard the noble Clerke <hi>Guari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Veronenſis</hi> reade in <hi>Ferraria.</hi> Hee continued Biſhop of <hi>Elie</hi> 24. yeares 11. Moneths and two daies, departing this life at <hi>Durham</hi> the fourth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1478. as I have read, and was buried at <hi>Elie,</hi> betweene two Marble pillars, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beſtowed great ſommes of money upon the reparations of that famous Belfrie of the Church of <hi>Elie,</hi> and upon other ornaments of the ſame Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Bourchier</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſxe,</hi> did the third time poſſeſſe the honorable place of the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurerſhip of <hi>England</hi> in the 11. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in which office hee continued (as I gather) 12. yeares, being all the reſidue of the life of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth, who departed this world, about the ninth day of <hi>Aprill</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1483. which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15042:83"/>
               <hi>Bourchier</hi> being made Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1461. married <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> daughter of <hi>Richard de Conis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge</hi> Earle of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> by whom hee had yſſue <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Bourchier, Thomas, Iohn, Henry,</hi> and <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phery,</hi> Knights.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Richard Wood</hi> Knight, whom ſome call Sir <hi>Iohn Wood,</hi> being before under Treaſurer in the 23. yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, was in the ſame yeare made Knight about a Moneth before the death of the ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth. This man did poſſeſſe the place of the Lord Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (as I gather out of the record of <hi>Pellis exitus,</hi> of that yeare) in the ſecond yeare of the Raigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, being the yeare of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption 1484. which office I ſuppoſe, that hee kept untill the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> the third was ſlayne, by <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> afterward King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Reignold Brey</hi> Knight, the ſonne of <hi>Richard Brey</hi> Phyſician (as ſome have noted to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt) being ſervant to <hi>Margret</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Richmond</hi> mother to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, was for the fidelity of his Lady, and good ſervice in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. to the Crowne received into great favour with the ſaid King, and made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> as appeareth by the record of <hi>Pellis exitus,</hi> made under his name in the firſt yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1485.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15042:83"/>
beſides which Office, hee had many other offices and honours, part whereof were that he was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of the Kinges warres, that he was one of the executors to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, that hee was made Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> at the Coronation of the King, and created a Banneret at Blacke-heath field. Hee died in the 18. yeare of the <hi>prudent Prince.</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, being in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1503. and was honorably buried at <hi>Windſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Dinham</hi> Kinght, the ſon of Sir <hi>Dinham</hi> Knight, a faithfull ſervant to the houſe of <hi>Yorke,</hi> aſwell in ayding the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> to whom <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, ſonne to the ſaid Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> in the ſecond yeare of his raigne, had given one Annuity of 30. pound <hi>per Annum;</hi> did after the death of the ſaid <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth in the ſecond yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh poſſeſſe the place of Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1486. and ſo continued vntill in <hi>An.</hi> 16. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, and then gave place to <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Surrey.</hi> Of which Lord <hi>Dinham</hi> thus writeth, <hi>Leland. Dominus Dinham primus fuit fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dator ſancti Nicholas alias Hortland,</hi> He was created Lord <hi>Dinham</hi> in the firſt yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the 4. ſhortly after the Coronation of the ſaid King in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1461. He dyed in <hi>Anno</hi> 16. of the ſame King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1500. and the 30. day of <hi>Ianuary</hi> was brought to the <hi>Gray Fryers</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and there buried. He married <hi>Elizabeth</hi> daughter of the Lord <hi>Fitzwater,</hi> by whom he had yſſue <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Phillip,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Dinham</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:15042:84"/>
his baſe ſonne that married one of the daughters and heires of Sir <hi>Iohn Ormond:</hi> Which <hi>Thomas</hi> was buried at <hi>Aſhring,</hi> Three miles from <hi>Berkham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,</hi> beſides which children, this Lord <hi>Dinham</hi> or <hi>Denham</hi> (for ſo I finde both written in Chronicles) had by his legitimate wife divers daughters, which were <hi>Margaret</hi> married to <hi>Nicholas</hi> Baron of <hi>Carew Ioane</hi> married to the Lord <hi>Zouch, Elizabeth</hi> marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord <hi>Fitz Warren,</hi> and <hi>Katherine</hi> married to Sir <hi>Thomas Arundell</hi> of <hi>Cornewall</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>Here I thinke it not amiſſe to ſay ſomewhat of a note which I have ſeene, that maketh <hi>Iohn Touchet</hi> Lord <hi>Audley</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> which note is this. <hi>Iohn Touchet</hi> Lord <hi>Audley</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> dyed the 26. day of <hi>December</hi> in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1490. falling in the ſixt yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, and had iſſue <hi>Iames</hi> Lord <hi>Audley,</hi> beheaded the 28. of <hi>Iune</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1497. being the 12. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> created the firſt Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi> of that name (in the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third) was at the ſame time alſo created Earle of <hi>Surrey.</hi> This man after the ſlaughter of his father at <hi>Boſworth field,</hi> when the Tyrant <hi>Richard</hi> the third was ſlaine by <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, was after received into ſuch favour with the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, that hee was advanced to be Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> in the 16. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1500. Which place hee continued all the life of the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, who died in the 24. yeare
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15042:84"/>
of his raigne, being in <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1509. After which for the good ſervice hee uſed in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. permitted him to keepe that Office, which he poſſeſſed untill the 15. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1523. This man was created Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi> on <hi>Candlemas day</hi> in the fift yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1513. at what time alſo his ſonne <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> was made Earle of <hi>Surrey.</hi> This Duke was advanced to that honour, in recompence of the death of the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> and for the good ſervice that hee did againſt that Nation in the ſaid 5. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. with an augmentation of his armes: the Armes of <hi>Scotland, in medio benda Armorum proprij Nominis</hi> of <hi>Howard.</hi> Touching which victory of the death of the King of <hi>Scots. Buchanan, Lib.</hi> 13. writeth to this effect. That the ſaid <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> (as a note of the conqueſt) gave to his ſervants (to weare on their left arme) being a white Lyon (the beaſt which he beare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the proper Enſigne of that houſe) ſtanding over a Red Lion, the peculiar note of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland</hi>) and tearing the ſame Red Lyon with his pawes. This <hi>Tho.</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried two wives, his firſt wife was <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the daughter of <hi>Fredericke Tilney</hi> Knight, by whom he had iſſue <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Surrey,</hi> after Duke of <hi>Norfolk, Edward</hi> ſlaine at <hi>Breſt</hi> Admiral of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Edmond Howard,</hi> with <hi>Elizabeth</hi> married to <hi>Thomas Bulline</hi> Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and <hi>Muriell</hi> married to <hi>Iohn Grey</hi> Lord <hi>Liſle:</hi> His ſecond wife was <hi>Agnes</hi> daughter of <hi>Philip Tilney</hi> Knight, by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15042:85"/>
whom he had yſſue <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingham</hi> with many others. This <hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi> died in the 16. yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1544. and was buried at <hi>Thetford</hi> in <hi>Norfolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> ſonne to the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> being Earle of <hi>Surrey</hi> poſſeſſed the place of the Lord Treaſurer in the 15. yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1523. the which office he continued in the 38. yeare of the ſaid King, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1546. in the which yeare on the 28. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> the ſaid King <hi>Henry</hi> died, ſo that this Duke and his father were Lord Treaſurers of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> almoſt 48. yeares: But about ſome few daies more then a Moneth before the death of the ſaid King, that is to ſay, on the 12. day of <hi>December,</hi> this Duke with his ſonne <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Surrey</hi> were committed to the Tower, the one by water, the other by land. Shortly after which, the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> was beheaded at <hi>Tower-hill</hi> the 19. day of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> about 9. dayes before the death of the King. And the Duke remained as condemned to perpetuall priſon, till the beginning of the Raigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> who then ſet him at liberty: He married for his firſt wife <hi>Anne</hi> the daughter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, but had <hi>Thomas</hi> that died young after, he married <hi>Elizabeth</hi> daughter to <hi>Edward</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> by whom hee had yſſue <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Surrey</hi> beheaded as before, <hi>Thomas Viſcount Bindon</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> married to <hi>Henry Fitzroy</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> Hee died about
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15042:85"/>
the beginning of the Raigne of Queene <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward Seymer</hi> Earle of <hi>Hartford</hi> was after the death of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> in the firſt yeare of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1546. in which yeare hee was alſo made protector of <hi>England</hi> and Duke of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet,</hi> of whom thus writeth <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> calling him <hi>Regni Camerarium,</hi> in the life of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cranmer</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in theſe words, pag. 397. <hi>In teſtamento</hi> (meaning King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8.) <hi>Edwardo Principi minori novem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis nato haeredi ſuo Sexdecem tutores, ex Epiſcopis ſolos Thomam Cranmerum Cantuarienſem archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum &amp; Cuthbertum Tonſtallum Dunelmenſem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum dedit.</hi> And a little after, pag. 398. fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>Verum pluribus (ut diximus (ei minori)</hi> (that was King <hi>Edward) a patre conſtitutis curatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ne numero ſuo, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> multitudine ad diſſentiones faciles eſſent &amp; proclives, unus electus eſt, qui ex conſilijs reliquorum impuberis regis tutelam ſolus adminiſtraret: Is futit Edwardus Seimerus Comes He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refordienſis totius regni Camerarius regiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Auuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. Qui ſuſcepta tutela regis, totius regni atque do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniorum ſuorum proctteor &amp; Somerſeti Dux nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> creatus eſt.</hi> This Duke of <hi>Somerſet</hi> being Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> continued in the ſame office (untill his death which was) more then 4. yeares, and was beheaded in the fift yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1551.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:15042:86"/>Sir <hi>William Paulet</hi> Knight Marqueſſe of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> was made Lord Treaſurer, upon the death of the Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> in the fift yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1551. Which office hee kept by the ſpace of Twenty yeares and more, a longer time then ever any other Treaſurer had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, except the two laſt Dukes of <hi>Norfolke.</hi> This man being a man of extreame age, (as attaining to the yeares Ninetie Seven) died Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> the tenth of <hi>March,</hi> in <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1571. (being the 14. yeare of the Raigne of the famous Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) at his Mannor of <hi>Baſing.</hi> Hee in his life time did ſee the Children of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Children growne to the number of One Hundred and Three; a rare bleſſing of God to men of his calling. He maried <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the daughter of Sir <hi>William Capell</hi> Knight, by whom he had iſſue, <hi>Iohn</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Wincheſter, Thomas, Chidiocke,</hi> and <hi>Giles, Alice</hi> married to <hi>Richard Stowell, Margaret</hi> married to Sir <hi>William Berkeley, Margery</hi> married to <hi>Richard Waller,</hi> and <hi>Eleanor</hi> married to Sir <hi>Richard Perckſhall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Cecill</hi> Knight, principall Secretary of State, created Lord <hi>Burghley,</hi> upon the death of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> was made Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England</hi> the 13. <hi>Iuly</hi> 1572. being in the 14. yeare of the reigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in that office during his life, being alſo (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected unto that moſt noble Order of the Garter. Chancellor of the Vniverſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and a Commiſſioner for the Office of Earle Marſhall of of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:15042:86"/>
               <hi>Thomas Sackvill</hi> Barron <hi>Buckhurſt,</hi> heire Male of that ancient Familie that have flouriſhed in a continued ſeries from the Conqueſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming over out of <hi>Normandie,</hi> deſerved Nobly in that action was made Lord Treaſurer the 15. of <hi>May</hi> in the 41. yeare of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and continued in that office during his life: Hee was after by King <hi>Iames</hi> Created Earle of <hi>Dorcet</hi> the 13. of <hi>March</hi> 1603. being Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Garter, and Chancellor of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert Cecill</hi> ſecond ſon to <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghley,</hi> being Principal Secretary of State to Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and after to King <hi>Iames,</hi> was by the ſaid king created Baron <hi>Cecill</hi> of <hi>Eſſendon</hi> the 13. of <hi>May</hi> 1603. vicount <hi>Cranborne</hi> the 20. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1604. and Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> the 4. of <hi>May</hi> in the ſixt yeare of King <hi>Iames,</hi> and upon the death of the Earle of <hi>Dorcet</hi> hee was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and continued in the place till his death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Walden</hi> (ſecond ſonne to <hi>Thomos Howard</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke</hi>) created Earle of <hi>Suffolke</hi> by King <hi>Iames,</hi> being then Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine and Knight of the Garter, was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> the 12. of <hi>Iuly</hi> in the 12. yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Iames.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Montague</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of the Kings Bench, was made Lord Treaſurer of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15042:87"/>
               <hi>England</hi> the 14. of <hi>December</hi> in the 18. yeare of King <hi>Iames,</hi> and the 19. day of the ſame moneth and yeare he was Created Baron of <hi>Kimolten Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> in <hi>Huntington-ſhire,</hi> and Vicount <hi>Mandevile,</hi> and immediately after the Coronation of King <hi>Charles</hi> he was created Earle of <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lyonell</hi> Lord <hi>Cranfield</hi> of <hi>Cranfield</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Bedford,</hi> ſo created by Letters Patents, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date the 9. of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1621. was made Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer the 19. of <hi>October</hi> following, and created Earle of <hi>Middleſex</hi> the 19. of <hi>October.</hi> 1622.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iames Ley</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Cheife Iuſtice of the Kings Bench, was made Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England</hi> the 22. of <hi>December</hi> in the 22. yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Iames,</hi> and upon the 31. day of the ſame Moneth he was created Baron <hi>Ley</hi> of <hi>Ley</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and immediately after the Coronation of King <hi>Charles,</hi> he was created Earle of <hi>Marleburgh</hi> in <hi>Wiltsſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> Lord <hi>Weſton</hi> Chancellor of the <hi>Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer,</hi> upon the remove of the Earle of <hi>Marleburgh</hi> was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England</hi> upon the 15. day of <hi>Iuly</hi> in the 4. yeare of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and was after that created Earle of <hi>Portland</hi> in <hi>Dorcet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> by Letters Patents, bearing date the 17. day of <hi>February</hi> in the eighth yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:15042:87"/>Vpon the death of the ſaid Earle of <hi>Portland,</hi> his Majeſtie appointed Commiſſioners for the ſaid office, viz. <hi>William</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> his Grace; <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> Lord Privie Seale; <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Cottington</hi> Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the <hi>Exchequer;</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Cooke,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Windebank</hi> Knights, Principall Secretaries of State.</p>
            <p>The right reverend Father in God <hi>William Iuxon,</hi> firſt Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> then tranſlated to <hi>London</hi> and made deane of the Kings Chappel, and called to be of the Privy Councell, and was made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> the Ninth day of <hi>March,</hi> 1635.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:88"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15042:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
